<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;कवित्वम् on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kavitvam/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;कवित्वम् on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kavitvam/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>प्रक्रिया</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kavitvam/prakriyA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kavitvam/prakriyA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;आदौ विषयग्रहणम्। ततो विशिष्ट-वर्ण्यार्थ-स्फुरणम्।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;पदानि बहुसावधानतया चिनोत्य् उत्तमः।&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;एवं ब्रूते राजारामजशङ्करः। कुन्तकोऽपि कालिदास्यपद्ये कस्मिंश्चित् - &amp;ldquo;एषां प्रत्येकं कश्चिदप्यर्थः शब्दान्तराभिधेयतां नोत्सहते ।&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;अधमा अपर्याप्तप्रतीक्षया पद्यम् उद्गिरन्ति। तेन तेषाम् आत्मवञ्चनम् इवेति राजारामज-शङ्करः - &amp;ldquo;आशुकवितासु साहित्यावधानप्रसङ्गेषु सविवरणापेक्षैः पद्यैश् च विस्मितानां प्रेक्षकाणाम् अभिनन्दनेन वर्धते तद् आत्मवञ्चनम्, कवितापक्वतापेक्षा च ह्रसति +अनाशुपद्येष्व् अपि।&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;छन्दसाद्य्-अनुरोधेन कदाचिद् वर्ण्यार्थपरिवर्तनम् अपि।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>प्रेरणम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kavitvam/preraNAni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kavitvam/preraNAni/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;परयजनम&#34;&gt;प्रयोजनम्&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;काव्यं यशसेऽर्थकृते व्यवहारविदे शिवेतरक्षतये ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;सद्यः परनिर्वृतये कान्तासम्मिततयोपदेशयुजे॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;साधनप्रक्रिया - By communicating experience of mental states of characters.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;कतभद-पररणभद&#34;&gt;कृतिभेदे प्रेरणाभेदः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;शास्त्रेषु &lt;strong&gt;शास्त्रकाव्येषु&lt;/strong&gt; च प्रेरणम् भिन्नम् एवम् भवेत् - &amp;ldquo;न ख्यातिलाभपूजार्थं ग्रन्थोऽस्माभिरुदीर्यते । &lt;strong&gt;स्वबोध-परिशुद्ध्यर्थं&lt;/strong&gt; ब्रह्मविन्-निकषाश्मसु ॥&amp;rdquo; । प्रायेण भैरप्प-विष्णुशर्म-सदृशाः शास्त्रकाव्यकर्तारः।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;मुक्तक-कवनं&lt;/strong&gt; गानं नृत्यम् अपि वा &lt;strong&gt;ऽऽत्मतृप्तय&lt;/strong&gt; उद्भवेत्, किन्तु महाकाव्यनिबन्धनं प्रायेण न तथेति भाति।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;महकवयष&#34;&gt;महाकाव्येषु&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;परम्परायां यशः&lt;/strong&gt;।&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;A poet I think should necessarily bank on posterity. I always compose verses thinking am dead. Contemporaries can like or dislike your poetry for personal reasons. You become more responsible too when you know you are writing a verse for somebody whom you cannot please by any other means&amp;rdquo; इति शङ्करः।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;one must regards people from the past who have achieved this feat (such as Kalidasa) as evaluators of one&amp;rsquo;s poetry. One must almost bring them back to life in one&amp;rsquo;s imagination and converse with them in all simplicity without guile. I think if done sincerely, such great poets of the past can surely come to our aid and tell us if we are treading the correct path&amp;rdquo; इति शङ्करः।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;गोष्टिप्रोत्साहनम्&lt;/strong&gt; -&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;It does help to know others who are also interested in the sort of poetry one is interested in. One cannot always evaluate the standard of one&amp;rsquo;s poetry. Further, one is motivated more by the fact that others are also writing. This may hold good for writing muktakas.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;अस्य सीमा त्वैवम् - यथा वदति शङ्करः - &amp;ldquo;Something like this: when you climb a small hill in your locality, you are likely to be joined by many people who can guide you and whom you may guide on the way. But when you decide to climb the tallest mountain in the world, you most likely have to do it alone. The world may not be capable of offering you any helpful inputs because it is as yet unprepared for such a feat&amp;hellip; In the case of muktakas, there is not the sort of waiting period that a MahAkAvya expects. There is greater uncertainty in a Mahakavya - we are not sure how the work may shape itself. Often a single verse of a Mahakavya may not create as great an impact as a muktaka but cumulatively the MahAkAvya must far exceed the muktaka in its impact. But since there is uncertainty and no immediate positive response from readers ( because the poet may share one verse only at a time and it might not be read in its full context) the poet has to motivate himself/herself without foreseeing any immediate benefit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;साम्प्रत-प्रभावः&lt;/strong&gt; - &amp;ldquo;A poet may certainly feel an inner urge to create poetry, but most poets would not have gone very far unless they felt that there was a demand for their works amongst people around them. A poet banks on posterity for appreciation only when he fails to draw the attention of contemporaries.&amp;rdquo; फल्गु-कवय एवम्।&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
