<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Shankar thesis on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Shankar thesis on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>00 Abstract</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/00_abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/00_abstract/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;IV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Shankar. R, NIAS, 2018&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This thesis, titled A Qualitative Approach to the Psychology of Three Self-conscious Emotions from Sanskrit Poetics, represents a coming together of the fields of mainstream contemporary psychology, Indian psychology, emotion studies, Sanskrit poetics, Indian philosophical systems allied to Sanskrit poetics (especially the Samkhya system), and Sanskrit literature to foster an understanding of asūyā, garva, and vrīḍā – three mental states listed, described, and illustrated through vignettes by Sanskrit aestheticians.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>00 Preface</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/00_preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/00_preface/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;VI&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PREFACE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Being a practicing psychiatrist, a votary of the Indian aesthetic theory as propounded by Sanskrit aestheticians of yore, and a Sanskrit poet, I have frequently contemplated on the relevance of poetry and poetics for understanding the mental states of real-world individuals and the possibility of such relevance illuminating therapy sessions, allowing the therapist to not only empathize with the client in the latter’s experience of myriad mental states but also guide him/her in the attainment of greater psychological well-being, one in which the experience of pleasure is maximized and displeasure minimized.+++(4)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>01 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/01_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/01_intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER 1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Introduction&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This thesis adopts a qualitative Indian psychological approach to study three mental states - asūyā, garva, and vrīḍā - that are listed, described, and illustrated through vignettes in Sanskrit poetics. By “Indian psychological approach” is meant an approach to psychology founded on ideas and practices that developed over several centuries in India (Cornelissen, Misra, &amp;amp; Varma, 2011). For more than two millennia, the classical Indian language of Sanskrit has been enriched by the works of several aestheticians. Many among them rearranged existing textual material, some produced commentaries that can aid us in understanding primary texts, yet others critiqued age-old tenets, a few reinterpreted canons on the basis of their own philosophical orientations, a small number of them employed aesthetics as a tool to understand religious doctrine, and a handful came up with path-breaking theories capable of integrating diverse concepts. One important topic which a majority of them, if not all, focused was on the communication by and through literary works of myriad mental states, including emotions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Literature Review</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/02_lit-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/02_lit-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER 2&#xA;2. Literature Review&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;21-an-overview&#34;&gt;2.1 An overview&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the objectives of this thesis is to gain an understanding of three mental states – asūyā, garva, and vrīḍā – that are documented in Sanskrit poetics using an Indian psychological approach. A second objective is to compare and contrast these mental states with their corresponding categories in contemporary psychology, namely, self-conscious emotions such as envy, jealousy, pride, shame, embarrassment, and guilt. Given the interdisciplinary nature of the topic, a review of literature must clearly embrace two broad disciplines: Indian psychology and contemporary Western psychology. It is convenient to begin with a review of literature about self-conscious emotions and related Western psychological concepts before proceeding to review work on analogous concepts from an Indian psychological standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Data and Method</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/03_Data_and_Method/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/03_Data_and_Method/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;31-preamble&#34;&gt;3.1 Preamble&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Reiterating from the literature review, there are no studies that have analyzed asūyā, garva, and vrīḍā – the three mental states (bhāva-s) this thesis focuses on – within an interdisciplinary framework that brings together contemporary psychology and traditional Sanskrit poetics. An important objective of this study is to gain an understanding of the concepts that underlie three mental states - asūyā, garva, and vrīḍā – documented in Sanskrit poetics and thereby contributing to the growing knowledge base of Indian psychology. This is a prerequisite for achieving the second objective, namely, comparing and contrasting the target mental states with their corresponding self-conscious emotions from modern psychology. Towards realizing the above-mentioned objectives, the following two sets of data shall been chosen: (1) textual documentation from Sanskrit poetics and (2) vignette verses that Sanskrit aestheticians quote for the purpose of illustrating mental states such as asūyā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Analysis and Discussion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/04_Analysis_and_Discussion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/04_Analysis_and_Discussion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.1 A recapitulation of data and method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As already elucidated in the previous chapter, the data in this study comprises of (1) textually documented details on asūyā, garva, and vrīḍā and (2) vignette verses that Sanskrit aestheticians supply in order to illustrate the mental states mentioned above. In the present chapter, these two sets of data shall be examined along the following lines: 1)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Grouping textually documented information under the heads of definitions, list of antecedent stimuli and consequent responses, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Conclusion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/05_Conclusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/05_Conclusion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;51-overview-of-the-thesis&#34;&gt;5.1 Overview of the thesis&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Self-conscious emotions, such as envy, jealousy, pride, shame, guilt, and embarrassment, are a class of emotions that require the capacity for self-awareness and the ability to form self-representations. In spite of their late arrival into the field of emotion studies, self-conscious emotions have created a revolution of sorts by distinguishing themselves as different from the &amp;lsquo;basic&amp;rsquo; emotions in several respects. In contrast to contemporary Western psychology, Indian psychology - an approach to psychology based on traditional Indian knowledge systems - has not made significant progress in understanding these emotions. While this sad state of affairs is partly because the study of self-conscious emotions is itself a recent phenomenon, a more pertinent cause is the absence in Indian psychology of coherent models that can explain indigenous psychological constructs (including those corresponding to self-conscious emotions) and their mutual interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/REFERENCES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/shankaraH/thesis/REFERENCES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Primary Sanskrit texts with abbreviations **&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ab.D – &lt;em&gt;Abhinayadarpaṇa&lt;/em&gt; of Nandikeśvara. Ed. and Trans. M. Ghosh. 2nd ed. Calcutta: Firma K. L. Mukhopadhyay, 1957.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A.Bh.2/2 – &lt;em&gt;Abhinavabhāratī&lt;/em&gt; commentary of Abhinavagupta on the &lt;em&gt;Nāṭyaśāstra&lt;/em&gt; of Bharata.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vol. 2. Eds. V. M. Kulkarni &amp;amp; T. Nandi. 2nd ed. Vadodara: Oriental Institute, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A.Bh.2/3 - &lt;em&gt;Abhinavabhāratī&lt;/em&gt; commentary of Abhinavagupta on the &lt;em&gt;Nāṭyaśāstra&lt;/em&gt; of Bharata.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vol. 3. Eds. V. M. Kulkarni &amp;amp; T. Nandi. 2nd ed. Vadodara: Oriental Institute, 2003.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
