<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;बालरामवर्मा on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/bAlarAmavarmA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;बालरामवर्मा on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/bAlarAmavarmA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>बालरामभरतम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/bAlarAmavarmA/bAlarAmabharatam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/bAlarAmavarmA/bAlarAmabharatam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[बालरामभरतम्&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=NDk4MTc0MjkyMDc1NDU1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;——————&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is a matter for extreme gratification for the Royal Family, for Travancore and also for the Department for the Publication of Oriental Manuscripts, Trivandrum, that a treatise on natya, composed by Śrī Bālarāma Varma Maharaja, in the midst of his arduous State duties, is now placed before the public. The work, based as it is on numerous previous authorities, is, in the main, the result of the practical experience of the author on Natya. This publication is therefore all the more important for those interested in the revival of Indian national dance, and especially for the student of Kerala theatre. The science of nātya is defined by the author as &lt;strong&gt;भावरसार्थक्रियाकारित्वं भरतत्वम्&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong&gt; and this definition has been applied to the abhinayas of the various parts of the body, such as anga (head, &amp;amp;c.), upāṅga (eye, &amp;amp;c.) and pratyaṅga (neck, &amp;amp;c). Accepting rāga, tāla and other musical accompaniments as the external means of expressing emotions, the author deals in great detail with the various internal and external gestures, giving definitions and applications to one and all of them. Numerous systems of abhinayas, both internal and external, that had been in vogue in Kerala alone, have also been illustrated, and this is evident from the following lines found at the close of the different sub-sections of the book.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
