<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 WINNING OF FRIENDS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 WINNING OF FRIENDS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Tiger and the Traveller</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/01_Tiger_and_the_Traveller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/01_Tiger_and_the_Traveller/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Thus,&amp;rdquo; replied Speckle-neck: &amp;ldquo;I was pecking about one day in the Deccan forest, and saw an old tiger[^6] sitting newly bathed on the bank of a pool, like a Brahman, and with holy kuskus-grass[^7] in his paws.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Ho! ho! ye travellers,&amp;rsquo; he kept calling out, &amp;rsquo;take this golden bangle!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Presently a covetous fellow passed by and heard him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Ah!&amp;rsquo; thought he, &amp;rsquo;this is a bit of luck—but I must not risk my neck for it either.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Jackal, Deer, and Crow</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/02_Jackal_Deer_and_Crow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/02_Jackal_Deer_and_Crow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Far away in Behar there is a forest called Champak-Grove,[^16] and in it had long lived in much affection a Deer and a Crow. The Deer, roaming unrestrained, happy and fat of carcase, was one day descried by a Jackal. &amp;lsquo;Ho! ho!&amp;rsquo; thought the Jackal on observing him, &amp;lsquo;if I could but get this soft meat for a meal! It might be—if I can only win his confidence,&amp;rsquo; Thus reflecting he approached, and saluted him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Vulture, the Cat, and the Birds</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/03_Vulture_the_Cat_and_the_Birds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/03_Vulture_the_Cat_and_the_Birds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;On the banks of the Ganges there is a cliff called Vulture-Crag, and thereupon grew a great fig-tree.[^17] It was hollow, and within its shelter lived an old Vulture, named Grey-pate, whose hard fortune it was to have lost both eyes and talons. The birds that roosted in the tree made subscriptions from their own store, out of sheer pity for the poor fellow, and by that means he managed to live. One day, when the old birds were gone, Long-ear, the Cat, came there to get a meal of the nestlings; and they, alarmed at perceiving him, set up a chirruping that roused Grey-pate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Dead Game and the Jackal</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/04_Dead_Game_and_the_Jackal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/04_Dead_Game_and_the_Jackal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In a town called &amp;lsquo;Well-to-Dwell&amp;rsquo; there lived a mighty hunter, whose name was &amp;lsquo;Grim-face.&amp;rsquo; Feeling a desire one day for a little venison, he took his bow, and went into the woods; where he soon killed a deer. As he was carrying the deer home, he came upon a wild boar of prodigious proportions. Laying the deer upon the earth, he fixed and discharged an arrow and struck the boar, which instantly rushed upon him with a roar louder than the last thunder,[^29] and ripped the hunter up. He fell like a tree cut by the axe, and lay dead along with the boar, and a snake also, which had been crushed by the feet of the combatants. Not long afterwards, there came that way, in his prowl for food, a Jackal, named &amp;lsquo;Howl o&amp;rsquo; Nights,&amp;rsquo; and cast eyes on the hunter, the deer, the boar, and the snake lying dead together. &amp;lsquo;Aha!&amp;rsquo; said he,&amp;rsquo; what luck! Here&amp;rsquo;s a grand dinner got ready for me! Good fortune can come, I see, as well as ill fortune. Let me think:—the man will be fine pickings for a month; the deer with the boar will last two more; the snake will do for to-morrow; and, as I am very particularly hungry, I will treat myself now to this bit of meat on the bow-horn,&amp;rsquo; So saying, he began to gnaw it asunder, and the bow-string slipping, the bow sprang back, and resolved Howl o&amp;rsquo; Nights into the five elements[^30] by death. That is my story,&amp;rdquo; continued Slow-toes, &amp;ldquo;and its application is for the wise:—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 The Prince and the Wife of the Merchant&#39;s Son</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/05_The_Prince_and_the_Wife_of_the_Merchants_Son/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/05_The_Prince_and_the_Wife_of_the_Merchants_Son/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the country of Kanouj there was a King named Virasena, and he made his son viceroy of a city called Virapoora. The Prince was rich, handsome, and in the bloom of youth. Passing through the streets of his city one day, he observed a very lovely woman, whose name was Lávanyavati—i.e., the Beautiful—the wife of a merchant&amp;rsquo;s son. On reaching his palace, full of her charms and of passionate admiration for them, he despatched a message to her, and a letter, by a female attendant:—who wonders at it?—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Old Jackal and the Elephant</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/06_Old_Jackal_and_the_Elephant/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/01_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/06_Old_Jackal_and_the_Elephant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the forest of Brahma&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; lived an Elephant, whose name was &amp;lsquo;White-front.&amp;rsquo; The Jackals knew him, and said among themselves, &amp;lsquo;If this great brute would but die, there would be four months&amp;rsquo; food for us, and plenty, out of his carcase.&amp;rsquo; With that an old Jackal stood up, and pledged himself to compass the death of the Elephant by his own wit. Accordingly, he sought for &amp;lsquo;White-front,&amp;rsquo; and, going up to him, he made the reverential prostration of the eight members,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; gravely saluting him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
