<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 THE PARTING OF FRIENDS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 THE PARTING OF FRIENDS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Lion, the Jackals, and the Bull</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/01_Lion_the_Jackals_and_the_Bull/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/01_Lion_the_Jackals_and_the_Bull/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the Deccan there is a city called Golden-town, and a wealthy merchant lived there named Well-to-do. He had abundant means, but as many of his relations were even yet richer, his mind was bent upon outdoing them by gaining more. Enough is never what we have—&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Looking down on lives below them, men of little store are great;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Looking up to higher fortunes, hard to each man seems his fate.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Monkey and the Wedge</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/02_Monkey_and_the_Wedge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/02_Monkey_and_the_Wedge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In South Behar, close by the retreat of Dhurmma,[^5] there was an open plot of ground, upon which a temple was in course of erection, under the management of a man of the Káyeth caste,[^6] named Subhadatta. A carpenter upon the works had partly sawed through a long beam of wood, and wedged it open, and was gone away, leaving the wedge fixed. Shortly afterwards a large herd of monkeys came frolicking that way, and one of their number, directed doubtless by the Angel of death, got astride the beam, and grasped the wedge, with his tail and lower parts dangling down between the pieces of the wood. Not content with this, in the mischief natural to monkeys, he began to tug at the wedge; till at last it yielded to a great effort and came out; when the wood closed upon him, and jammed him all fast. So perished the monkey, miserably crushed; and I say again—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Washerman&#39;s Jackass</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/03_Washermans_Jackass/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/03_Washermans_Jackass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There was a certain Washerman[^7] at Benares, whose name was Carpúrapataka, and he had an Ass and a Dog in his courtyard; the first tethered, and the last roaming loose. Once on a time, when he had been spending his morning in the society of his wife, whom he had just married, and had fallen to sleep in her arms, a robber entered the house, and began to carry off his goods. The Ass observed the occupation of the thief, and was much concerned.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Cat Who Served the Lion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/04_Cat_Who_Served_the_Lion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/04_Cat_Who_Served_the_Lion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Far away in the North,[^10] on a mountain named &amp;lsquo;Thousand-Crags,&amp;rsquo; there lived a lion called &amp;lsquo;Mighty-heart&amp;rsquo;; and he was much annoyed by a certain mouse, who made a custom of nibbling his mane while he lay asleep in his den. The Lion would wake in a great rage at finding the ends of his magnificent mane made ragged, but the little mouse ran into his hole, and he could never catch it. After much consideration he went down to a village, and got a Cat named Curd-ear to come to his cave with much persuasion. He kept the Cat royally on all kinds of dainties, and slept comfortably without having his mane nibbled, as the mouse would now never venture out. Whenever the Lion heard the mouse scratching about, that was always a signal for regaling the Cat in a most distinguished style. But one day, the wretched mouse being nearly starved, he took courage to creep timidly from his hole, and was directly pounced upon by Curd-ear and killed. After that the Lion heard no more of the mouse, and quite left off his regular entertainments of the Cat. No!&amp;rdquo; concluded Damanaka, &amp;ldquo;we will keep our mouse alive for his Majesty.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Terrible Bell</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/05_Terrible_Bell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/05_Terrible_Bell/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A goblin, your Majesty,&amp;rdquo; responded Damanaka, &amp;ldquo;it seemed so, at least, to the good people of Brahmapoora. A thief had stolen a bell from the city, and was making off with that plunder, and more, into the Sri-parvata hills, when he was killed by a tiger. The bell lay in the jungle till some monkeys picked it up, and amused themselves by constantly ringing it. The townspeople found the bones of the man, and heard the noise of the bell all about the hills; so they gave out that there was a terrible devil there, whose ears rang like bells as he swung them about, and whose delight was to devour men. Every one, accordingly, was leaving the town, when a peasant woman named Karála, who liked belief the better for a little proof, came to the Rajah.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Prince and the Procuress</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/06_Prince_and_the_Procuress/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/06_Prince_and_the_Procuress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the city of &amp;lsquo;Golden-Streets&amp;rsquo; there reigned a valorous King, named Vira-vikrama, whose officer of justice was one day taking away to punishment a certain Barber, when he was stopped by a strolling mendicant, who held him by the skirts, and cried out, &amp;lsquo;Punish not this man—punish them that do wrong of their own knowledge.&amp;rsquo; Being asked his meaning, he recited the foregoing verses, and, being still further questioned, he told this story—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Black Snake and the Golden Chain</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/07_Black_Snake_and_the_Golden_Chain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/07_Black_Snake_and_the_Golden_Chain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A pair of Crows had their abode in a certain tree, the hollow of which was occupied by a black snake, who had often devoured their young. The Hen-bird, finding herself breeding again, thus addressed her mate: &amp;lsquo;Husband, we must leave this tree; we shall never rear young ones while this black snake lives here! You know the saw—&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;From false friends that breed thee strife,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;From a house with serpents rife,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Saucy slaves and brawling wife—&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Get thee out, to save thy life.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Lion and the Old Hare</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/08_Lion_and_the_Old_Hare/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/08_Lion_and_the_Old_Hare/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;On the Mandara mountain there lived a Lion named Fierce-of-heart, and he was perpetually making massacre of all the wild animals. The thing grew so bad that the beasts held a public meeting, and drew up a respectful remonstrance to the Lion in these words:—&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wherefore should your Majesty thus make carnage of us all? If it may please you, we ourselves will daily furnish a beast for your Majesty&amp;rsquo;s meal.&amp;rdquo; The Lion responded, &amp;ldquo;If that arrangement is more agreeable to you, be it so&amp;rdquo;; and from that time a beast was allotted to him daily, and daily devoured. One day it came to the turn of an old hare to supply the royal table, who reflected to himself as he walked along, &amp;ldquo;I can but die, and I will go to my death leisurely.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Wagtail and the Sea</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/09_Wagtail_and_the_Sea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/02_THE_PARTING_OF_FRIENDS/09_Wagtail_and_the_Sea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;On the shore of the Southern Sea there dwelt a pair of Wagtails. The Hen-bird was about to lay, and thus addressed her mate:—&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Husband, we must look about for a fit place to lay my eggs.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;My dear,&amp;rsquo; replied the Cock-bird, &amp;lsquo;will not this spot do?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;This spot!&amp;rsquo; exclaimed the Hen; &amp;lsquo;why, the tide overflows it.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Good dame,&amp;rsquo; said the Cock, &amp;lsquo;am I so pitiful a fellow that the Sea will venture to wash the eggs out of my nest?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
