<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;कृष्णस्वामी on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sangrahaH/kRShNasvAmI/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;कृष्णस्वामी on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sangrahaH/kRShNasvAmI/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>आर्यचरित्रम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sangrahaH/kRShNasvAmI/Aryacharitram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sangrahaH/kRShNasvAmI/Aryacharitram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[आर्यचरित्रम्&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=MjczOTEzNTA2Mjc2Nzk1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PREFACE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;MISSING_FIG href=&amp;quot;../../../../../books_images/U-IMG-1701084542aaaaaa.png&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;MISSING_FIG href=&amp;quot;../../../../../books_images/U-IMG-1700717412aaaaaa.png&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;HE following stories of ancient India have been taken from the two great epics of this country and some of the principal &lt;em&gt;puranas.&lt;/em&gt; They aretold in the words of the authors themselves, sometimes as they are narrated in the ancient books and occasionally with omissions where the narrative was unduly long or required compression. In the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana,&lt;/em&gt; apart from the main story which has been a source of solace to millions in the land, there are few anecdotes of sufficient importance to interest and instruct the reader. It will be scarcely consistent with the object of this publication to issue a collection of Aryan stories without giving a place to the story of that great epic which has moulded the lives and guided the aspirations of hundreds of generations in this vast continent. A modern composition giving the story of that poem within the limits of a few pages can never possess the charm or command the authority of Valmiki&amp;rsquo;s verse. I have decided therefore to include the story of the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; in the language of Valmiki in an abbreviated form, keeping only to the main incidents so that the thousands of young men who complete their school and college education at the present day with no more knowledge of India&amp;rsquo;s greatest epic than they might have gathered on the laps of their grandmothers, might learn to appreciate and admire and treasure in their hearts the lofty morality, the heroic deeds and the sublime poetry that adorn the stately verse of the foremost poet of the land. Hundreds of beautiful passages and innumerable scenes of surpassing loveliness have necessarily been sacrificed in this endeavour to give to the hurried modern world in a brief compass a taste of the splendidproduct of the greatest poetic genius that has yet been born inI&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
