<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;वामनशिवरामआप्टे on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sangrahaH/vAmanashivarAmaApTe/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;वामनशिवरामआप्टे on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sangrahaH/vAmanashivarAmaApTe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>कुसुममाला</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sangrahaH/vAmanashivarAmaApTe/kusumamAlA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sangrahaH/vAmanashivarAmaApTe/kusumamAlA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[कुसुममाला&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=NjQxODczNTM1MTAxNjc2&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;——————————————————————————————————————&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;PUBLISHED BY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;H. P. SHIRALKAR,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;159 Shanwar Peth, Poona City.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;printed at the Chitrashala Press Sadashiv Peth, Poona City&lt;br&gt;&#xA;by S. N. Joshi.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;——————————————————————————————————————&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PREFACE TO THE FIRST EDITION.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;MISSING_FIG href=&amp;quot;../books_images/U-IMG-1735393112Screenshot2024-12-28190749.png&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The following pages have been intended to serve as a reading book for Sanskrit students preparing for the Mrtriculation Examination. They contain about 20 extracts taken from the well-known works of most of the renowned standard Sanskrit writers, beginning with Vâlmîki and ending with Jagannâtha Pandit. The extracts are intended to give the student specimens of different styles and modes of thought, and will be found to display a variety of forms descriptive, moral, didactic, narrative, argumentative, epic, dramatic, lyric &amp;amp;c. Each extract has an intelligible beginning and an end, the subject treated therein being given in English at the commencement, and its source at the end. In selecting passages from different works I have had to abridge or condence them in several gases by leaving out single words or long compounds, or even several sentences or verses, where the omission could be made without impairing the beauty of the original or affecting the context or train of reasoning. It was found necessary to do so to prevent the extracts from being needlessly long, but in some cases even the passages so condensed became rather lengthy, and have, therefore, been divided into Parts,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
