<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;रामवर्मा-कुलशेखरः on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/sangItam/rAmavarmA-kulashekharaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;रामवर्मा-कुलशेखरः on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/sangItam/rAmavarmA-kulashekharaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>कुचेलोपाख्यानम्-अजामिलोपाख्यानं-च</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/sangItam/rAmavarmA-kulashekharaH/kuchelopAkhyAnam-ajAmilopAkhyAnaM-cha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/sangItam/rAmavarmA-kulashekharaH/kuchelopAkhyAnam-ajAmilopAkhyAnaM-cha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[कुचेलोपाख्यानम्-अजामिलोपाख्यानं-च&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=ODIyODM4MjE4NjgwOTM0&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;MISSING_FIG href=&amp;quot;../../../books_images/1688643285.png&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;H. H. Svati Tirunal Sri Rama Varma Kulasekhara Peruma।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Maha Rajah of Travancore 1813 to 1847 A. D.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;of the treatise ‘शं सदालं निदध्यात्’indicates through Mudrālaṅkāra, the date of completion of the work in the Kali Era, (1803875 days from the beginning of that Era) and the date of the author is thus the first part of the 19th century. Historically, this king was the son of Raṇi Lakṣmi Bai and was born in the month of Meṣa in the year 1813 and demised in his 34th year. His father was ŚrīRaja Raja Varma of the Parpa dynasty (Changanacherry) and his mother died in his second year and his maternal aunt ŚrīParvati Bai was the Regent during his minority. Just as the Crescent Moon gathers effulgence through the acquisition of fresh digits, he grew gathering brilliance through his proficiency in all fine arts. His genius and innate aptitude for music and literature, ripened by his education, easily raised him to the position of a great scholar, and poet. This poet was in fact a second creator. He had arare and perfect mastery over various languages such as Malayalam, Sanskrit, Mahratti, English, Telugu, Kaneresc, Tamil and Urdu. His Tutor in English and Politics was Mr. Subba Rao, his future Dewan. And it is most astonishing that the knowledge of the science of Politics proficient in tactics and embellished by exceeding courage, valour and heroism emblazed a heart that was imbued with the sweetest poetical fervour. Such great qualities as serenity, magnanimity, compassion, impartiality and imperiousness illumined his illustrious reign. During the very short period of his life, in the midst of the manifold demands of his kingly office, he attained a unique celebrity as a great man of letters. And his works are:—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
