<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 WAR on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 WAR on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Battle of the Swans and Peacocks</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/01_The_Battle_of_the_Swans_and_Peacocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/01_The_Battle_of_the_Swans_and_Peacocks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the Isle of Camphor there is a lake called &amp;lsquo;Lotus-water,&amp;rsquo; and therein a Swan-Royal, named &amp;lsquo;Silver-sides,&amp;rsquo; had his residence. The birds of the marsh and the mere had elected him King, in full council of all the fowls—for a people with no ruler is like a ship that is without a helmsman. One day King Silver-sides, with his courtiers, was quietly reposing on a couch of well-spread lotus-blossoms, when a Crane, named &amp;lsquo;Long-bill,&amp;rsquo; who had just arrived from foreign parts, entered the presence with an obeisance, and sat down.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Weaver-Birds and the Monkeys</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/02_Weaver-Birds_and_the_Monkeys/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/02_Weaver-Birds_and_the_Monkeys/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In a nullah that leads down to the Nerbudda river there stood a large silk-cotton tree, where a colony of weaver-birds had built their hanging nests,[^4] and lived snugly in them, whatever the weather. It was in the rainy season, when the heavens are overlaid with clouds like indigo-sheets, and a tremendous storm of water was falling. The birds looked out from their nests, and saw some monkeys, shivering and starved with the cold, standing under a tree. &amp;lsquo;Twit! twit! you Monkeys,&amp;rsquo; they began to chirrup. &amp;lsquo;Listen to us!—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Old Hare and the Elephants</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/03_Old_Hare_and_the_Elephants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/03_Old_Hare_and_the_Elephants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Once on a time, very little rain had fallen in the due season; and the Elephants being oppressed with thirst, thus accosted their leader:—&amp;lsquo;Master, how are we to live? The small creatures find something to wash in, but we cannot, and we are half dead in consequence; whither shall we go then, and what shall we do?&amp;rsquo; Upon that the King of the Elephants led them away a little space; and showed them a beautiful pool of crystal water, where they took their ease. Now it chanced that a company of Hares resided on the banks of the pool, and the going and coming of the elephants trampled many of them to death, till one of their number named Hard-head grumbled out, &amp;lsquo;This troop will be coming here to water every day, and every one of our family will be crushed.&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Do not disquiet yourself,&amp;rsquo; said an old buck named Good-speed, &amp;lsquo;I will contrive to avert it,&amp;rsquo; and so saying, he set off, bethinking himself on his way how he should approach and accost a herd of elephants; for,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Heron and the Crow</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/04_Heron_and_the_Crow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/04_Heron_and_the_Crow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;The high-road to Oogein is a very unshaded and sultry one; but there stands upon it one large Peepul-tree,[^9] and therein a Crow and a Heron had their residence together. It was in the hot weather that a tired traveller passed that way, and, for the sake of the shade, he laid his bow and arrows down, and dropped asleep under the tree. Before long the shadow of the tree shifted, and left his face exposed to the glare; which the Heron perceiving, like the kindly bird he was, perched on the Peepul-tree, and spread his wings out so as to cast a shadow on the traveller&amp;rsquo;s face. There the poor fellow, weary with his travel, continued to sleep soundly, and snored away comfortably with open mouth. The sight of his enjoyment was too much for the malevolent Crow, who, perching over him, dropped an unwelcome morsel into the sleeper&amp;rsquo;s mouth, and straightway flew off. The traveller, starting from his slumber, looked about, and, seeing no bird but the Heron, he fitted an arrow and shot him dead. No!&amp;rsquo; concluded the Parrot, &amp;lsquo;I like the society of honest folk.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Appeased Wheelwright</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/05_Appeased_Wheelwright/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/05_Appeased_Wheelwright/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There was a Wheelwright in Shri-nuggur, whose name was &amp;lsquo;Heavy-head,&amp;rsquo; He had good reason to suspect the infidelity of his wife, but he had no absolute proof of it. One day he gave out that he should go to a neighboring town, and he started accordingly; but he went a very little way, and then returning, hid himself in his wife&amp;rsquo;s chamber. She being quite satisfied that he was really gone away, invited her gallant to pass the evening with her, and began to spend it with him in unrestrained freedom. Presently, by chance, she detected the presence of her husband, and her manner instantly changed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Dyed Jackal</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/06_Dyed_Jackal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/06_Dyed_Jackal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Jackal once on a time, as he was prowling about the suburbs of a town, slipped into an indigo-tank; and not being able to get out he laid himself down so as to be taken for dead. The dyer presently coming and finding what seemed a dead Jackal, carried him into the jungle and then flung him away. Left to himself, the Jackal found his natural color changed to a splendid blue. &amp;lsquo;Really,&amp;rsquo; he reflected, &amp;lsquo;I am now of a most magnificent tint; why should I not make it conduce to my elevation?&amp;rsquo; With this view, he assembled the other Jackals, and thus harangued them:—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Faithful Rajpoot</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/07_Faithful_Rajpoot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/03_WAR/07_Faithful_Rajpoot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I will tell you the tale,&amp;rdquo; said the King, &amp;ldquo;as I heard it from &amp;lsquo;Lilyflower,&amp;rsquo; daughter of the Flamingo &amp;lsquo;White-flag,&amp;rsquo; of whom I was once very fond:—A soldier presented himself one morning at King Sudraka&amp;rsquo;s gate, and bade the porter procure an audience for &amp;lsquo;Vira-vara, a Rajpoot,&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; who sought employment. Being admitted to the presence, he thus addressed the King:—&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;If your Highness needs an attendant, behold one!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;What pay do you ask?&amp;rsquo; inquired the King.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
