<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;वेङ्कटमखी on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/sangItam/venkaTamakhI/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;वेङ्कटमखी on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/sangItam/venkaTamakhI/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>चतुर्दण्डीप्रकाशिका</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/sangItam/venkaTamakhI/chaturdaNDIprakAshikA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/sangItam/venkaTamakhI/chaturdaNDIprakAshikA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[चतुर्दण्डीप्रकाशिका&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=NDgzMzUzMDI4NDk4ODM0&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PREFACE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;_____&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; Venkatamakhin ranks high among the writers on Carnatic Music. The system of 72 Melas which is the bedrock on which the science of modern South IndianMusic is built is his creation. His work called the Chaturdandi Prakasika has turned Carnatic Music into the channel in which it now flows. It is therefore unquestionably the most important of the authorities in the science of Music at the present day.&#xA;&#xA; The history of Music as a fine art dates back to the Vedas. Gandharva Vidya is one of the Upavedas and was specially cultivated in connection with Samagana. Indeed, tradition has it that Brahma evolved Music out of the Samaveda. And from very early times several writers have devoted themselves to cultivating the theory of Music. Bharata is the most important of these writers and there were several others of eminence, many of whose works are extant even now in part. It is from these writers that we get some of our fundamental concepts such as Svaras, Srutis, Vadins, Samvadins and so forth. Apart from this, their practical importance at the present day is not considerable. The modern Ragas, the Melas and Janyas and the modern types of composition arelater evolutions though possibly they had their origin in those days.&#xA;&#xA; The medieval history of Music, so to say, begins with Sarngadeva. His work, Sangita Ratnakara, forms a bridge between the ancient and modern periods. On the one hand, his work is a digest of ancient theory; and on the other, it has the beginnings of the modern Raga system. Though the ancestors of Sarngadeva belonged to Kashmir, his family had for two generations settled in Doulatabad in theDeccan, He took special pains to acquaint himself with the South Indian Ragas which deals with in his work. The writers who came after Sarngadeva in the Karnataka country are numerous-Vidyaranya, Ramamatya, Somanatha, Govinda Dikshita and several others. They give the Lakshanas of many Ragas which are current even now, and some of these Lakshanas are useful as guides to us even at the present day. But the more interesting portion of their works is where they seek to give a scientific background to the Ragas. They group Ragas into Melas and Janyas. The number of Melas range from 15 in Vidyaranya to 20 in Ramamatya. But their classification is empirical and not based on any principle.&#xA;&#xA; It is only when we come to Venkatamakhin that we have for the first time a system based on science. He classified the Melas according to their Svaras.. Their number was determined by the possible number of combinations, subject to certain limitations, of the several Svaras, and thus the number of 72 was obtained. Then, he groupedthe various Janya Ragas under the several Melas suitably to their Svaras. Simple as it might now appear, it was left to Venkatamakhin to propound this. Chaturdandi Prakasika which evolved this scheme was written about 1620 A. D. Thereafter this scheme of Melas has ruled unchallenged, and at the present day it is generally accepted and followed.&#xA;&#xA; Among writers who dealt with South Indian Music after Venkatamakhin, special mention must be made of King Tulajaji of Tanjore. He wrote his work called Sangita Saramrita about 1735 A.D. He closely follows Venkatamakhin and one reads with interest his observation that the Melas formulated by Venkatamakhin remained obscure and that therefore he would deal only with the Melas and Ragas which were in actual practice in his own time. Indeed Venkatamakhin himself says that only 19 Melas were actually in use in his time, and that the other Melas had been formulated by him only for scientific completeness, and to provide for Desiya Ragas and Ragas which might be invented in future (Chatur. Chap. 4, stanzas 82 to 86). He himself had invented Simharava. His system would enable musicians of genius to evolve new melodies and it did. Shortly after the time of King Tula- jaji, there were born those three great composers who are regarded as the Trinity of South Indian Music-Tyagay-ya, Muttusvami Dikshita, and Syama Sastrin. The former two, in particular, have in their immortal melodies composed in the new Melas of Venkatamakhin, established not merelythe soundness of Venkatamakhin&#39;s system but have rendered it a matter of scientific necessity of our presentday Music. It is no longer an academic problem. That is why some attempts recently made, as for example by the late Mr. Ponnusvami Pillai of, Madura, to question the necessity for 72 Melas have failed to succeed, because we cannot afford to lose the divine melodies. of Sri Tyagayya and Sri Muttusvami Dikshita in the Ragas sought to be eliminated.&#xA;&#xA; Thus we see that Venkatamakhin is the Panini of of modern Carnatic Music and bis Chaturdandi Prakasika is indispensable to every student thereof. It must be a matter for surprise that this work should not have been published before. There are several reasons which have contributed to this result. All the great scientific treatises down to the time of King Tulajaji of Tanjore were written in Sanskrit and with the decay of Sanskrit knowledge, an exact knowledge of the science also waned. It is difficult to explain how otherwise the works of Ahobala, Ramamatya, Somanatha, Govinda Dikshita, Venkatamakhir, Tulajaji and others remained unknown to the music-knowing public, except by name, until quite recently. It is only now that the Music Academy has been able to publish in the pages of its Journal, the Sangita Sudha of Govinda Dikshita with the aid of practically one manuscript. There is only one manuscript of Sangita Saramrits of King Tulajaji and that too some what incomplete and it is yet to be published. Likewise we have a single manuscript of the Chaturdandi Prakasikaincomplete towards its end, and the present. edition is based thereon.&#xA;&#xA; Secondly, it should not be forgotten that the primary attraction of Music lies in its practice and after the lyrical sweetness of Tyagayya, the classic majesty of Dikshita and the rhythmic concord of Syama Sastrin, the study of the science as such must have been considerably neglected. We know that till recently most of the professionals stopped with acquiring Svara-jnana and did not care to acquire a knowledge of the science and did not possess any notion of the history of the science of Music. Before the days of printing, knowledge of the science was confined to &#39;Sishya Paramparas&#39;. The public at large knew the names of the ordinary Ragas and put all the other Ragas under a comprehensive group - called &#39;Apurva Ragas&#39;. They knew the songs but they had no knowledge of the science unless they were Sanskrit scholars. The &#39;Sishya-pramparas&#39; were jealously preserving the secrets entrusted to them. Sri Tyagayya and Sri Muttusvami Dikshita cultivated the system of Venkatamakhin. In the line of Muttusvami Dikshita, Subbarama Dikshita, his adopted son, himself a composer of no mean attainments and well versed in the science, produced his Sangita Sampradaya Pradarsini, a monumental work based on the tradition of Venkatamakbin. It is that family that has preserved the only manuscript of the Chaturdandi Prakasika that is now available and it is on that version that the present edition is based.&#xA;&#xA; Mr. Bhatkhande of Poona was able to copy from the above manuscript in the possession of Subbarama Dikshita at Ettayapuram, a few chapters and printed them for private circulation only. Now, by the kindness of Brahmasri Muttusvami Dikshita of Ettaya- puram, the son of Subbarama Dikshita and the present representative of the Dikshita line, we are in a position to place the work before the public.&#xA;&#xA; Venkatamakhin wrote two works on Music. One is the Chaturdandi Prakasika and the other deals with Raga Lakshana. In the Chaturdandi Prakasika, we find the fundamental principles enunciated but their practical application was explained in another treatise dealing specially with Ragas and their Lakshanas. In this latter work, Venkatamakhin gave his nomenclature of the 72 Melas and classified the Janya Ragas under the several Melas. He illustrated them by a number of Lakshana Gitas, some of which are printed in the Sangita Sampradaya Pradarsini. No publication of the Chaturdandi Prakasika can give an adequate idea of the contribution of Venkatamakbin to South Indian Music unless the Raga Lakshana and the Lakshana Gitas are also printed and made available to the public. We have accordingly issued in a supplement the Raga Lakshana. We intend publishing the Lakshana Gitas in a separate volume låter. On the life and contribution. of Venkatamakhin, it is. proposed to write more fully in the second volume which will be issued with a translation of the present work. We shall therein discuss in detail the several questions arising on this work&#xA;&#xA; We cannot conclude this preface without expressing our deep sense of gratitude to Brahmasri Muttusvami Dikshita of Ettayapuram for having given us his manuscript of the Chaturdandi Prakasika for publication; to Mr. V. Raghavan, B.A. (Hons.), whose enthusiastic research in Music Literature is responsible for clearing many knotty problems, for his kind suggestions with reference to the Chaturdandi Prakasika and to Mr. K. S. Visvanatha Sastri, Jt. Hony. Secretary of the Music Academy, for seeing the matter through the press.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;विषयसूचिका&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
