<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Part 1 - The Present Work</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Volume II of the Nātyaśāstra (translation) falls into two parts: (1) Chapters XXVIII-XXXIII which are on music in its vocal as well as instrumental aspect and (2) Chapters XXXIV-XXXVI which are on residual matters concerning the production of plays, and the legendary origin of drama (&lt;em&gt;nāṭya&lt;/em&gt;). Though the age of the entire work and other relevant matters have been treated of in the Introduction to the Volume I, the remaining Chapters require some preliminary notes. Naturally the Chapters on music are to be taken up first.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Part 2 - The Ancient Indian Theory and Practice of Music</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-the-indian-conception-of-music&#34;&gt;1. &lt;em&gt;The Indian Conception of Music&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Though music occupied a very important place in the life of Indians of ancient time, one single word such as “Gāndharva” denoting all its different aspects (vocal as well as instrumental) appears only in the middle of the 4th century B.C.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This word occurs in the Jātakas. For according to the Guttila Jātaka (no.243) the legendary Brahmadatta was born in a family of Gandharvas (musicians), and after gaining a great proficiency in the art of music he came to be known as a Gandharva. As this Jātaka mentions playing of a Vīnā, and the two kinds of Mūrchanā&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in this connection, the word Gāndharva in the sense of music may well be pre-Buddhistic. And it is certainly not later than 200 B.C. For it occurs in the Hāthigumphā inscription of Khārvela. In earlier times, &lt;em&gt;gīta&lt;/em&gt; (song) and &lt;em&gt;vādya&lt;/em&gt; (instrumental music) were separately mentioned, or the compound word &lt;em&gt;gītavāditra&lt;/em&gt; (Pali, &lt;em&gt;gītavāditta&lt;/em&gt;) represented music in its totality. But dance and drama (&lt;em&gt;nṛtta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;nṛtya&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;nāṭya&lt;/em&gt;) were very closely associated with music vocal and instrumental, from ancient times, possibly long before the time of Buddha. For &lt;em&gt;prekṣā&lt;/em&gt; (Pali, &lt;em&gt;pekkhā&lt;/em&gt;) was an equivalent of “Nāṭya” which included &lt;em&gt;nṛtta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;gīta&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;vāditra&lt;/em&gt;. Buddha forbade the monks to witness it (&lt;em&gt;pekkha&lt;/em&gt;) as well as the separate performances of &lt;em&gt;nṛtta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;gīta&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;vāditra&lt;/em&gt;. Due to this very close association of the three arts, there came into vogue in about the 3rd century A.C. the word “Saṃgīta” for signifying by means of a single term all the different phases of music including dance. For, according to Indian conception, dance (&lt;em&gt;nṛtta, nṛtya&lt;/em&gt;) owing its origin to rhythm like its vocal and instrumental counterparts, was a kind of music, the vehicle of rhythm in this case being human body with its different limbs. The Nāṭya also depending on &lt;em&gt;nṛtta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;nṛtya&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;abhinaya&lt;/em&gt; (gesture) belonged to the category of dance. Probably these facts led dance especially in its connexion with all kinds of dramatic spectacles, to a substantial union with music.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Part 3 - Literature on Ancient Indian Music</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-early-writers-c-600-bc-200-ac&#34;&gt;1. &lt;em&gt;Early Writers (c&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;600&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;B.C&lt;/em&gt; .—&lt;em&gt;200&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;A.C&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-nārada&#34;&gt;(a) &lt;em&gt;Nārada&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nārada mentioned repeatedly in later literature on music, seems to be the earliest writer on the subject, and the Śikṣā named after him&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; appears, apart from its interpolated passages, to be a very old work, and it may be as old as 600 B.C., and its teachings may be earlier still. As one couplet&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from it has been quoted by Patañjali with a slight variation, it is not later than 200 B.C. Like the Pāṇinīya Śikṣa (c. 600 B.C.) it is written chiefly in the Anuṣṭubh metre; and it treats of musical theories in connexion with the singing of Sāmas. The fact that it describes the Gāndhāra Grāma in detail (together with its Mūrchanās) shows clearly that it is much anterior to the NŚ which ignores altogether this Grāma and was written when they become obsolete. The NŚ quotes the NāŚ. (1.3.13) at least once (XXXIII. 227) without naming it. As this śiksā discusses the seven notes in the three Grāmas and the Mūrchanas and Tānas connected with them, the Indian Music seems to have been pretty advanced at the time when this work was composed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Part 4 - More About the Ancient Indian Theory and Practice of Drama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-the-three-types-of-character&#34;&gt;1. &lt;em&gt;The Three Types of Character&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Characters of all kinds male, female and hermaphrodite in the ancient Indian plays, were classified into three types: superior, inferior and middling&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, for the purpose of distinguishing them by assigning to them special movements to be followed by appropriate music and drumming. Division of Heroes (&lt;em&gt;nāyaka&lt;/em&gt;) and Heroines (&lt;em&gt;nāyikā&lt;/em&gt;) into four classes, had also included the same purpose.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-the-prominent-position-of-the-nāṭaka&#34;&gt;2. &lt;em&gt;The Prominent Position of the Nāṭaka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the very detailed description given in the NŚ of the various types of character such as the king and his entourage, inside and outside the royal palace&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, it appears that the Nāṭaka which usually include such characters, was the most prominent among the ten kinds of play. The special purpose of the description seems to have been to help the playwrights who cannot always be expected to possess a first-hand knowledge of habits and customs of such characters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Part 5 - More Data of India’s Cultural History in the Nāṭyaśāstra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/2/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-language&#34;&gt;1. &lt;em&gt;Language&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The NŚ mentions besides Sanskrit and the various kinds of Prakrit the Ardha-Saṃskṛta as the language of Dhruvās.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; By this last term we are probably to understand the so-called Gāthā-Sanskrit which Prof. Edgerton has called hybrid Sanskrit. His hypothesis about its origin does not however appear to be convincing. This new nomenclature seems to ignore the historical circumstances which brought this kind of language into existence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-metre&#34;&gt;2. &lt;em&gt;Metre&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In course of describing Dhruvās the NŚ has described various metres. Most of these names are otherwise unknown.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
