<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 Notes on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 Notes on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>०० कथामुखम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/00_kathAmukham/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/00_kathAmukham/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;NOTES.&#xA;P. 1. -The title of the whole work in five books composed by Vishnus arman पञ्चतन्त्राणि यस्मिन् शास्त्रे तत् ।&#xA;urg-The Introductory part of the story.&#xA;:-Kartikeya, the elder son of S&amp;rsquo;iva,&#xA;Yugas (i. e. their presiding deities).&#xA;-The four -A daughter of Daksha, wife of Kas&amp;rsquo;yapa and mother of the demons called daityas after her. -the gods, also called A&amp;rsquo;dit- yas. :-The divine mothers, eight in number and re- presented as attending on Skanda and sometimes on S&amp;rsquo;iva. T-A class of demi-gods who are represented as Siva&amp;rsquo;s attendants, under the command of Ganes&amp;rsquo;a.&#xA;N. B. This sl. was found by H. H. Wilson also in one of the Mss. before him. He remarks-One Ms. indeed, calls upon all the Hindu pantheon, on Brahmà&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;and all the other objects of Hindu reverence, to be propitious to the reader; but this is a soli- tary reading, and a probable interpolation.&#xA;&amp;ndash;A celebrated sage, father of Vyasa and author of a Smriti. agara-i. e. with Vyása. -A reputed sta- tesman and diplomatist who flourished in the latter part of the fourth century B. C. He is the author of a treatise on political science and state craft called after him-Chàna- kyanîti and of many other books.&#xA;Science of politics with precepts on conduct in life generally.&#xA;arr-The science of politics and also of practical life giving such rules of conduct as tend to the increase of pro- sperity. तद्यथानुश्रूयते -It is thus related. अनश्रूयते -heard tradi- tionally, narrated in succession. rea-Situated in the south, southern; fr. af indec, and . &amp;amp;c - who was the very wish-granting tree (fulfiller of desires) to the whole multitude of supplicants, the pair of whose feet was covered with a stream of rays proceeding from the&#xA;258&#xA;gems in the diadems of eminent noble kings, who was an adept in all the arts &amp;amp;c. :-lit. whose intellect was greatly perverted, depraved in mind. rariga-Averse to the study of the S ástras. -Abs. or indec. p. p. of with en.&#xA;P. 2. Padar:-destitute of discrimination, thought- less, inconsiderate. &amp;amp;c.-does not conduce to my-or bring me any-happiness. T-or rather (used to modify or correct a previous statement).&#xA;2. Of sons unborn, (born and) dead, and illiterate, those not born and those dead are to be preferred; for these latter cause but little (or momentary) pain while a foolish son would burn (cause pain) as long as life endures.&#xA;at from a to choose-what is chosen or preferred; used&#xA;वृ adverbially followed by a, as in the next sl, in the sense of this is better or to be perferred, not that. :-scil. give or cause.&#xA;3 Better is an abortion,&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;better is a child dead (as soon as) born; better it is even to have a daughter born; better if the wife be barren; and it is also better if the child be ever lodged in the womb; than an illiterate son though endowed with the qualities of (or possessing excel- ient) beauty and wealth; (or endowed with&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;and other good qualities).&#xA;What is to be done with (what is the good of) a cow which neither brings forth a calf nor gives milk.? What is the use of that son being born who is neither learned nor full of devotion?&#xA;gf-the awakening i. e. unfolding of intellect, mental faculties. The reading-: manifestation has also the same meaning. srgstaat-should be adopted or put into execution. वृति-means of livelihood or subsistence. पञ्चचती- is rather unusual, the usual form being पञ्चशतं सिद्धिं यान्ति- let it be so managed that my desires will be crowned with&#xA;259&#xA;success or fulfilled. aft: &amp;amp;c.-Grammar is studied in twelve years. The Inst. is used to denote the time re- quired for the completion of an action. -mark the meaning-knowledge was originally imparted orally.&#xA;मन्नादीनि - Manu slands for मनुस्मृति; the codes of religious and secular laws composed by Manu and others. The science of love or erotic science. To-such as those composed by Vátsyà. and others. Vátsyáyana is identified by some with Chanakya, at-These are&#xA;fast:-The&#xA;the three Purusharthas which every human being ought to secure, the fourth being Moksha, scope or condition of life. a noun.&#xA;studied or mastered)&#xA;pot. p. here used as a&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१ मित्रभेदम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/01_mitrabhedam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/01_mitrabhedam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;18-people-who-go-to-distant-foreign-countries-get-by-being-assiduous-twofold-or-threefold-of-the-original-amount-by-selling-goods-with-due-care-or-judicionsly-वधनत-&#34;&gt;-like Om is an auspicious word (particle) and is, therefore, used at the beginning of a work.&#xA;1 A great friendship that was growing between a lion and a noble bull was destroyed by a wicked and exceeding- ly ambitions jackal.&#xA;-is a strange Comp; but words like qq when added to other words in a Karm. lose their original import and have the sense of &amp;rsquo;excellence;&amp;rsquo; see H. Gr. § 221. (b.)&#xA;P. 4. tro-who had acquired a large fortune by just means. चिन्ता समुत्पन्ना - A thought crossed or arose in his mind. af &amp;amp;c.-Although one has ample wealth, the means of acquiring money (lit. the production of) should be devised and put into practice or execution, fagura- is not acquired or accomplished, does not come into our possession. -he is regarded as a man (others have no value with rich men). f-mechanical skill; work- manship. There is not that kind of knowledge, gift &amp;amp;c. which is not sung (eulogised) of (as possessed by) the wealthy by supplicants: i. e. they attribute every kind of knowledge &amp;amp;c. to rich men (although they may not possess these ). Cf. यस्यास्ति वित्तं स नरः कुलीनः &amp;amp;c.&#xA;5-(even a stranger) acts as a relative to- wards (the rich). ara-Acts wickedly towards (does not hesitate to offend or do injury to).&#xA;6 All actions proceed (are properly accomplished) from wealth, increased and then well amassed (by proper ma- nagement) as do rivers from mountains when (sufficiently) high and well sloping.&#xA;7 That a man not deserving of respect is respected, or one not fit to be approacshed is approached, or that one who ought not (lit. does not deserve) to be saluted is salu- ted, is (all due to) the power of wealth.&#xA;8 Like (the vigour of) the organs of sense on eating,&#xA;262&#xA;all actions (business of every kind) depend on wealth: for this reason wealth is said to be the means of accom- plishing every thing.&#xA;9 This world of mortals seeking (hankering after), wealth, resorts even to a cemetery (has recourse to even despicable or horrible means); and leaving one&amp;rsquo;s father even goes far (to distant climes.)&#xA;गतवयसां - Advanced in age. अर्थेन हीना:-destitute of riches (अर्थ:). भवति - accrues, is gained. विद्योपार्जनेन by acquiring knowledge (with a view to gain one&amp;rsquo;s livelihood).&#xA;-usury, dealing in money, lending money at interest. -the profession of a merchant, trading. वाणिज्य - वणिजः कर्म ०ज्येन &amp;amp;c. - The money acquired by trad- ing is not looked down upon or found fault with, i. e. is considered as honourably acquired.&#xA;11. Begging is practised by the low i. e. is consider- ed as a mean (dishonourable) profession; and alas ! a king does not reward (service) adequately; husbandry entails a great deal of labour (or is fraught with dangers) (with the reading 4-stands in danger of being ruined by want of rain); the acquistition of knowledge is exceeding- ly difficult owing to a behaviour of humility towards a Gura (:ff: v. 1.-the act of attending on a Guru, is beset with great difficulties (and thus the ac- quistion of knowledge is not an easy task); from (if one were to practice) usury poverty (sometimes) results owing to the loss of the purse transferred to the hands of (the money lent to) others; (since all these professions have something or another to be found fault with) I think there is no mode of earning one&amp;rsquo;s livelihood superior to (or, no profession is better than) trading.&#xA;P. 5. 12. Of all the means (of acquiring wealth) the storing up of merchandise is the best (or, is the only one so called); for that alone is the best (lit. commended) for&#xA;263&#xA;the production of wealth; any other than that is of a doubtful nature (uncertain as to its result). ex f of seven kinds. गान्धिक - गन्धः पण्यभस्य a vendor of perfumes व्यवहारः - dealing in perfumes or fragrant wares निक्षेप-&#xA;:-Lit, receiving deposits; hence a Banking business (carried on by a single individual). -A Compa- ny&amp;rsquo;s business. qff-Lit. the coming, for pur- chasing goods, of customers of one&amp;rsquo;s acquaintance, hence securing first customers and then carrying on trade.fr -telling false prices and making money thereby, emrará -weighing goods in a false balance i. e. defrauding cus- tomers to gain money, -importing salable wares or goods.&#xA;13 Of all articles of sale, perfumery is the best; what is the good of commodities like gold and others! since in the former case what is bought for one is sold for a hun- dred.&#xA;14 When a deposit is made in the house the merchant (receiving it) prays to his (favourite) deity saying-If the depositor dies (would die ) I will make you the proferred present. is a present promised to a deity for the fulfilment of a desired object. What is meant is-It is not a safe course to deposit money with a merchant for interest,&#xA;15 A man entrusted with a Company&amp;rsquo;s business thinks, delighted at heart-I have to-day obtained the whole earth full of wealth; why want any other thing.&#xA;16 A shopkeeper, eagerly looking at a customer ac- quainted with him coming, rejoices at the prospeet of getting his money as a man does on the birth of a son.&#xA;17 Always cheating persons of one&amp;rsquo;s acquaintance by measures imperfectly filled up as also by telling false prices is the natural (peculiar) duty (course of conduct) of the Kiràtas. The Kirs&amp;rsquo;tas are a degraded wild tribe living&#xA;264&#xA;on the borders of forests (किरं पर्यन्तभूमिं अतन्ति traverse इति)- Cf. Ra&amp;rsquo;tnavali. II. 3.&#xA;18. People who go to distant foreign countries, get, by being assiduous, twofold or threefold (of the original amount) by selling goods with due care (or judicionsly विधानतः ).&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;agarrafa-Lit going towards i.e. which had a market for them or which were in demand at Mathura&amp;rsquo;. famous ancient city, still going by the same name, situated on the right bank of the Yamuna&amp;rsquo; near Agra and the birth place of Krishna. It was founded by S&amp;rsquo;atrughna.g- Permitted by, taking leave of, his elders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२ मित्रप्राप्तिकम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/02_mitraprAptikam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/02_mitraprAptikam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TANTRA II.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;15-an-archer-warrior-stationed-on-the-wall-of-a-fort-can-well-engage-a-hundred-gefa-speak-highly-of-commend-fa-conversant-with-see-i-232&#34;&gt;P. 97. मित्रप्राप्तिकम् मित्रप्राप्ति &amp;lsquo;The acquisition of friends and secondly &amp;rsquo;the work descriptive of it,&amp;rsquo; by the &amp;lsquo;rhetorical transference of an epithet&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;1.&#xA;:-Buddhi here means &amp;lsquo;political insight, the power to know what measures to take in an emergency; sound statesmanship. Trans.-Wise men, gifted with genius and well-informed, accomplish their purposes quickly, although without means, like the crow, the mouse the deer and the tortoise.&#xA;Ho-is Mahilapur or Meliapur, a town situated near Madras (called Mayilpur, or the city of the Peacock, in Tamil, the Maliarpha of Ptolemy). See Wilson&amp;rsquo;s works Vol. IV. p. 11.&#xA;०स्थः - situated. महो०-very lofty. उच्छ्राय height आ- -The hollows of which were occupied by. 10- which refreshed (comforted) multitudes of travellers by its shade. quo-a banian tree (the off-shoots of which go downwards and take root).&#xA;2. The beasts of the forest () lay (rested) under its shade; its leaves all round were occupied by multitudes (flights) of birds; its hollows were inhabited by insects; troops of monkeys dwelt on its stretching branches; and the honey in its flowers was fearlessly drunk off by bees: thus affording happiness to multitudes of different crea- tures, that tree alone was all worthy of praise. A tree other than such is a burden to the earth. (or, every other tree was &amp;amp;c.) This sl. is attributed to the poet Bijaks in Sargadhara&amp;rsquo;s Paddhati, No. 972 (Peterson).&#xA;Swift-fier; light of foot (लघु पतनं यस्य) प्राणवा०-in quest of food.&#xA;going to.&#xA;346&#xA;-with the intention or object of sit-with o-with chilblained feet, splay-footed,&#xA;o-with hair raised up (being tied into a knot). OTPA&#xA;i. e. looking as hedious as.*&#xA;-where I have my residence. लुब्धक - hunter. कालकूट - deadly poison -काल- मपि कूटयति (burns) - also called हालाहल-was the most viralent poison that sprang up from the churned ocean.&#xA;P. 98. fargar-white like the flowers of the Sind, tree (सिन्दुवारः श्वेतपुष्पः). वाक्यार्गलया &amp;amp;c. - held back, kept in check, by the bolt in the form of. fa-Lit, speckle- necked (चित्रा ग्रीवा यस्य). सहस्र० - सहस्रं परिवारो यस्य with a retinue of a thousand followers. ao-warned against, disuaded from. f-was confined or caught into the net.&#xA;8. Unexpected death overtakes those who are over- powered by (lit. too much attached to) the greediness of tongue or those who live in the midst of water and who are ignorant (not cautious enough to save themselves), as it does the ignorant fish which live in water and which are drawn (to the bait) by the greediness of tongue.&#xA;-or rather, (why blame them ?). This is used to modify or correct a previous statement. -Owing to the adverseness of fate.&#xA;4. How could Rávana not know that it was wrong (a crime) to carry away, by force, the wife of another (Sità)?&#xA;*The description of the fowler in the Mass. before Wilson, it appears, was more detailed. Cf. his remark-&#xA;The fowler is very minutely described &amp;lsquo;in the Pancha Tan- tra, as an inhabitant of the city, living by bird-catching, of an uncouth figure, with splay feet, and clumsy hands; round as a ball; sturdy, though advanced in years; clad in red garments, with his hair bound into a knot on his head, carry- ing a net and staff, and followed by dogs; in short, he looked like Destiny with the fatal noose; like the personification of Sin; like the heart of iniquity; like the monitor of the wicked; like the friend of Death.&amp;quot; Wilson&amp;rsquo;s works Vol. IV. p. 28.&#xA;347&#xA;by&#xA;How could Rama also not see the impossibility of a g old deer (being born)? Or how could Yudhishthira bring calamity upon himself by playing at dice (gambling) all at once (thoughtlessly )? Generally the intellect of those whose reasoning (discerning faculty) is bewildered (clouded) an impending calamity fails them (loses its acuteness). -Rávana, son of Vis&amp;rsquo;ravas and grandson of the sage Pulastya. दार-Lit. भ्रातॄन् दारयन्ति (cause the separation used in the pl. of) fa :. The word is Mas. and number. -This was Maricha, who assumed the form of a golden deer at the instance of Rávana and appeared before Sita while dwelling in Panchavati with Ráma and Lakshmana, in order to entice away Ráma, fo-Lit. firm in battle. This is an aluk Sama&amp;rsquo;sa, -through thought- lessness, Yud. always acted thoughtfully and yet he gambled.&#xA;5. The intellects of (even) great men go astray (proceed in the wrong way) when they are caught into the snares of the god of death (are doomed) and whose power of judg- ment is obscured by Destiny.&#xA;-With his stick raised. Har-On perceiving that, being aware of the fact that.&#xA;6. He, whose presence of mind does not fail him in all (kinds of) difficulties, surmounts them without doubt, through the force of this (his behaviour i. e. his firmness of mind).&#xA;7. The attitude of the great is the same whether in prosperity or adversity. The sun is red when he rises, and red in appearance also when he sets.&#xA;हेलया with ease. सपा० with the net on नोचेत् — If on the other hand; else, if, fao-allowing yourselves to be bewildered or overpowered by fear.&#xA;8. Threads although very thin and long (and so the more liable to give way), if many and lying evenly resist great tension (lit. many pullings) on account of their&#xA;348&#xA;multiplicity. The same similitude applies to (or, the same is the case with) the good (i. e. good men, although very weak can resist many difficulties and come out suc- cessful if acting in union with others &amp;amp;c.) The sl. is from Mah, Bhár. V. 36. 59.&#xA;P. 99. 9. These, although mere birds, are carrying away my net being united; there is no doubt, however, that they will fall down as soon as they quarrel (among themselves).&#xA;geo-being in close pursuit of them. -when they passed beyond the range of his sight.&#xA;10. What is not to happen can never take place; and what is destined to take place comes to pass though no effort be made (for it). What is not destined to be (remain in one&amp;rsquo;s possession) passes away even though lying on the palm of the hand (so sure in one&amp;rsquo;s possession).&#xA;11. When fate is adverse, if one comes by some fortune somehow, that passes off taking with it something else also, like the treasure Sankha (one of the nine treasures of Kubera).&#xA;-in the bargain, to add to my misfortune. The means of supporting my family,&#xA;maintenance. स्वस्थैः -with easy minds, free from fear, myo-To the north-eastern side of.&#xA;12. When calamity befalls all men equally no one but a friend would give assistance even though it be in mere words. -Perf of with has given and will give -advised. o-the fort (in the form) of his hole having a thousand (i. e. a large number of) openings or passages. Here सहस्र is used for a large number. अकुतो०- without fear from any side; in perfect safety.&#xA;13. Just as a snake without fangs, or an elephant destitute of rut is reduced to submission by every one (or, falls into the power of all) so is a king without a fort.&#xA;349&#xA;14. Not even with a thousand elephants or a hundred thousand horses that end is gained by kings in a battle which is gained by them by having one fort, ferqa-the Atm, is probably for the metre. See I. 231.&#xA;15. An archer (warrior) stationed on the wall (of a fort) can well engage a hundred. gefa-speak highly of, commend, fa-conversant with, see I. 232.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;16-friends-full-of-affection-and-giving-who-are-a-hource-of-delight-to-the-eyes-come-to-the-house-of-the-magnanimous-alone-every-day&#34;&gt;P.100. तारस्व० - in a loud voice; तारश्चासौ स्वरश्च तेन । महती- trying, critical, 5-state of my danger; or the danger I am in. To-critical situation. -very great. goo-horripilated, with the hair standing on end, fer-&#xA;-with a steady (fearless) mind.&#xA;16. Friends, full of affection and giving (who are a Hource of) delight to the eyes, come to the house of the magnanimous (alone) every day.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;बनधन०---बनधन-शष&#34;&gt;i, e आदित्यस्य &amp;amp;c. – see foot-note. अपूर्वाणि -ever new i. • they never cloy or become stale, ever give the same delight. 17. The happiness which is produced in the mind of him to whose house guests come every day is not found even in heaven. faa &amp;amp;c.-v. l. (see foot-note) no pleasure is equal to the delight which is found in his heart (he enjoys).&#xA;18. In accordance with the law of fate (a) a man obtains the fruit of his good or bad actions (done in a previous life) from that (person or thing) by that cause, in that manner, at that time, the same, that much of it and there, from which, by which cause, in which manner, at which time, which, of which measure, and where it may be due to him.&#xA;19. A bird descries flesh (bait) from a distance of a hundred and fifty yojanas (a yojana 8 or 10 miles); but the same bird does not notice, as fate would have it, the net standing near.&#xA;20. Seeing the eclipsing (lit. tormentation) of the sun&#xA;350&#xA;and the moon by the planet Ràhu, the confinement of elephants, snakes and birds and the poverty of the talented I come to think-alas, Fate is all powerful! The sl. occurs in Bartribari; see Nit, s&amp;rsquo;at. 91.&#xA;P. 101. 21. The birds that sport (move) in a part of the sky meet with ealamities; fishes are caught by experts from the deep with its unfathomable waters; of what conse- quence is a bad deed or a good deed in this world or what is the use of getting a position of advantage in this world? For the god of destruction, with his hand stretebed for- ward, catches all creatures (alike) even from a distance. The reading of the last line in the Hitopades&amp;rsquo; a is कालोहि व्यसन-&#xA;To which is better.&#xA;a term of address expressive of affection. Good friend, mso-servants come after their master; the master has precedence over the servant,&#xA;creatures. gal-even this much.&#xA;poor&#xA;22. When a king always shows great respect to his Servants they, seeing that (taking that i. e. the respect shown, into consideration), do not leave him even when without wealth.&#xA;23. Confidence ( of subjects) is the root of wealth; owing to that the elephant is the chief of a herd; while the lion, though lord of beasts, is not surrounded (attended upon) by the animals of the forest.&#xA;is used as such, is treated as.&#xA;V. 1.&#xA;अपरं - besides, the other consideration is this. कदाचित्- goes with भवति.&#xA;24. That master, who lives in happiness while his well- behaved servants are experiencing misery, goes to hell and comes to grief in this as well as in the next world.&#xA;25. The king who has compassion for and divides gains equally among his servants can be well expected to protect even the three worlds.&#xA;26. Since a man who has friends accomplishes objects,&#xA;351&#xA;even such as are difficult to be accomplisded, one should make friends that are one&amp;rsquo;s equals.&#xA;P. 102. बन्धमोक्ष:- बन्धात् मोक्षः how he was set free from the bonds, art af: &amp;amp;c.-Ob, how admirable the talent of this Hiranyaks, his strength and the provision of his fort, &amp;amp;c.-Then such exactly is the way (i. e. securing such trusty friends to assist in time) to effect (lit. which has for its object) the freedom (or release) of birds from bondage बन्धनात् मोक्षः बन्ध०क्षः स आत्मा यस्य ।&#xA;er&#xA;but I, I on the other hand.&#xA;27. Wise men, even though endowed with fullness (abundance, opulence) should make friends: for the sea, though entirely fall (of water), awaits the rise of the moon (to swell up).&#xA;बन्धन० - बन्धनं शेषः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;विशेषाद० - hiding fro-hiding&#xA;o-on a weighty or im-&#xA;चित्रग्रीव०- imitating the voice of Chi. यस्य remaining still confined in the net. himself inside still more. portant business. मैत्रीविरो०- मैत्र्या विरोधस्तस्य भावात्. owing to friendship being contrary or opposed to the natural course of things. farrara-( see V. 1.) owing to our antipathy.&#xA;28. Friendship and marriage are proper between those whose wealth is equal and whose families are of equal rank, and not between the fat and the lean (rich and poor). I. 284. Mah. Bhár. I. 132, 10.&#xA;29. That foolish man, who, evil-minded (wanting in good sense) forms friendship with one who is his unegual, being inferior or superior to himself, meets with ridicule. -Here do I &amp;amp;c. -I will have recourse to sitting here without food till I die, see IV. p. 3.&#xA;30. One should not make an alliance with an enemy even though the peace be compactly formed. E-Lit the purifier, fr. q. 4 does extinguish or put out.&#xA;P. 103. gr-what is not proper (for you to say),&#xA;352&#xA;what does not stand to reason. -due to some act (on the part of persons, such as insulting one, deceiving one &amp;amp;c.), resulting from some cause.&#xA;31. The enmity due to some cause quickly terminates by means of remedial acts (good acts done to counteract the effcet of bad acts causing the enmity); natural enmity does not come to an end without the offering up of life (terminates with death alone).&#xA;-brough about by, arising from, a cause. aceiro-by doing acts of kindness fit for (calculated to remove) it (i. e. the cause). ft-by any means. शष्पभुजः-graminivorous animals. ईश्वर - rich men सपत्नी०- rival or co-wives. -a Brahmana who strictly adheres to the rules of conduet laid down by the Vedas; Eo-those who swerve from the duties enjoined by the Vedas; hence pious and impious men. पतिव्रता -a woman entirely devoted to her husband, (पतिरेव व्रतं यस्या:), a chaste lady. कुलटा-भटतीति अटा कुलस्य अटा lit, one who wanders to a house; a comp. of the S&amp;rsquo;akandh- wádi class; a debauched or unchaste woman, &amp;amp;c.-not that every one kills every one, but one afflicts- causes anguish to-the soul. To-This is not the proper cause अप्रशस्तं कारणम्.&#xA;32.&#xA;From some cause one becomes a friend and also from a cause one becomes an enemy, of another; therefore, a wise man should employ (form) friendship and not enmity in this world.&#xA;fri-for the discharge of friendly duties (that we may behave towards each other as friends). ff-the quintessence of, most essential principle of-policy.&#xA;33.-estranged, made an enemy.&#xA;friends with, to win over. To-seizes&#xA;-to make&#xA;upon, accepts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३ काकोलूकीयम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/03_kAkolUkIyam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/03_kAkolUkIyam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TANTRA III.&#xA;-describing the enmity (or, war)&#xA;between crows and owls,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One should not trust a person once made hostile nor an enemy who has become a friend: see-the cave that was full of owls was burnt down by the fire set by crows.&#xA;errero-having many branches.&#xA;०खगस०-०. L. inhabited by birds of various kinds. This reading is rejected because the tree is deseribed as the special lodge of crows. :-covered with very thick foliage. of- a:-having a large retinue of crows; attended by many crows. विहित० — having built a fortress. अरिम० - Lit.&#xA;fa-having the destroyer of enemies ( अरीणां मर्दन. ). गिरिगुहा०-resid- ing in (who had taken shelter in) the cave of a moun- tain serving as a fort.&#xA;a fort. पूर्वविरोध०—owing to previous enmity. a &amp;amp;c.-whatsoever crow he came across नित्याभि० - By his constant attacks. दुर्गं -the fortress&#xA;०दुर्गं—the situated on &amp;amp;c. -all round (i. e, not a crow was left outside that ).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He who being full of sloth neglects his enemy and a disease moving ( gaining strength) freely, is slowly killed by them.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He who would not put down (destroy) an enemy and a disease as soon as manifested (he or it appears ), is, though very strong, killed by him or it afterwards, gain- ing strength.&#xA;yig:-Now, one day.&#xA;:-powerful; or furious,&#xA;-endowed with industry, energetic,&#xA;abo&#xA;knows the proper time for action. -At nightfall&#xA;or approach of night,&#xA;40-causes the destruction&#xA;of or works havoc upon our partisans,&#xA;390&#xA;P. 135.&#xA;&amp;amp;e.-What steps should be taken to kgs-which is proper to&#xA;retaliate or counteract this, be adopted, effer &amp;amp;c.-See notes Tan. I p. 12.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;अत्र अस्मिन् विषये or एतादृशे प्रस्तावे. A minister should say something (give advice) even though unasked under such circumstances: but when consulted he should quickly (without loss of time) say what is wholeso ne, whether it be agreeable or disagreeable,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He, who, being asked, does not say what is benefi- cial and salutary in the end, he-a minister and a speaker of sweet things (at the same time) is said to be simply&#xA;an enemy.&#xA;What is meant is this-a minister, when consulted, should not simply seek to please his master by saying what is agreeable to him but guide him rightly.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Read in the text after the fifth Sl.-go: go&#xA;सततं प्रियवादिनः । अप्रियस्य च पथ्यस्य वक्ता श्रोता च दुर्लभः ॥ It is always easy, O king, to find men who speak sweetly; but it is difficult to find one who speaks or one who (without being irritated) listens to what is wholesome although disagreeable.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Therefore, O king, let a consultation be held after retiring to a secluded place so that we shall find out the cause of his (enemy&amp;rsquo;s) action and effectively check him.&#xA;अन्वयागत - heriditary. एवं स्थिते-matters standing thus; under such circumstances, o-striking at the proper&#xA;time, seizing the proper opportunity to attack.&#xA;worthy of being entered into an alliance with.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;बलीयसि &amp;amp;c. - शत्रौ बलीयास सति तं प्रणमतां &amp;amp;c. The riches (royalty) of those, who bow to their enemy when he proves stronger but who strikes when the proper time comes, do not go away from them just as rivers do not flow in a&#xA;391&#xA;direction contrary to the current,&#xA;-irregularly derived&#xA;fr. against and a water or the current of water. निन्नगाः- निम्नं गच्छन्तीति निम्नगाः see Kam. Nit, IX, 50.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;That enemy, who is very truthful (lit. rich in truth), pious, noble, possessed of a multitude of relatives, power- ful and victorious in many battles, is fit to be made peace with. Cf. Kam. Nit. IX. 42.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A friendly alliance should be formed even with a wicked person on knowing that there is danger to life, since when life is saved every thing else is also saved. For the first 1. see Kam. Nit. IX. 45.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-He, who has been victorious in many battles, is, for that reason, fit to be made peace with.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enemies quickly fall into the power of him with whom the victor-of-many-battles forms a friendly alliance, owing to his prowess. see Kam. Nit, IX. 52,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One should desire to form peace even with one&amp;rsquo;s equal, since victory in a battle is uncertain; no dangerous step should be taken (or, one should not risk his interest); so counsels Brhaspati. See Kam, Nit. IX, 59.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Victory in a battle, in the case of men fighting in this world, is doubtful: therefore that (a battle) should be had recourse to when the other three remedies (1, and) have been tried (i. e. after they fail.) ga The Par. is irregular; it is, however, found in the Veda and in epie poetry.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A man, who, blinded by pride, does not make peace (with another), causes, when forcibly struck even by his equal, the destruction of both, as does an unbaked earthen pot when struck by another. -v. 1. may mean-with whom self-respect is the chief consideration (91 m = ) or separate arra through pride.392&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Const.&#xA;&amp;amp;c. The fight&#xA;of a weak man with a powerful one leads to his destruc-&#xA;tion; for the powerful man destroyed his enemy as does a (of earth ).&#xA;stands unharmed having stone after breaking a jar&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Acquisition of territory, an ally and gold (money)- these three are the benefits to be derived from war: when not even one of these is to be gained one should not have recourse to it. See Kam, Nit. X. 28 where the second half is read as-&#xA;i fago see Tan. I. 229&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A lion, digging the hole of a mouse, filled with pieces of stone, gets his claws broken; or if he gets the fruit (of his labours, it is (simply) a mouse,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Therefore, one should not occasion war nor should wage it under any circumstances in a case where there would be no substantial gain but simply fighting.&#xA;assumes an&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One, desirious of unfailing (continued) wealth (royalty) should imitate the action (mode of behaviour) of the cane plant (which always yields and never unbending attitude) when attacked by a more powerful enemy, and never that of a serpent (which rises up suddenly and meets with destruction). See Kam. Nit. X. 32, 33.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;काले काले-Assuming the contraction of a tortoise (i. e a humble attitude) a talented man should even bear blows (inflicted by the enemy); and at times (i. e. when- ever he would get favourable opportunities) he should rise like a black serpent (i. e. at once wreak his vengeance ). See Kam. Nit, X, 35 where the reading is the proper time comes. This reading is better.&#xA;when&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Seeing that war is imminent (about to break out) one should avert it by efficient means of peace, on account of the uncertainty of victory; one should not arms) recklessly.&#xA;rise (in&#xA;v. 1. One should&#xA;give up&#xA;rashness.&#xA;393&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is no precept to the effect that one should fight with a powerful person; a cloud never moves in a direction contrary to the wind. -a rule of political&#xA;science.&#xA;साममन्त्रं सन्धि० - counsel for conciliation leading to the conclusion of peace or calculated to bring about the cessa tion of hostilities.&#xA;P. 137. न मम प्रतिभाति - does not appear advisable&#xA;to me.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;सुश्लिष्ट - well-formed. See II. 30. अत्यन्तलुब्धः- exceedingly greedy, very avaricious, covetous. -Im- pious, unrighteous.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One should not enter into an alliance with a man who is destitute of truthfulness and righteousness (or the principle of truthfulness ); for, although firmly allied, he, on account of his wickedness, will change beforelong.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;An enemy who is cruel, very avaricious, lazy, re- gardless of truth, blundering (in policy ), timid, un- steady, foolish and a despiser of warriors, can easily be rooted ont (extirpated ).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;संधानकी o mention of or proposal for peace. भूयो० &amp;amp;c.-will be highly exasperated; or, will cause greater disturbance (cf. अन्तःकोप, प्रकृतिकोप &amp;amp;c. ),&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the case of an enemy manageable by (the use of) the fourth remedy (i. e. Danda or war) the proposal for peace is a wrong piece of policy; what wise man (physician) will sprinkle water over the body of a person (with the object of cooling him) attacked with fever which has not yet reached the stage of treatment and which is curable by inducing perspiration only. The verse is taken from S&amp;rsquo;is. II. 54.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Talks about (negotiations for) peace, serve, on the contrary, to inflame an enemy already angry, as drops&#xA;5&#xA;394&#xA;of water falling all of a sudden on ghee which is very much boiled, (only) agitate it. -is no proper or adequate&#xA;reason.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The lion, taking his stand on his high spirit (his great strength) plants his foot (paw) on the head of an intoxicated elephant, though the latter is superior in bulk, See Kâm, Nît, XIII. 16.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A small (weak) man, endowed with the power of energy, can kill even a big (or, physically strong) man, as a lion does an elephant :-so say the Bharadwajas. Cf. Kám. Nit. IX. 56.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Those enemies who can not be killed by (sheer) force, should be killed by using deceit, as Bhima killed Kichaka by assuming the disguise of a woman.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enemies yield to the power of one whose punish- ment is very severe as ( people do to that of) the god of death who punishes cruelly (or who holds the fierce rod ); but they treat as straw him who puts up with every thing (is very mild).&#xA;P. 138. 33. What is the good of his being vainly born, whose lustre (valour) does not overpower that of spirited men (or, his powerful enemies) and who is, (therefore, only) the destroyer of his mother&amp;rsquo;s youth.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;That wealth, which is not marked (lit. whose body is not smeared) with the saffron in the form of the blood of the enemies, does not bring pleasure to the mind of talented men, though covetable,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What praise can belong to the life of that king whose territory is not copiously sprinkled with the blood of his enemies and with the water of the tears of their wives.&#xA;काधिक:- superior in strength, निर्मयाद: one who has&#xA;fan-one&#xA;395&#xA;transgressed the bounds of propriety or acted villainously.&#xA;-marching away, flight.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Neither peace nor war, nothing else than a march against or from, is considered advisable in dealing with one who is superior in strength, wicked and acting improper- ly (Hataria lit. not keeping within the bounds of propriety).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Yána (marching off) is of two kinds:-one is for saving one&amp;rsquo;s life and wealth (treasure) when in peril (when there is danger from the enemy threatening the loss of both); the other is of the form of an expedition by one (a king) desirous of conquest (i, e. one is flight for safety; the other an expedition by a powerful king confident of success. ). यात्रा ० - यात्रा 8 march for attack लक्षणं distin- guishing mark यस्य and is nearly equivalent to यात्रारूपं of the form of. faufg-Noun in a formed from the desidera. tive base of f.&#xA;91&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The expedition into an enemy&amp;rsquo;s territory by a con- queror, eminently powerful, is said to be very opportune (lit. commended) either in the month of Kârtika or Chaitra and in no other. कार्तिके - See Rag. IV. 14. मार्गशीर्ष and are also recommended as proper months for leading an expedition into an enemy&amp;rsquo;s territory. See Man. Smr. VII, 282, These months are recommended because they are the months of plenty and are free from the obstruction of rain. Besides there is no danger of corn-fields being devastated,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(But) when the enemy is involved in a diffi- culty or has weak points, all times are spoken of (recom- mended) as fit for leading an attack. Cf. Man. Smṛ. VII. 183.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Having well effected the protection of one&amp;rsquo;s own country by means of men who are brave, friendly (or trustworthy) and possessed of great strength one should&#xA;396&#xA;march against another&amp;rsquo;s country already occupied by one&amp;rsquo;s spies. -The attacking king should first know every particular about the enemy&amp;rsquo;s country by means of his spies. See Man, Smr. VII. 184.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He, who attacks an enemy&amp;rsquo;s country without know- ing its roads or any thing about provisions (a), water and corn (i. e. without knowing how to procure these or make arrangments for these ), ( not only fails to conquer that country, but) does not even return to his own country (i. e. is vanquished by his enemy and des troyed). arar V. 1. provisions of various kinds.&#xA;a ga &amp;amp;c.-So it is advisable for you to effect a flight (the first kind of Yana ).&#xA;P. 139. -read aa. Therefore, O lord, it is not at all (a) proper for you to adopt the second kind (of Yána i. e. to undertake an expedition ); you should neither enter into a war nor propose peace with that powerful and wicked enemy.&#xA;-Wise men have recourse to object in view or looking to the cause adopt such a course.&#xA;flight with some forcing them to&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The reason why a ram falls back (retreats) (when fighting) is that he should (be able to) strike (with great- er force ); the lion too contracts his body when wishing to leap (upon his prey) through great rage; with their motives concealed in their hearts and keeping their deliberations and movements secret, talented men put up with anything (f) disregarding it altogether ( i, e. waiting for an opportunity they suffer any insulte not caring for them).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He, who, finding that his enemy is powerful, quits his country, lives and gets his kingdom again like Yudhishthira (the eldest of the Pândavas ).&#xA;When Dharma lost his kingdom by gambling and was&#xA;397&#xA;asked to go into exile with his wife and brothers, he did so, knowing that his enemies were strong and his own party weak. He returned after living for twelve years in the forest and one year incognito, strengthened his party and wrested back his kingdom from the Kauravas.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The weak man, who, through pride, fights with a more powerful enemy, does what is desired by him ( his enemy) and brings destruction upon his own family.&#xA;flee &amp;amp;c.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-Therefore, now that you are assailed (pressed hard) by a powerful enemy, it is time for you to ff-do not appear to me to be advis- able. A maintaining one&amp;rsquo;s ground. fa:-especially. яf-commends itself to my judgment,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;having got into its own place. - च्युतः-driven or dislodged from, परिभूयते—is despised or overpowered.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Attacked (besieged) by a powerful enemy a king should take shelter in a forest putting forth efforts: and stationed there he should call his friends to his help that he should effect his escape (or release). See Kâm, Nit. IV. 55.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He, who, with his mind bewildered by fear on hear ing of the approach of an enemy, leaves his own place, will not enter it again.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Like a serpent without fangs or an elephant with- out rut, a king, who is out of (leaves) his own place, is easily assailable by all creatures. -lit. approachable i. e. any one can go to him and insult him or attack him, org-Loc. for the Inst. It will be better to read rgft: 50. एकोपि शक्तानां शत्रूणां शतमपि योद्धुं सहेत् &amp;amp;c. - Even one man&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;will be able to fight with even&#xA;a hundred power- ful enemies &amp;amp;c.&#xA;P. 140. 51, 52, The two Slokas ought to be taken&#xA;398&#xA;together. They constitute what is called gri. e. two S&amp;rsquo;lokas forming one grammatical sentence. Cf. at युग्ममिति प्रोक्तं त्रिभिः श्लोकविशेषकम् । कलापकं चतुर्भिः स्यात्तदूर्ध्वं कुलकं स्मृतम् ॥&#xA;Therefore, having strengthened a fortress, furnishing it with brave warriors and provisions, surrounding it with a rampart and a ditch and embellishing it with machinery, and other things, one should wait in it, always bent on fighting: for if one lives (i. e. comes out victorious) one gets a kingdom, if one dies, one goes to heaven.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Even weak men who live in one place are not over- powered (troubled) by even a strong man acting adversely as creepers growing together (lit. in one place) are not injured by even a strong wind blowing in a contrary direction. बलिना should also be taken with मरुता. साध्यन्ते v. 1. for a means brought under power; reduced to submission&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;54-56. Since even a large tree, strong and deep- rooted (well-imbedded in the earth) but growing singly can be uprooted by a strong (9) wind, but (a) the trees which grow in a mass and are firmly rooted are not uprooted even by a violent wind on account of their grow- ing in one place; so enemies consider a man who is single (unassisted) although possessed of valour, as capable of being vanquished and then they kill him,&#xA;ga in S&amp;rsquo;l. 54 has no particular meaning; S&amp;rsquo;l. 55, should better have been omitted. S&amp;rsquo;lokas 54, 56-see Mah. Bhâr. Van, 36, 63, 64.&#xA;enereo-What is known by the name of A&amp;rsquo;sana or maintaining one&amp;rsquo;s ground. same as q: the six&#xA;षाङ्गुण्य- षड्गुणा:&#xA;expedients. -taking shelter or making an alliance with (a more powerful king especially ).&#xA;399&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What can a spirited man, though strong, do if without a helper (allies)? Fire, kindled in a place where there is no wind, is extinguished of itself.&#xA;Fargo-who will free you from the difficulty or avert the calamity? -by mere speech even (much less by actual help ).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The wind becomes the assistant (helper) of the fire that burns forests; but the same (wind) puts out a lamp: who has friendship for the lean (weak) ? v. 1 for at means &amp;lsquo;regard or respect for.&amp;quot;&#xA;एकान्तः-&#xA;-an absolute rule; the only course of action. -living together; hence union.&amp;rsquo;&#xA;P. 141. 59. Just as a bamboo growing in a cluster thick and surrounded by other bamboos, cannot be cut down, so a king who has a number of assistants () cannot be destroyed though weak: See Kâm. Nit. IX, 46.&#xA;f: &amp;amp;c.-If then there be a resort to (or one gets the support of) the best of men what to say then (that the combination will be irresistible ). उत्तमस्योत्तमेन वा संश्रयः,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To whom is the company of a great man (or, men) not elevating? (i. e. whom will it not elevate or raise in rank); the water lying on a lotus-leaf possesses the lustre (or, beauty) of a pearl.&#xA;न प्रतीकारो भवति-there can be no resistance on our part &amp;amp;c.&#xA;:-opinion, counsel or advice.&#xA;tai-&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-&#xA;old, who had been long in his service. Loc, Abs.; notwithstanding your presence here, although you were here. -for testing them (i. e. their&#xA;qar-for knowledge); or it may mean-(arta: a) for taking a comprehensive view of the matter, a-will advise. To-what was in conformity with the (dicta of the ) science of polity नीतिशास्त्र नीतिशास्त्रस्य वा श्राश्रयः&#xA;400&#xA;based on the science of politics; or it may be an Avya. Comp. ; नीतिशास्त्रस्य आश्रयः यस्मिन्कर्मणि तद्यथा तथा in a manner to be supported by the principles of &amp;amp;c. aggà &amp;amp;c. All that is made use of at the time proper for each, (as there is an occasion for or as circumstances arise for, the use of each). -double-dealing or duplicity; keeping apparently friendly relations with the enemy with a view to throw him off his guard and to destroy him.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When an enemy is wicked and powerful one should deal with him distrustfully (cautiously) taking one&amp;rsquo;s stand on duplicity, now proposing peace, now fighting,&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-Therefore an enemy is easily extirpated by those who, themselves distrustful, secure his confidence and hold forth hopes (to him).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Men well-versed in politics allow an enemy to grow strong once, though they have to uproot him: phlegmatic affection, when increased by means of molasses, is easily cured.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;एकभावः- एकः भावः feeling यस्य; acting with sameness of heart; hence honest, sincere. The man who acts honestly with women, an enemy, a treacherous friend and especially with harlots, does not live (i. e. he will be destroyed by them.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The duties towards gods, Bráhmaņas, one&amp;rsquo;s own self and one&amp;rsquo;s preceptor, should be performed with a devot- ed mind; the rest (other things) depends on (must be done with) duplicity (i. e. double dealing is necessary in other cases, honesty will not do).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Oneness of action (sincerity) is always commend- able in the case of ascetics whose souls are purified (lit. imbued with the knowledge of the Supreme soul); but not in the case of men who are attached to women and especi ally of kings.&#xA;401&#xA;-by having recourse to cupidity (to be excit&#xA;ed in the enemy.)&#xA;P. 142 gato-bring them to light by means of emis- saries or spies (प्रणिधि ).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;66&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;गन्धेन — by smell or scent. पश्यन्ति-see things, चारै:- by means of spies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;-an auxiliary, a helper; an official connected with a king or in immediate attendance on him. See below,&#xA;He, who knows the Tirthas (i. e. the real character of the helping officials) on his own side and on those of his enemies, particularly by means of secret spies, will never come to grief (or find himself in difficulty or be reduced to a miserable plight).&#xA;कतिसंख्यानि - what is their number. कति संख्या येषां. :-when they are known, An instance of Inst.&#xA;Absolute.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;p-144--assemblage-of-f-among-themselves-75--clever-shrewd-shrewdest-cleverest-fai-of-animals-having-jaws-i-e-carnivorous-animals-a-mendicant-wearing-white-garments-probably-an-ascetic-of-the-svetâmbara-sect-a-class-of-jaina-bhikshus-advice-or-opinion&#34;&gt;Have you known&#xA;(I hope you have) the eigh- teen Tirthas on the side of the enemy and fifteen on yours by means of three secret (lit. not known as such) spies. See Mah. Bhår. III. 5, 38.&#xA;fi &amp;amp;c.-By the word &amp;lsquo;Tirtha&amp;rsquo; an official (a) is meant. आयुक्तं कर्म यस्य one to whom &amp;amp; duty of state is entrusted; hence an official. तद् यदि - तद् refers to तीर्थं. gfa-corrupt, treacherous. If the officials on the side of the enemies be not faithful (not discharging their duties faithfully) then this leads to the destruction of the master (the king). i-eminently good, excellent, स्यात् - will contribute to the prosperity of तथथा – They are as under. (5) -a door-keeper or warder; fr. + meaning &amp;lsquo;pertaining to&amp;rsquo;. (6) saat-the superintendent of the women&amp;rsquo;s apartments. (7) garers: (more usually Я) The chief adviser or counsellor general, (8) -A sort of master of the ceremonies.402&#xA;(9) fo-an introducer of persons, a gentle-man-ucher; (10) the chief justice. (11) T-the master of requests. (12) The chief officer of the army. (14) The treasurer or superintendent of the treasury. (15) The governor of the fort; (16) if this means anything it means the collector of customs or the receiver general of taxes. But more probably the 1 or the superin- tendent of prisons&amp;rsquo; is meant here, (17) Protector of the frontier or lord of the marches; (18) favourite servants.&#xA;C&#xA;i &amp;amp;c.-By the alienation of these or when these are won over, an enemy is quickly brought under control or subdued, -the chaplet-maker or florist. Far- ध्यक्ष:- the superintendent or chief of spies. सांवत्स० &amp;mdash; the astrologer, o-the bearer of the betel-nut-box. -&#xA;-the body-guard, fo-the quarter-master. विलासिनी - the concubine. वैरद्वारेण-by exciting the en- mity of these (by one&amp;rsquo;s self or by the enemy).&#xA;89. The physician, the astrologer and the preceptor are the spies to be appointed (to watch) one&amp;rsquo;s own party; similarty (spies in the disguise of) serpent-exhibitors and lunatics know every thing that passes in the camp of the enemies.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-These should be employed because they have an easy access every where and enjoy the confidence of all, Tifge-These also have easy access every where and can observe the designs of the enemy without being suspected.&#xA;P. 143. 70. Let spies who know their duty make an entrance into, by means of the Tirthas ( officials that can be reached-flight of steps) and sound the bottom (the very secrets) of the large body of water in the form of the enemies. There is a play here on the wood which also means a flight of steps leading into the water.&amp;quot;&#xA;Just as one can reach the bottom of water by means&#xA;&amp;quot;&#xA;403&#xA;of a flight of steps so the spies can penetrate the very heart of the enemy through the officials and know his secret plans.&#xA;प्राणान्तिकं - प्राणानामन्तः प्राणान्तः स सामीप्यमस्य which leads to the destruction of life, deadly. faf-a cock; at fa- रन्तीति विष्किराः gallinaceous birds. सोद्वेगं with dejection, sorrowfully. &amp;amp;c.-does not care for us at all, does not think of us.&#xA;71.&#xA;-read. He, who does not protect creatures (subjects) that are terror-striken and harassed by the ene- mies, is without doubt, the god of destruction (himself) in the form of a king.&#xA;72. If there be no king to safely guide (lit. the proper guide of) his subjects then they would suffer destruction, as a boat without a helmsman sinks in the ses. TETTO- Sikandar: . See Kám. Nît. I. 10.&#xA;78. 74. The two verses are to be taken together and form a g. A man should abandon the following six, as one does a broken boat in tha sea, viz. a preceptor who does not teach (lit. explain) satisfactorily (), a sacrifi- cial priest who does not keep up his knowledge by constant study, a cowherd fond of staying in the village (i. e, who does not take the cattle to better pasture grounds outside a village) and a barber fond of going to the forest (neglecting his duty and therefore who cannot do his work well). See Mah. Bhár, Van, 33, 79-80, and XII. 57. 43-45.&#xA;-of a handsome form; beautiful aspect (: Tr कारो यस्य.). साधिते &amp;amp;c. when the water of varicus sacred rivers had been brought, ggufi &amp;amp;c.-after the collection of 101 herbs had been got ready, -had been set up. * &amp;amp;c.-After the picture of the globe of the earth&#xA;404&#xA;ohequered with mountains, seas and the seven continents had been drawn. nitag &amp;amp;c.-when the golden jars, lamps and trumpets had been filled respectively with water, oil and wind from the mouth.&#xA;fag &amp;amp;c.-when auspicious things such as mirrors &amp;amp;c, had been made ready. Toro &amp;amp;c.-when the Brà hmanas were engaged in repeating the Vedas in one voice ( all together ). समुदितानि मुखानि mouths i. c. voices येषां तेषु. अग्रमहिषी - the chief queen कृकालिका - proper name,&#xA;P. 144. :-assemblage of. f-among themselves. 75. :-clever, shrewd (shrewdest, cleverest). fai of animals having jaws i, e. carnivorous animals. a mendicant wearing white garments-probably an ascetic of the S&amp;rsquo;vetâmbara sect (a class of Jaina Bhikshus). advice or opinion.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;76&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Plans (policies, schemes), thought out by experts and discussed with many and from various points of view and well considered, do not fail under any circumstances.&#xA;समेत्य - having joined them, निरूपितस्ति० - is determined or fixed upon, settled. gear-At the commencement, when his coronation is just to begin.&#xA;fa&#xA;a kind of&#xA;ducks. i-a species of parrots.- (Loc. Abs.) when these principal kinds of birds are in existence (available). - dreadful, deformed मुखं यस्य of hideous aspect.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Crooked-nosed and very squint-eyed, formidable and of an unpleasant aspect-such is his face when not angry; what will it be when he is angry?&#xA;0 The seven dwipas are-Jambu, Plaksha, S&amp;rsquo;álmali, Kusha, Kranncha, S&amp;rsquo;aka and Puskkara. The seas are also seven (according to the Purâns) viz. Kshårodhadhi, Iks&amp;rsquo;ura- sodadhi, Surâ, Sarpis, Kshirodadhi, Dadhima and S&amp;rsquo;uddhoda- dhi. The seven mountanis are-&#xA;महेन्द्रो मलयः सह्यः शुक्तिमानृक्षपर्वतः । विन्ध्यश्च पारियात्रश्च सप्तैते कुलपर्वताः ।।&#xA;405&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What object shall we gain by making this owl which is frightful by nature, very fierce, cruel and of a re- pulsive aspect, a king!&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One mighty (lit. possessed of lustre, spirited) king proves a blessing to the world. 2nd line-ga- स्वन्त इव अत्र बहवो विपत्तये भवन्ति; if there are many, they lead to trouble ( or destruction) as many suns at the end of a Yuga cause the destruction of the world.&#xA;a&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-Then by the mere mention of his (Garuda&amp;rsquo;s) name you will be beyond the reach of (lit. not to be approched or assailed by) your enemies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When there is a master, even at the mere mention of the name of the great before wicked men, good results st once. Or गुरूणां may be taken with दुष्टानां; even the mere mention of the name of the lord before wicked men though powerful &amp;amp;c. This accords well with the follow- ing story.&#xA;P. 145. 81. Great success is achieved by the designa- tion (mention of the name) of the great; the bares lived happily by making mention of the Moon.&#xA;अनावृष्टिः - drought, want of rain. यावत् continuing or lasting for. a meaning &amp;lsquo;as long as&amp;rsquo; governs the Acc.&#xA;-a deep pool T-overpowered by thirst.&#xA;हद - &amp;amp;&#xA;almost dead.&#xA;7-some (a).&#xA;i&#xA;at ease, alam-lonely, secluded from view,&#xA;situated in the middle of a tract of land.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;01&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;-will feel&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;•-Gangá&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;is supposed to flow in the sky, on the earth and in the&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;lower regions,&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;azo-That being done i. e. the journey being under- taken. -by them travelling or journeying on. -having bathed or plunged into. -i, e. the holes or burrows of the hares. -had their legs, heads and necks, broken. fia: Ga-had just life left in them. og-whose dwellings were trampled&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;6&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;406&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;down or destroyed by the treadings of the elephants, जर्जरित • - with bodies severely injured, oलताः- रुधिरेण लुताः covered with blood. इत० - इताः शिशवो येषां whose young ones were killed. -with their eyes covered with the moisture of tears.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;82. स्पृशन्नपि - though merely touching. ing (exhaling venomous breath).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;जिघ्रन् -Smell- -even while paying respect (although outwardly showing respect ).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;किमन्यत्र - read oन्यत्.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;83.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;-for the sake of, i. e. to save.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;P. 146. 84. - : habitable, comfortable, prosperous. For his own sake, a king should abandon, without hesitation (thinking about it), his land though contributing to his comforts, yielding corn and causing increase of cattle.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;fo-coming down or inherited from the great-grand- father, ancestral.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;ff-some means of frightening them, a scare- crow. A noun from the desider, of aft.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;86. &amp;amp;c.&amp;ndash;the hood should greatly be expanded. eri: &amp;amp;c. -the display of the hood strikes terror. ०पिकास्थानं-object or cause of fright. सा च &amp;amp;c. The causing of such fright depends upon a clever mes- senger (i. e. must be skilfully managed ). free a pretended or false messenger. -to say that, with the message that. fa-forbids you; orders you not to come here. TECTITE:-my followers or protegees.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;-worde appearing to be credible, trustworthy or reliable. -clever in arranging or getting up a speech; knows how to address appropriate words. -skilled in, who knows, the duty or business of a messenger.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;87. That is a desirable messenger for a king, who&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;407&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;possesses a handsome form (or, who knows how to con- ceal his features), who is free from avarice, eloqnent, well versed in the different S&amp;rsquo;ástras and able to know the minds (divine the thoughts) of others.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;88. आचरेस - is used here in the sense of नियोजयेत्. He, who deputes as a messenger to a king&amp;rsquo;s court one who is foolish, avaricious and especially one telling lies, fails in his object.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;afo-Let such a messenger be found out, if you wish to be entirely () free from this calamity.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;निरूपितः - appointed or depnted. अगम्य - beyond the reach of, inaccessible to, the elephants. -sportively&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(and so carelessly).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;P. 147. -No fault should be found with a messenger who speaks the truth (delivers the true mes sage). aga-speak through messengers,&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;89. Even when weapons are raised and relatives killed, messengers ought not to be killed by a king, even when they utter harsh words.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;eratafe-i, e. Yesterday. a-trodden down, des- troyed by your herd.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;:-engaged or lost in medi- tation. निभृतं - silently. त्रजे - read व्रज. ०भङ्गात्-owing to the disturbance caused to his contemplation.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;set out to go.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;-addicted to vices. ggo-in the habit of back-biting, disposed to speak ill in one&amp;rsquo;s absence.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;90 Formerly a hare and Kapinjala ( name of s sparrow) seeking justice and going to a mean judge for decision both met with destruction. s means here the lord of as or law-cases, one who decides a care.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;P. 148.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;&amp;ndash;by narrating the old accounts (stories) of divine sages, Brahmana sages &amp;amp;c, and by&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;408&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;telling each other the curiosities seen in the course of our wanderings. ro-full of ripe S&amp;rsquo;àli (a kind of rice) corn. सोद्वे० - dejected at heart. उताहोस्वित्- or. कपिन्ज-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;-As I had despaired of Kapinjala&amp;rsquo;s return. पीवर० - पीवरा तनुर्यस्य fat in body.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;88&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;91. Men do not experience ( find) that happiness &amp;amp;c. which they enjoy, though poor, in their country, their town and their own house,&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;-revilingly, blaming him for it.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;place of residence. qr-harsh things.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;92. One cannot establish one&amp;rsquo;s mastery over a pond, a well, a tank, a temple and trees after they are once abandoned,&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;P. 149. 93. Enjoyment is proof ( of ownership) in that case in which things such as land and others are enjoyed for ten years in one&amp;rsquo;s presence (with one&amp;rsquo;s know- ledge ); neither a witness nor documentary proof ( lit. a writing) is necessary for it.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;94. This law (1) applies to men, as stated by the great sages; in the case of beasts and birds ownership lasts so long as they are in possession of a thing.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;F&amp;amp;c.-If you regard the Smṛti law as binding or as an authority. :-The sharp-jawed ( g ). कृत० - having taken Kus&amp;rsquo;a grass in his hand. ऊर्ध्व० - ऊर्ध्वो बाहू यस्य with arms raised. अर्धपाद०-touching the earth with the half parts of his feet.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;-a discourse on religious matters;-delivered this exhortation on religion. असारः - अविद्यमानः सारः यस्य without substance, unreal, -Family-relation is like jugglery, a mere de- lusion; or, is short-lived; vanishes in a moment. मुक्त्वा &amp;amp;c. - leaving righteousness; here मुक्त्वा has the sense of-except, without. &amp;amp;c.-There is no other course&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;409&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;open to man (to save himself) than righteousness (doing religious duties and securing merit thereby ).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;95. The bodies are not everlasting (ie. are perishable in a moment); prosperity is not at all permanent; and death is always close at hand (ready to overtake a creature); therefore, a store of religious merit should be made,&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;96. without the securing or laying by of any religious merit. &amp;amp;c.-He does not ( cannot be said to) live though emitting breath like a blacksmith&amp;rsquo;s bellows.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;97. कौपीनं- कूपपतनमर्हतीति कौ० sin; it also means the secret parts ( तत्सम्बन्धात्त प्याद्वा पुरुषलिङ्गमपि । तत्सम्बन्धात्तदाच्छादन- aft a piece of cloth which covers those parts). Proficiency in religious matters without the performance of religious rites is as useless as the tail of a dog which neither covers the private parts nor keeps off mosquitoes or gnats. The 1st line may also be taken with qr-which does not make one wear a Kaupina (lead an ascetic&amp;rsquo;s life) nor removes passions (which are like &amp;amp;c. ).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;98. got-worthless corn; shrivelled grain;&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;&amp;amp;1&amp;amp;-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Amara. Those who do not regard religion as the canse (of all that happens) are like the Pu. in corn &amp;amp;c. See Mah. Bhár. XII, 181. 7.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;99. :-better, more valuable or of greater conse- quence. पिण्याक-oil-cake. मानुपात्- मानुषस्येदं मानुषं a human concern; religious duty is of greater cousequence than hu- man affairs (secular concerns).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;100. Men, regardless of religion (who do not attend to their religious duties) are created like beasts, for the use of others, being mere voiders of urine and ordure and eaters of food.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;P. 150. 101. Those versed in politics commend stea- diness (patience) in all actions; but speedy is the course of religious duty, which is attended with many obstacles.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;410&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(religious duties should be promptly executed since these are beset with &amp;amp;c. ),&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;102. The principle of Dharma is briefly explained to you, O people; what have you to do with a detailed descrip- tion? Doing good to others leads to merit; giving trouble to others, to sin.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;103. Hear the essence of religon; and having heard it lay it to your hearts:-The 2nd line may mean-(1) 3: परेषां च प्रतिकू न स० One should not do what is unfavourable to oneself or others; or (2) one should not do unto others what one regards as unfavourable to one&amp;rsquo;s self; or (3) aft- कूलानि आत्मनः समाचरेत् न परेषां one should do what is against one&amp;rsquo;s interest with regard to one&amp;rsquo;s self (if he has to do so at all) and not to others. -an expounder of the principles of religion; a preacher of religion.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;व्रतवै० - विकलस्य भावो वैकल्यं deficiency; his vow may be interfered with or disturbed. •द्वारेण - according to the rules of law. हीन०- हीनं वदतीति हीनो वादोरयेति वा one who makes a defective statement; one whose cause is wrong. anta &amp;amp;c.-refraining from doing injury to life is the only path of virtue ( or sanctioned by religion ).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;104. Since Dharma is said by the wise to be grounded on ahims&amp;rsquo;a ( abstaining from injuring or destroying life) one should protect (not kill) even a louse, a bug &amp;amp;c.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;105. He who kills even carnivorous animals is said to be a cruel man and goes to the horrible hell; what to say then of him who kills harmless ones.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;qar-the real meaning.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;rice seven years old.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&amp;amp;c.-By Aja is meant&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;/dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;106&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If by cutting trees (for making sacrificial posts &amp;amp;c. )&amp;hellip; and sheding a profusion of blood (lit, causing mud with blood) one can go to heaven, &amp;amp;c.&#xA;411&#xA;GT-But I will decide as to who should be the -properly, rightly, justly.&#xA;winner and who the loser,&#xA;-the dispute or matter at issue.&#xA;P. 151.&#xA;dispute. 107.&#xA;prestige).&#xA;-the real nature or cause of your&#xA;-through pride (i. e. to keep up one&amp;rsquo;s -delivers a wrong judgment, decides&#xA;a case unjustly (lit, not according to justice).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;-read . He, who gives a wrong de- cision about a horse, kills (is guilty of killing) one creature &amp;amp;c.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He, who seated in a court (of law), does not speak out distinctly (does not give his decision in clear terms i, e. does not declare, the truth fearlessly) should be abandoned from a great distance (i. e. such a judge should be dismissed like one to be avoided from a great distance ); or it is justice that he should declare the truth (the king should see that he does justice).&#xA;fat-free from any misgiving, full of confidence. qui-quickly. fam &amp;amp;c.-Their confidence was so much gained by him that &amp;amp;c. -lying on the lap.&#xA;with his saw-like jaws.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-i. e. you too will meet with the same fate as that of &amp;amp;c. ( die like them).&#xA;-as each liked, each according to his choice. अभिषेo about to be crowned. केनापि हे०- with some object in view; for some purpose. Afa-obs- tructed. -together with our relatives, descen- dants &amp;amp;c.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What is pierced with &amp;ldquo;arrows grows again;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip; but the wound caused by speech in the form of words bad- ly spoken and obscene is never healed. against gr., though found in epic poetry. Mah, Bhár, V, 34. 75, XIII. 104, 83,&#xA;-The Arm, is The sl. is fr412&#xA;P. 152. 111 When a man utters, without cause, in this world, a speech which takes no note of (in which there is no consideration of ) place and time, which is not good for the future, which is disagreeable and which is deroga- tory to one&amp;rsquo;s dignity, it is not a speech but poison itself.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A talented man, though endowed with strength, should not turn another into his enemy: what wise man will needlessly swallow poison, thinking he has a doctor (to save his life)?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A wise man should not, under&#xA;any circumstances (a), give utterance to the reproach of another in an assembly; and even that should not be spoken, though true, which, when said, would cause pain,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He, indeed, is a talented man who does a thing after having discussed it again and again with his well meaning friends and himself carefully () considered its propriety (lit. the ground for doing it) by the power of his own intellect; and he is the abode of wealth and glory.&#xA;भवतं - read भवनं. अन्वया०— hereditary. एवं गते—such being the case, under these circumstances. -Other than the six usual expedients. eo- a big i, e. powerful&#xA;measure.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Men, possessed of varied talent and having good worldly knowledge, are able to deceive even those who are preeminently powerful, as did the rogues a Bráhmana with respect to a goat,&#xA;fire.&#xA;ano-who had taken the vow of keeping the sacred R-over-cast. 50-to ask for a goat.&#xA;-next or coming new-moon-day.&#xA;will offer a sarcifice i, e. the .&#xA;mentioned (recommended) in the S&amp;rsquo;ástras.&#xA;a fat body, stout.&#xA;A qo-I&#xA;-such as is&#xA;To-having&#xA;P. 153-running here and there, geo- came facing him, confronted him, say-of to-day; to.&#xA;413&#xA;day&amp;rsquo;s fall of frost or cold will be useless (i. e. it will have no effect upon us). oqfta &amp;amp;c.-having changed his dress. -( coming before him) by a side way. आहिता ० - आहितः kept up अग्निः येन, बाला०- O you young (foolish) keeper of fire, -against the practice of the world. -a ridiculous deed, what will expose you to laughter.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;: go-are declared to be of equal (equally unholy) touch. afano-represent as,&#xA;Tat. (अध्वनः अन्तरं) a short distance on his way.&#xA;Fat-a Gen. मृतवत्सः -&#xA;-8&#xA;dead calf.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;-a beast, a lower animal. :-a foolish or ignorant person. -will be purified by taking the Pan, or practising the Chá, vow. qo-so called from its being made up of the five products yielded by a cow. They are affai. e. milk, curds, clarified butter, ( ghee) urine and cow-dung.&#xA;is a religious observance or expiatory penance which consists in regulating the daily quantity of food according to the waxing and waning of the moon: thus it consists of fifteen mouthfuls on the full-moon-day, is then diminished by one mouthful every day till it is re- duced to nothing on the new moon-day and is increased again in a like manner in the bright fortnight. See Yàj. Smr. III. 324 et seg. and Man. Smṛ. XI. 217.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;2nd line. Bathing, with the garments on, is prescribed for the removal of his sin.&#xA;go-with intent to go to, in the direction of.&#xA;P. 154. 119. There is no one in this world that is not deceived (i. e. every one is deceived) by the modesty of new servants (as they are anxious to gain the favour of their master, and hence theire modesty ), by the words of guests, by the weepings of amorous ladies and by the&#xA;414&#xA;prolix speeches of designing persons. :-enmity, opposition.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One should not excite the enmity of many (many should not be turned into foes); -great many men,&#xA;-a huge serpent.&#xA;अतिदर्प:- Lit. having great pride ( अतिगतो दर्पो यस्य Fogo-the way directly leading to his hole (the usual entrance to his hole).&#xA;ness of his body.&#xA;कति व्या०-several he killed.&#xA;perforated.&#xA;-on account of the huge- :-was harassed or distressed. प्रभूoon account of the&#xA;great number of the ants. -with his whole body :-can not be disobeyed i. e. will necessarily be acted on. fager-turning me into, treating me as an enemy.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-Having smeared my body with blood brought (from some source) in such a way that the spies of the enemy might be convinced of it (might believe it to be true). gofro-by a well planned act; in a well-organised manner. go-made them favourable, having gained their favour. &amp;amp;c.-I have known it well ( am con- vinced of this) that we shall not gain our object by any other means.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Men, well-versed in policy, call that a fort which is provided with the means of escape, while that which is destitute of the means of egress is a prison in the form of a fort.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-nor should you feel any pity for me.&#xA;P. 155. When war breaks out, one should look upon (consider) one&amp;rsquo;s servants, although dear as life, desirable protected and fondled, as dry fuel (i. e. who must sacrifice their lives for the king).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One should always take care of one&amp;rsquo;s servants as of life and nourish them like one&amp;rsquo;s own body for the&#xA;415&#xA;sake of one day, that they should be serviceable to him one day) viz, that on which there is an encounter with the&#xA;enemy.&#xA;:-Be forbidden or prevented (from following the line of policy determined upon ). go-vain or useless hence a sham quarrel, उच्छृङ्खल० - उद्गता शृङ्खला a chain, hence restraint : with unrestrained i. e. desparaging words. Put-punishment, fo-who acted as the enemy&amp;rsquo;s spy.&#xA;-the calamity that had overtaken the minister, guara-It is through (by the force of) religious merit that an enemy is found who being frightened takes to flight?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When an enemy is in the act of fleeing that is one weak point (a fit opportunity to attack him ); another is when he takes shelter in another place when he is easily subdued, the royal servants being engaged (and therefore not prepared to resist an attack ).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;An enemy cannot be subdued even by gods without taking advantage of his weak point. सम्प्राप्य- having discovered. See I, 116,&#xA;अधःपरि० &amp;ndash; Having surrounded it from below. बन्दिभिः - by the bards, -i. e. before they take shelter &amp;amp;c.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;An ennmy taking shelter behind even a hedge cannot be conquered by one desirous of conquest; what to say then of one who has taken shelter in a fort furnished with excellent provisions.&#xA;P. 156. ao-When things were being thus dis- cussed, at this conjuncture, rar &amp;amp;c.-without get-&#xA;e स्मद्वृत्तान्ता&#xA;ting any tidings or information about us.&#xA;-as they&#xA;came (i, e. without accomplishing any thing to mark their coming).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;-The sign or characteristic of talent (here the faculty of judgment and determination).&#xA;416&#xA;at &amp;amp;c.-Therefore, better is a thing not undertaken than to have it obstructed in the very beginning. fagro-full of (lit. possessed by) amazement, rataito&amp;ndash; The day gone by, yesterday. युष्मव्यापा० - युष्माभिव्यापादिताः gs killed by you.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A man inferior in power should not, if he desires his own welfare, wish even in mind to stand (even think of standing) on hostile terms with one more powerful; for, in this world one who acts the part of a reed is not killed; while it is clear that one who behaves like a moth (reck- lessly rushes upon danger) suffers destruction.&#xA;341770-By giving presents.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;-on seeing i, e. discovering. ::-Ins. abs.; if it (life) be saved.&#xA;To-suspecting me to be your partisan.&#xA;my protection or refuge.&#xA;rof-&#xA;-In some eds only four&#xA;ministers are mentioned. See p. 83.&#xA;P. 157.&#xA;ft-Lit, without any consideration or&#xA;thinking about the matter; at once.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A weak enemy should be killed before he attains power; for, after he gains power according to his own valour he becomes invincible or one difficult to be conquered. स्वस्य पौरुषं स्व०; तरय बलं स्व० लं; प्राप्तं स्व० येन.&#xA;130, Since (a) an opportunity presents itself but once to a man eagerly expecting it, it is difficult for him to get it again if he does not wish to do a thing at the proper time.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See the funeral pile that is lighted up and my hood that is broken, the friendship which is re-formed after being destroyed grow not again by means of affection.&#xA;fo-Though engaged in cultivating his lands. soro-at the close of the sultry seasen. i-dis-&#xA;417&#xA;tressed or oppressed with heat,&#xA;g-stretched over.&#xA;-having&#xA;This should be प्रसृतै; or read प्रसारितवृद्द as one word. क्षेत्र०- The deity (presiding over) the field. formed this resolution. :- -a shallow vessel or earthen&#xA;pot. -having offered. दीनार—a gold coin. निरूप्य सम्प्रo-same as अवधार्यं above.&#xA;(Cf. the Mar. word a ). having appointed. इत्येवं&#xA;jP. 158. अमुक्त० न मुक्तममुक्तं अमुक्तं जीवितं येन; not losing his life. ao-with fangs containing deadly venom. संस्कृत: - burnt in the due form, तथैव सम० thought that to&#xA;be so.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He, who does not show favour to those who seek his protection, loses what is actually in his possession, as did the swans in Padmasara,&#xA;conflict.&#xA;-formed of gold, golden.&#xA;-a quarrel, a&#xA;&amp;ndash;such being the case, Your Majesty&#xA;is the authority i. e. is to order what is to be done next. तारस्वरेण — with a loud voice, loudly. यौवनो - Through the infatuation or inconsideration of youth.&#xA;P. 159. o-costly, of great value. a. कण्ट०- अविद्यमानाः कण्टकाः यस्मिन् without thorns ie rival kings or dangerous enemies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A story is told that an enemy who sought protec- tion was duly honoured by a pigeon and presented with his flesh.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A certain fowler (lit, bird-hunter) who was of mean behaviour and like the god of death to animals, used to roam over a great forest.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He had no friend, &amp;amp;e.; he was left by them all on account of his cruel deeds,&#xA;418&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;2nd line. and who cause terror to creatures, are like serpents.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;sig:-one day.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Now, while he was in the forest all the directions became dark with clouds and there was a heavy fall of rain with violent wind as at the time of the destruction of the world,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;मुहुर्मु०-again and again, constantly. अन्वेषयन्- looking for, seeking. This should properly be erfasan. afto-shelter.&#xA;P. 160. 141-2. When he saw for an hour that the sky had the stars clearly displayed (i. e. that the rain had ceased) he got to a tree &amp;amp;c. &amp;amp;c.-I seek his protec- tion, F-pierced with, shivering from, cold, re- गतं चेतः यस्य fainting from.&#xA;143,&#xA;144,&#xA;-who had lived there for a long time. -void of interest.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A woman, who is devoted to her husband, who considers her husband as her life, and who is intent on (takes delight in) doing what her husband likes and what is to his interest &amp;amp;c.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;fr-what is measured, little.&#xA;151.-even by offering your life, at the cost of&#xA;your life,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;शाकुनिक:- शकुनैर्जीवतीति One who lives by killing birds, a fowler, afro-he is suffering from cold and hunger; offer worship (welcome) to him.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;183. हर्षा०—transported with joy. घनं - dense, बहुनिर्वै &amp;ndash; full of great disgust (for the world.)&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;184. विरता० - with all desire gone. निर्दग्धाo-his sins entirely burnt up i, e. being quite free from sin. conferring a benefit, doing a favour. g-omit a. What to say then that it (well-being) is desired of one seeking protection. विप्रकृत-injured, harassed by. पुष्टये भ०- will be for adding to our prosperity and will show us their weak points.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;185. fa-just for the good or benefit of one. विवदन्तः &amp;ndash; should be विवदमानाः, as वद with वि is Atm in this&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;sense.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;fugo&amp;ndash;whose only wealth was the presents or dona tions given by others. qfara:-who was destitute of, i. e. had not the means of enjoying, such pleasures as the use of fine garments, ointments &amp;amp;c. -covered over with hair, beard, and nails grown.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;P. 164.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;soro&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;प्ररूढo&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;:-whose body was blighted up&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;fo-a couple&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;-from the time they&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;with cold, heat, wind, rain and the like. of young cows or calves. were young. यवस-grass.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;संवर्ध्य - having fostered or&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;reared up पुष्टिं नीतं-nourished बन्धनपा–a rope or cord for tying them, geo-read in the com.- प्रविरला तीक्ष्णदन्तानां ( तीक्ष्णाश्च ते दन्ताश्च तेषां ) पंक्तिर्यस्य having thin rows of sharp (pointed) teeth.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;nose prominent or raised up.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;of his eyes clearly displayed. veins.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;low cheeks.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;o-with the bridge of his&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Co-with the red corners -with protuberant&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;-with limbs depressed. &amp;ndash;with hol- a &amp;amp;c.-whose body, hair and beard were&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;tawny like fire well kindled with sacrificial oblations. क्रूर० - क्रूराणि कमोणि यस्य whose actions are cruel. जातप्र-&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;:-who was inspired with confidence.422&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;who eats only at the time of the sixth meal i, e. on the evening of every third day (as an expiatory act.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;See&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Man, Smr. XI. 200. ). -having the same&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;एककार्यों object in view (viz. to do injury to the Brahmana ). कालमन्वे० - Looking for an opportunity. नैष न्यायः-this is not proper (for you to do ). -would wake up. Si-useless, to no purpose, an obstacle. ST0-as they were thus disputing, each saying that he would accomplish his object first, and a quarrel ensued.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;-being careful or on his guard.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;1 P. 165. -By meditating on and repeating the spells pertaining to the proper (lit. desired) deities,&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;guio with a stick or club raised or held up.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;186. -weak or vulnerable points. -keep secret,&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;देव० - Lit. देवस्येव शक्तिर्यस्य; having the strength or power of a god.-on account of a serpent residing in the cavity (lit. the ant-hill) of his stomach.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;421&#34;&gt;T. e. a stranger coming.&#xA;P. 161. 154.&#xA;-his sin.&#xA;-do not show&#xA;hatred to him,&#xA;-Aor. 2nd pers. sing. A.; the Aor., with the aug.&#xA;dropped, is often used with the prohibitive particle in&#xA;the sense of the Impera,&#xA;&amp;hellip;..T-thinking that&#xA;419&#xA;he took your beloved a prisoner अहं स्वकृतैरेव प्राक्तनैः कर्मभिः I am caught by the bonds of actions done by myself in a previous life.&#xA;156.&#xA;due to or caused by my imprisonment. &amp;amp;c.-having fixed your mind on duty.&#xA;157. fo-conforming to duty and propriety.&#xA;:-approaching him humbly or modestly.&#xA;158.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-you should not be uneasy at heart; you are in your own house here.&#xA;161, 2nd line.-Warm your limbs here unsuspiciously and being free from fear.&#xA;162,-We all, tenants of the forest, live upon what we get by chance (a lit, what comes to our hand). I have nothing in my possession by which I can satisfy your appetite.&#xA;163. One maintains a thousand men, another &amp;amp;c.; while I, an insignificant creature, not having done any meri- torious deed, find it difficult to maintain my own self&#xA;even.&#xA;164. -in a house (a house-holder&amp;rsquo;s stage of life) beset with troubles of various kinds.&#xA;165. I will, therefore, so use my body of miserable existence (or, which is maintained with difficulty) that I shall not have to say, when a guest comes, that I have nothing to give him.&#xA;166. af-will satisfy.go-wait for a short space of time.&#xA;P. 162. 167. धर्मात्मा - धर्मः आत्मा यस्य he of a charita- ble nature. Having spoken these words, the bird, of a charitable disposition, went round the fire and entered it as he would his own dwelling.&#xA;168.fo-greatly affected by the feeling of pity.&#xA;169.&#xA;420&#xA;certainly he does not love himself,&#xA;-is enjoyed ( its consequence is suffered ).&#xA;वा&#xA;170. I, therefore, evil-minded (qqi ar fada) and given to wicked deeds (पापं कर्म पा० तस्मिन् रतः ) taking de- light in doing evil deeds) &amp;amp;c.&#xA;171. Surely this magnanimous Kapota, thus offering up his flesh, has well shown (set) to me, a wicked creature, an example of an opposite nature (i, e, of kindness, mercy).&#xA;172. From to-day, I will mortify my body, denying it comforts of every kind, just as the hot season dries up small quantities. ( reservoirs) of water,&#xA;173 Bearing (exposing myself to) cold, wind and heat, with my limbs emaciated and dirty (regardless of the beauty of person) I will devote myself to the discharge of high religious duties by observing fasts of various kinds. 174. -The small stick fixed in the cage as a perching rod.&#xA;176. fat fo-what benefit is a woman to get by continuing to live.&#xA;177. कुलपूजा - read कुलं पूजा separately. Pride ( or self- respect), vanity, egotism, high birth, respect at the hands of relatives and power to command menials and servants- all these vanish at widowhood.&#xA;178. कृपणं piteously. दुःखमस्याः संजातमिति दुःखिता भृशं दु:०&#xA;. excessively afflicted with grief,&#xA;179. -celestial, heavenly. fan-scated in a celestial vehicle or balloon i. e. transformed into a god.&#xA;P. 163. 180. He, too, having obtained a heavenly (resplendent) body, spoke the following words which were true to their meaning.&#xA;प्राक्पुण्य०-&#xA;182. The deified Kap. enjoyed happiness &amp;amp;c. q That was the result of their previous meritorious deeds.&#xA;421&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;233-i-e-what-is-left-of-him-after-all-although-so-exaled-similarly-where-is-sagara-who-fixed-the-bounds-of-the-sea-sagara-was-a-king-of-ayo--dhya-of-the-solar-race-and-a-remote-ancestor-of-ráma-he-was-so-called-because-when-born-he-was-affected-with-poison-sa-with-and-gara-poison-his-sons-while-engaged-in-the-search-of-the-sacrificial-horse-excavated-the-earth-and-the-tremendous-chasm-thus-formed-was-filled-with-water-and-came-to-be-known-as-the-ságara-or-sea&#34;&gt;in every limb. Tato &amp;amp;c.-Although treated with vari- ous appliances and the use of medicines prescribed in good medical works by eminent physicians, having various remedies at command, he could not be restored to health ( or cured ). स्वास्थ्य० – स्वस्थस्य भावः the state of being restored to one&amp;rsquo;s original state, aft-enjoy the fruit of the actions done in the previous life or lives. वैदेशि० - विदेशे भवः तस्य foreigner or stranger निजवि०- the fruits of her own past deeds. go-accepting the command with the words &amp;lsquo;so it will be done&amp;rsquo;. aftard at: with a small retinue or number of attendants, प्रतिपय - having accepted or considered as आवासरक्षा०- having told him to take care of or look after the house, o-having done buying and selling business, -resting his head on.&#xA;423&#xA;P. 166. -torment, trouble, -contami- nated, defiled. To-full of gold coin. no-disclosed, laid bare. fuo-by drinking mustard seeds boiled with old sour rice-gruel. fae-concealed behind the branches (of trees). -touching or affecting their vital parte. अव्यङ्ग - free from bodily defect, विविधो० — better read fafiqo-the enjoyment of the fruit of her deeds in a previous life,&#xA;and that was done accordingly at fao-with a con-&#xA;i. e. Sthirajîvi&amp;rsquo;s life was spared.&#xA;cealed or inward smile.&#xA;187. विमानना-disrespect understand, भवति after this.&#xA;to-destroyed with the root (i, e. the king).&#xA;188. Coustrne — ये हितं- ते मित्ररूपा रिपवो हि इति विचक्षणैः संभा- aq. Those, who, disregarding benificial advice, act ad- versely (or in a manner contrary to one&amp;rsquo;s interest) are certainly (R) enemies in the form of friends.&#xA;189. A king, who, having got imprudent (or impolitic) ministers, acts against time and place, loses also what he actually possesses, just as darkness vanishes at sunrise. 3for-not, able to serve any purpose.&#xA;P. 167. go—having me in stock (or service). समुद्धर्तु - to resene me from misery. वैरयात०-for the re- quital of enmity or retaliation.&#xA;-clever in speaking feigned or pretended (deceptive) words. - born in the species of.&#xA;190. fan-speaking out what was to the interest of his master.&#xA;-By me residing in the middle of the cave, ryant faro-reflecting over my secret thoughts (or aims) and other things. -will take precautions, will be on their guard. शुचिः honest. भवस्पाद - भवतः पादो&#xA;424&#xA;भवत्पादौ भव० पद्मे इव तयोः रजः तेन पवित्रीकृता तनुर्येन यस्य वा my body rendered pure by the dust of your lotus-like feet, a&#xA;-when his request was acceded to.&#xA;-excellent,&#xA;best. प्रकृष्टमांसा०-a sumptuous meal of flesh. पोप्य०-be- ing fed or nourished.&#xA;191. -the fowler, the man who fixed the&#xA;nets.&#xA;P. 168. catching birds.&#xA;-engaged in the avocation of -(whose possession is) fraught&#xA;with danger. राज्ञे निवेद० - I will myself present the bird to the king. विकसित ० - नयने च वदनं च नयनवदनं ( स. द्वं० ); fa a 4 whose lotus-like eyes and face brigh- tened. अश्रद्धेय० - अश्रद्धेय च तद् व्याधवचनं च अश्र०नं तस्मिन्प्रत्ययः अश्रद्धेय० - यः अश्र०ः एव ०मात्रं तेन परिगृहीतस्तेन - accepted merely through confidence in the incredible words of a hunter. -on the lofty arched gateway. &amp;ndash;so far;&#xA;this much.&#xA;192. He, who takes action before a thing comes to pass (i. e. provides for the future or takes precaution before- hand), shines (lives happily); he, who does not provide for what is to happen, comes to grief; old age came over me while living here; still I never heard the words of a cave (knew a cave to speak ).&#xA;-Lit. having sharp or piercing nails.&#xA;P. 169. &amp;ndash;Some beast must come &amp;amp;c. fra:-silent, fergo-a line of the footprints of a lion. ज्ञास्यामि - ascertain the truth. फूत्कर्तु - to hiss out. तूष्णीं&#xA;-resuming silence; becoming quiet. Here off is treated as a preposition; also तूष्णीं भूत्वा समय: - agreement, ao &amp;amp;c.-I should address you and that you should call out to me (respond to my call).&#xA;comes.&#xA;when he&#xA;425&#xA;193. Such actions as the movements of the hands and feet and also the speech, of those whose minds are agitated with terror do not proceed; and their tremor is also great ( they tremble greatly ). वेपथु from वेपू+अथु; Cf. श्वयथु fr. श्वि, दवथु from दु &amp;amp;c.&#xA;sai &amp;amp;c.-will become my prey. fa-filled with its echoes. ff-far seeing, fore-sighted, prudent.&#xA;195. heriditary,&#xA;To-descended in order (of generations), fara-not at a distant date, before long.&#xA;P. 170. 196. Wise men should consider them to be enemies in the form of ministers, who, giving up a good line of policy, serve adversely (in a manner opposed to the interest of their master).&#xA;स्वकुलाये - in his own nest,&#xA;197. A man, doomed by fate, makes friends with an enemy, hates and destroys a friend, considers good as evil and an evil thing as beneficial.&#xA;कुलाय० - under the pretext of building a nest, दाहसाध्या- capable of being readilfy burnt or destroyed by fire, auto- a stick from the wood. go-equal to that of falling into Kum. (a kind of hell in which sinners are baked like a potter&amp;rsquo;s vessels). oo v. l. will die in the manner of &amp;amp;c.&#xA;v. l. our meeting.&#xA;198. When a business to be promptly attended to arises and a man delays (its execution), the deities, being angry, undoubtedly put obstacles in his way.&#xA;199. When any action, and especially one about to be attended with fruit, is not done at once, time saps its juice (i. e. it does not prove to be so advantageous when not done in time).&#xA;गृहया०-read&#xA;गृहया० - read गृहाया० when you return home (to your own place). Age-with an easy mind (lit. free from&#xA;426&#xA;anxiety or agitation).&#xA;To not being able to&#xA;get out on account of the door being &amp;ldquo;blocked up.&#xA;P. 171. 200. It is better for men of meritorious deeds to fall into blazing fire than to be in company with their enemies even though it be for an hour.&#xA;w-with the desire of or having an eye to the fruit aimed at (lit. to be obtained in the future).&#xA;201. Even poison swallowed with the object of accom- plishing an end acts like nectar, in the case of all creatures: no hesitation should be made in such a case,&#xA;202. A wise man, even though powerful, should, look- ing for better times, reside even with a mean person, dis- agreeable on account of harsh (lit. thunderbolt-like) words; did not Bhims, possessed of extraordinary strength live, as a cook, in the house of the king of the Matsya coun- try, with his hands occupied in holding the laddle, dirtied with smoke and engaged in troublesome tasks?&#xA;203. A talented man, expecting better days to come, should do the deed he has in his mind, of whatever kind, whether difficult or good or censurable; did not Arjuna whose hands had become hard on account of his touching the thick and flashing string of his bow,, Gândiva, live, with his girdle shining in his sportive dances?&#xA;-the name of the bow of Arjuna, which he had obtained from the god of fire when he assisted him in consuming the Khándavavana, See Mahábhá, I. 225 &amp;amp;c.&#xA;-Arj. so called because he could pull his bow with equal force with either of his hands.&#xA;204. A wise man, earnestly wishing for success, should conceal his own might, although endowed with calibre and energy, and should depend upon the workings of fate, Did not the Majestic son of Dharma (Dharms, the eldest&#xA;427&#xA;Pandava) suffer trouble for a long time in the house of Viràta, together with his brothers who were equal in valour to Indra, Kubera ( the lord of wealth) and Yama? (or although he had at his service his brothers &amp;amp;c.)&#xA;205. The two sons of Mádrt, endowed with beauty and noble birth, and possessed of strength, became the servants of Viràta, being engaged as the keepers of cattle (and horses).&#xA;P. 172. Did not Draupadi rub sandal in the house of the king of the Matsyas, being contemptuously addressed by the ladies in their pride as Sairandhrî ? even she, who, by her matchless beauty, by the qualities of youth, by birth in a noble family and by complexion, was like the goddess of wealth (Lakshmi), was reduced to a miserable condition according to the turn of adverse time (destiny).&#xA;Slokas 202-6 refer to the residence of the Pandavas in the house of Viràta under different disguises. Thus Dharma lived as Kamka, Bhima as Ballava or cook, Arjuna as Brhannatà, Nakula as master of the horses, Sahadeva as a cowherd and Draupadi as Sairandhri, doing menial work. See Tan. 1. p. 11.&#xA;ferro-the vow of lying or standing on the edge of a sword. :-an assemblage or company of. -whose intellect is unobstructed in i. e. penetra- tes or has deep insight into. qr as it really was, in its true state (rightly understood my motive or intention). a-who simply enjoyed the titles of ministers.&#xA;-not versed or skilled in the principles of policy.&#xA;207. A servant, who comes as a deserter from the enemy, disaffected and ready to join their company, should be set down as a spy from his having such duties to perform; he must always be discontented and corrupt,&#xA;428&#xA;209. Enemies strike at their foes whenever they observe them to be careless with regard to their sitting, or lying down, or marching or while engaged in taking drink or food.&#xA;209. Therefore, a wise man should, with every effort and diligently, save his own life, the abode of the collection of three (viz.Dharma, artha and Ka&amp;rsquo;ma); for if he is care- less he is destroyed,&#xA;210. Whom, eating unwholesome things (or, not observing regimen ), do diseases not afflict? (i, e. they afflict every one). What bad minister does not stand guilty of mistakes in policy? whom does wealth not make proud (or haughty)? whom does Death not strike down? and whom do carnal pleasures, when resorted to, not give pain?&#xA;211. The reputation of a greedy person is lost; friend. ship of a wicked man; the family of one who gives up the actions proper for it; virtue of one given to amassing wealth; learning of one addicted to vice; happiness of a miser and the sovereignty of a king who has careless ministers, (i, e, when a man becomes greedy he loses his reputation; a wicked man loses the friendship of others &amp;amp;c.)&#xA;eftero-by being in the company of the enemies.&#xA;-actually.&#xA;212. A wise man should gain his object by placing insult in the front and honour in the back graund (i. e. always expecting insu.t at the hands of others and not honour as long as he has to gain his end ); for folly lies in losing on&amp;rsquo;es object.&#xA;213. A talented man should even bear his enemies on his shoulder, looking to the time (. . when the time is such); many frogs were killed (and devoured) by a huge black-serpent (by doing so).&#xA;429&#xA;-the western mountain. -Lit, whose venom was mild, less deadly. go-How shall I live with easy means of subsistenceor easily maintain myself. धृतिपरी o-as if he was quite patient or contented. 3&#xA;-come to the surface of water; or on the margin or skirt of the pool. -Uncle (a term of address showing affection); cf. the Mará. word II. -as usual, विहरसि - movest about. क्रमः सज्जित: I put myself in an attacking posture. gamai-deeply engaged in their courses of study. faman:-noticed, observed, on-&#xA;-my mind being bewildered by its resemblance, ०जीविकया - gettting thy livelihood through their favour.&#xA;P. 174.&#xA;-better read no lit. on the region of&#xA;his hood i. e, on his large hood. seniority; in order of age.&#xA;-according to&#xA;-room to sit.&#xA;214. A going by sitting on (riding) an elephant, or on horse-back, or driving in a car, or being carried in a ve- hicle borne by men, is not so pleasant to me as my being borne by Mandavisha.&#xA;छद्मना—Cunningly, through craftiness. आहारवैकल्यात्- through want of food. era such is the curse pronounced by the Brahmana i. e. I cannot eat without permission,&#xA;-Unceasingly, continuously.&#xA;215. These frogs of various kinds have been secured by me with a stratagem; how long will they not be ex- hausted when devoured by me?&#xA;with his mind led astray (his power of per- ception obscured) with affected words (by Mand.)- 4-ridden by.&#xA;216. यथा वायोस्मि why I allow myslf to be ridden by or used as their vehicle by.&#xA;8&#xA;430&#xA;P. 175. अन्यासक्त० - अन्यस्मिन् आसक्तं मनो यस्याः सा ; with her mind attached to another. faz-a paramour. ga&#xA;-a kind of sweetmeat (made of flour mixed with milk,&#xA;sugar, cocoanut &amp;amp;c. ). -without the knowledge of भर्तुश्रौ०— her husband, 30-whose ready wit was roused or called up; or who had presence of mind ( meaning inborn). Tof-for this reason-she thought to her- self- If I offer these to the goddess &amp;amp;c. -hav- ing performed such acts as bathing the goddess, applying to her rubbed sandal, offering garlands of flowers, incense, oblations and other things. f-respectfully or reverently asked. Aor. of the cau. of with fa. कृतकं च तद्वचनं च कृतकवचनं तेन वश्वितं मानसं यस्या:; whose mind was misled (who was duped) by the artificially uttered words of her husband.&#xA;नाई&#xA;L&#xA;&amp;amp;c.—I do not see at all; I have become totally blind. सुतरां compar. of सु. देवीप्रसा०-i. e. this is the result of the favour of. -come close or within reach, पाणि - heels, विविधा ०-of different tastes, व्यग्रह०-distracted at heart, fa-contrary to expectation, disagreeable, untoward.-wishing to conceal his real form ( as giving a clue to his inward thoughts). gefra his evil purpose or wicked design.&#xA;P. 176. 217. - when burning; 2nd line, But the wind which is gentle but charged with frost destroys even the roots.&#xA;TET: of great mental strength or fortitude.&#xA;218. The greatness of the great, who wear the ornament of wise policy, lies in this that they do not give up what is undertaken even in a calamity giving rise to difficulties. After-v. 7. even though overtaken by difficulties.&#xA;219. Nothing, indeed, is begun by the weak-minded (lit, low men) for fear of obstacles; mediocres begin a thing&#xA;431&#xA;but desist (from their undertaking) when hampered by obs- tacles; but those possessed of excellent merits, (men of the best sort) although obstructed by a thousandfold difficulties do not abandon what they have once begun, with fa is Par.&#xA;220. ऋणशेषं-part or remnant of a debt. निःशेषं कृत्वा - baving totally removed it. ef-does not come to grief.&#xA;eife-bears fruit, comes to a prosperous termination or is crowned with success. &amp;amp;c.-valour alone does not lead to the accomplishment of an object..&#xA;221. न हि हताः are not really killed सुहताः-are to- tally killed (so as not to rise again).&#xA;-talent, political insight.&#xA;222. When a man destined to prosper undertakes s thing, his intellect expands (is able to take a full view of the business to be accomplished ), his memory becomes strong; his policy, leading to the desired results, is not thwarted; his speculative reasoning (or, foresight ) proves successful; his mind attains loftiness and he takes delight in doing laudable deeds. folde&#xA;aq &amp;amp;c.-Sovereignty is obtained by a man endowed with (unerring) policy, munificence, &amp;amp;c.&#xA;P. 177. 223. A man, who takes delight in the com- pany of a person who is munificent, brave and wise (learned), becomes meritorious (accomplished ); having merits he gets wealth and from wealth majesty; possessed of majesty he can enforce command and thence acquires kingdom.&#xA;० फलाति-read oलानि. अनुकृत्येन - acting in conformity with the wishes of the enemies; अनु कृत्यं यस्य or better read त्वया नु by you going there as a 4 or a malcon tent (a man432&#xA;who deserts his master being ill-treated by him; cf. Kám, Nit, XII. 22.&#xA;-humouring him (lit. having&#xA;entered his heart).&#xA;22. Even when an object (such as the destruction of an enemy) is capable of being gained by stringent (or forcible) means, it is both good and proper to resort to it from the beginning. (For even) the best of trees which has a lofty top, which is the very essence of the forest and which is fit to be treated with consideration even by the respectable, is cut down (as when one has to gain one&amp;rsquo;s end viz. to make a road through a forest ). A Ms. reads the sec. 1. as&amp;hellip; भूतो जनानां&amp;hellip; पार्थिवेन्द्रः.&#xA;faraftan &amp;amp;c.-what is the use of saying that which, afterwards, is unaccompained (unsupported) by action or which it is not easy to accomplish afterwards.&#xA;225. Construe :- अनिश्चितै&amp;hellip; उक्ता गिरः फलैः विसंवादमुपागताः सत्यः&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-The words spoken by those who are not resolute, who shrink from a determind effort and who betray (show) hundreds of faults successively (a), when failing to attain their end (when not corresponding with fruit), become an object of laughter among men.&#xA;ogg-trifling, unimportant, TT: &amp;amp;c.-disregard should not be shown i, e, they should be promptly executed.&#xA;226. Some men, who with careless minds neglect a duty to be done, saying-&amp;lsquo;I can do this,&amp;hellip;this is of small importance; this can be done without an effort; what anxiety with regard to this,-experience the pain of misery easy to obtain (so natural) in times of adversity.&#xA;227. One can sleep with an easy mind in a house &amp;amp;c. the serpent in which is taken a captive or bound up. -better read ag in which a serpent is always seen,&#xA;433&#xA;228. How can there be happiness, which must find room in a heart full of restlessness () (i, c. where it can not exist) so long as those, who are earnestly anxions to maintain (lit. are ardently fond of :) their self-respect, pride and valour, have not accomplish- ed (lit. gone to the other side of) their purposes, which are momentous on account of the object to be gained being attainable by mighty efforts, for the accomplishment of which blessings have been given by relatives and friends (lit. loving i. e. interested persons), which depend upon wise policy, the spirit of adventure and loftiness of mind and which come up to the height of desire (fulfil ambition).&#xA;P. 178. &amp;amp;c.-The work undertaken by whom has come to a successful end. This should better have been अवसितारब्धकार्यस्य अञ्चल - with the royal umbrelia, the throne and royalty ever unshaken.&#xA;229. T-such qualities as giving protection to subjects and the others.&#xA;230. The king who has a liking for merits, dislike (aversion) to vices and affection for good servants, enjoys for a long time royalty, characterised by waving chámaras and banners and decked with the white umbrella.&#xA;आत्मा व्यंसयि० - allow yourself to be elated or puffed up with; fr. अंसू with वि. यत्कारणं - since, for. वंशारो० दुरोराहा- It is as difficult to ascend (manage, secure ) royalty (the goddess of) as it is to climb up a bamboo tree. oro-&#xA;-taking delight in falling off (vanishing) in a moment she is difficult to be held fast (made firm) although held up (secured) with hundreds of efforts. प्रशस्ता० - म्भिनी- Although cleverly propitiated she deceives in the end. fagao-flying to (attracting) the minds of many, like वानo the monkey-species which is also विद्रुता०-ie. विद्रुतमनेक- Raat; whose unsteady (lit. not fixed on one object)&#xA;434&#xA;पद्मपत्री०&#xA;minds are differently attracted. qo-who does not&#xA;embrace any one firmly like water on a lotus-leaf which does not keep contact with (stick to) it. extremely fickle. (2) very fast.&#xA;T—(1)&#xA;I not permanent or steady. दुरुपधारा - दुर्गन उपचारों यस्याः; difficult to be served or waited upon; (2) whose bite is difficult to be cured. सन्ध्याभ्र० - Like the line of evening clouds she is मुहूर्त&amp;mdash; (1) whose attachment is momentary (2) whose red colour lasts for a short time. -(1) naturally evanescent or transitory; (2) naturally fragile, easily broken. like the nature of a snake, uzo-vanishing after be- ing seen for a moment.&#xA;232.&#xA;dag &amp;amp;c.-one should direct one&amp;rsquo;s mind to difficulties . e, one should expect or foresee difficulties and take precautions. -should be set on or directed to. Excepting this the verse is the same as V. 65,&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-No one is, indeed, beyond the reach of&#xA;(unassailable by) calamities.&#xA;232. q-restriction, confinement.&#xA;ai-of the&#xA;Yadavas, aro-teaching of dancing by Arjuná, See&#xA;supra sl. 203.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-Man, in this world, puts up with every thing, in obedience to the power of fate (lit. time ); for other particulars See V. 66.&#xA;233.-i. e. what is left of him after all, although so exaled. Similarly, where is Sagara, who fixed the bounds of the sea! Sagara was a king of Ayo- dhya, of the solar race and a remote ancestor of Ráma. He was so called because, when born, he was affected with poison (Sa with, and gara poison). His sons, while engaged in the search of the sacrificial horse, excavated the earth and the tremendous chasm thus formed was filled with water and came to be known as the Ságara or sea.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;-he-outwardly-means-1-nobility-of-birth-really--2-the-family-i-belong-to&#34;&gt;435&#xA;P. 179. :-Prthu, son of Vena. He was pro- duced from the right arm of his dead father. He was a great king and the earth received its name Pṛthvi from him. See Pṛthu for other particulars in Apte&amp;rsquo;s S. E. dic- tionary. :-The son of Sûrya and the progenitor of the solar race; See Rag. I, 12. See A.&amp;rsquo;s Dic, T-Surely; were they not? -They were called into existence or prominence and laid low-( destroyed).&#xA;23. Yuvanás&amp;rsquo;va.&#xA;A great king of the solar race, son of -Victorious over the three worlds. सत्यत्रतः - सत्यं व्रतं यस्य; lit, who observed the vow of truth- fulness. Name of Dharma, the eldest Pandava.&#xA;A king of the lunar race, the son of A&amp;rsquo;yus and grandson of Purûravas and father of Yayâti. He was a powerful and pious king. He was temporarily raised to the post of Indra when the latter lay concealed under waters to stone for his sin of Bráhman murder (for he had killed Vṛtra who was a Brahmana ). Anxious to win the love of Indránt, he, at her desire, caused himself to be conveyed to her house in a palanquin borne by the seven sages. On his way be asked the sages to move on quickly saying Sarpa, Sarpa. At this Agastya got angry and cursed him to be a Sarpa or serpent&amp;rsquo;, and he dropped down in aserpentine form from which he was relieved by Tudhishthira.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-These, who shared with Indra his seat, with their chariots and best of elehants, are thought to be so made by the great Kâla and also taken off from the world,&#xA;235. That king (any king), his ministers &amp;amp;c. were seen (brought under his influence) by (Fate) and&#xA;destroyed,&#xA;-unsteady like the ears of a rutting elephant, -solely intent on doing justice.&#xA;436&#xA;तावद् - In the first place; or एष तावद् as for him, he &amp;amp;c. argo-by the influence of the particular hour of time. fa-alienated, separated from.&#xA;129. Of kings whose minds are set on war, the treasure is exhausted &amp;amp;c. -with the enemy (Meghavarna ).&#xA;130. The self born (Brahmá) has declared that policy should begin with &amp;amp;c. and end with Danda or war, (forcible measures); 3 is the worst of them all.&#xA;P. 180. 131. Works, accomplished by means of a policy of peace, never produce bad consequences. Like the minds of the good they always contribute to pleasure.&#xA;132. The wise man who employs the policy of punish- ment &amp;amp;c.-is like the man who drinks the decoction of patola (3 Mar.) in a bilious affection when it can be easily put down by means of sugar.&#xA;133. quo-the rustling of leaves. (i. e. that are so cautious).&#xA;-by gentle means.&#xA;134. Is not the lotus-plant scorched up by the falling of snow or frost &amp;amp;c.&#xA;135. He wades gently through water out of compassion for creatures (lest they might be hurt by his treadings). Oh, the acquatic bird, crane, is very righteous!! (i. e. the crafty bird does it simply to delude and destroy his enemies the fish.&#xA;136.&#xA;-whose fever is to be reduced by perspira- tion being induced. See supra sl. 27. -even a wicked enemy can be subdued by means of treachery.&#xA;137. Since even an enemy, pre-eminent by valour, is Overcome &amp;amp;c.&#xA;138. &amp;amp;c,-who is desirous of a kingdom and is powerful.&#xA;437&#xA;139.&#xA;One should render the chief person on the side of the enemy an object of suspicion (or, win him over to one&amp;rsquo;s side) by false (cunningly written) writings and liberal gifts of money, as Chanakya did Rakshasa.&#xA;Rakshasa, the minister of the Nandas, wishing to restore the Nanda dynasty entered into an alliance with Malayaketu, the son of Parvataka, and planned an expedition against Kusumapura, the capital of Chandra- gupta. Chanakya, however, by his stratagems succeeded in making him an object of supicion to the prince who dismissed him from his service afterwards.&#xA;140. A king should seduce the army (of the enemy) by bribery, since it can then be easily overpowered, like good timber when eaten through by worms.&#xA;P. 181..141.&#xA;See IV. sl. 108 p. 36.&#xA;रक्ष्यः - should be prevented. उपप्र०—attracted or seduc ed by bribes.&#xA;142. A man, overpowered (or swayed) by greed, looks to money and not to the calamity (his action leads to) &amp;amp;c.&#xA;143. A wise king satisfies his enemy to remove his desire (to do evil) by gentle means &amp;amp;c.. For Vádara see IV. p. 8. sl. 26. and notes.&#xA;father (so&#xA;144. An enemy may be the killer of his cruel ); but even he, when lured by bribes, confidence in and deliver himself up to his enemy.&#xA;145.&#xA;will repose&#xA;:-(1) Stationed in a fort; (2) living in a&#xA;difficult place ( fishes).&#xA;-Men avoid giving bribes &amp;amp;c.&#xA;146. See supra sl. 62.&#xA;P. 86. 147. R-for ftat. When a king employs other means than force in the case of an enemy, the latter,&#xA;438&#xA;knowing him to be a coward, marches against him of his own accord (even though unprovoked ).&#xA;148. 1st line.-What is the use of that wealth, though splendid (or, increasing) which is obtained without the display of valour !&#xA;149. Wealth is certainly mentally possessed by every one; but in reality it is possessed by those who follow a very rigorous policy (lit. inflict severe punishment).&#xA;150. 2nd line:-But it is enjoyed, like a harlot, by those who are industrious and who pay money in the form of valour in a battle.&#xA;151. द्विषतां मूर्धसु पादम् अदत्वा पुरुषः श्रियं नाश्रुते, A man does not enjoy (or, get) wealth without placing his foot on the heads of his enemies, variegated with the jewels in their crowns and with their rays spreading upwards.&#xA;152. Wealth is drawn to themseves (by men) with arms which are of the size of the trunk of a powerful elephant and which are reddish brown by the bright rays of the shining (a) sword drawn in haste. See Kám,&#xA;Nit, XIII, 14.&#xA;153. The wealth of the enemy reduced to submission by being overpowered by valour becomes, of her own accord, the wife of one, although gone to sleep on the lap of another (the enemy).&#xA;154. A man, always trying to rise, should adopt the course of action of the lion and enjoy the Sr of the enemy by seizing her by the hair (forcibly) as one does an im- modest woman. See Kám, Nit. XIII. 11.&#xA;-advocating the object to be gained as de-&#xA;pending on &amp;lsquo;force&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;P. 183. -seizes, attacks. :-a member of a species attacks another of the same species.&#xA;439&#xA;156. Those, who, in this world, being destitute of mercy a full of apprehension, strike those who utter words of pity, who have sought their protection and who have received many wounds, go to Raurava and other hells. Another reading of the 2nd line is g भये सुखे वा.&#xA;157.&#xA;158.&#xA;159.&#xA;-rich in Dak. and other things.&#xA;See IV. 22.&#xA;Even the crows do not eat the flesh of those, when dead, who, being honoured and having gained their, object, do not become grateful.&#xA;P. 184. 160. When unknown persons (whose cha- racter is not known) enter the fort of a king, there is no doubt that enemies also quickly enter it.&#xA;arms.&#xA;-The cage in the form of the valour of their&#xA;161. -inborn, natural. foto-a jewel serving as a lamp.&#xA;162.&#xA;:-Kubera i, e. whose wealth came from Kubera, See IV. 85.&#xA;परिग्रहा०-even against the advice of my followers or ministers. ferro-why should Sthir, say much.&#xA;-He outwardly means-(1) nobility of birth; really- (2) the family I belong to.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;163&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As is the destiny of a man so are his inclinations or thoughts; such is bis mind, such are his impressions and such his servants, (i. e, every thing conforms to the will of fate).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A man in distress will lay all his grivances be fore a king; &amp;amp;c. a-guilty of a crime or going wrong.&#xA;440&#xA;mago-TJifficult or dangerous position of his fort (which afforded no means of escape).&#xA;-has all&#xA;the disadvantages of a fort as described before. Tert- weak, of feeble structure.&#xA;P. 185. i -with regard to me.&#xA;हित:- also he inwardly means - अहितः च तत्वानुरक्तः- (1) really attached to you; (2) a&#xA;truth; true to my mission.&#xA;177-8. see p. 80; 218-9.&#xA;go-attached to&#xA;ala-for so long a time.&#xA;P. 186. 179. 2nd 1.-These grow again and again; therefore, no remnant should be left.&#xA;180.-see supra 221.&#xA;ago-This is the result of Your Majesty&amp;rsquo;s glory indicating future prosperity. -mere executers of duties assigned to us.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;see 222.&#xA;तत्तव भवि०- I knew by the errors of judgment committed by the enemies of you, who were destined to prosper, that they were doomed by fate. fa-shrewd, sagacious. fo whether they are destined to prosper or to be ruined.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;see II. 84.&#xA;iga:-turned towards i. e. favourable. fo-endowed with sound judgment or unerring talent.&#xA;P. 187. 183. argo-wish to raise to prosperity. o-endow him with right understanding.&#xA;Mahàbhà. V. 35, 40.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;हिंसितुमि० — wish to destroy or ruin विश्ले०- deprive him of talent.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When talent is clouded and destruction is at hand, a wrong policy, which appears as right policy, never leaves the mind.&#xA;NOTES.&#xA;80:-&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४ लब्धप्रणाशम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/04_labdhapraNAsham/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/kAle/02_Notes/04_labdhapraNAsham/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TANTRA IV.&#xA;P. 189.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;the loss of what was gained; hence the book descriptive of it.&#xA;HERTY 10-Loc. Abs. He alone whose intellect (presence of mind) does not fail him when occasions (lit, things or works to be accomplished) arise (&amp;hellip; under trying circumstances), surmounts (extricates himself from) a difficulty, as did the monkey when in the midst of water. y no may also be taken as a simple Loc. One&amp;rsquo;s intellect as regards works to be accomplished &amp;amp;c. The Abs., however, is better.e&#xA;-The story runs thus (lit, is heard from mouth -near the shore of. -gives&#xA;to mouth, related). to the pres. the sense of the past tense; Pán. III. 2. 118. - jagged or pointed, hence frightful मुखं यस्य. ०सनाथे - Lit. having a master ( नाथ ); hence full of very soft sand. न्यविशत्- विश् with नि is more generally used in the sense of &amp;ldquo;encamping, as in&#xA;welcome.&#xA;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A guest, who comes after the daily sacrifice (Vais&amp;rsquo;va- deva) is performed, whether welcome or hateful, whether a fool or a learned man, leads (the householder) to heaven. -a daily sacrifice offered with fresh food to all the gods before the morning and evening meals; see Manu III. 84, 121.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One should not ask a guest coming at the close of the Vais, and on the occasion of a S&amp;rsquo;ráddha (an anniver- sary, fafe ) his Charana (the school or branch of the Veda to which he belongs, such as that of the A&amp;rsquo;pastamba &amp;amp;c.&amp;rsquo;; far-sacred knowledge (i. e. of the Vedas and their angas, ) &amp;amp;c.442&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To-Wearied or tired by the fatigue of a long journey.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;:-Unhonoured, not hospitally received. fa-breathing heavily (being dissatisfied or feeling insulted). fa &amp;amp;c.-The deities and his manes leave him with their faces turned away.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;t-moreover-another-consideration-is-this-that-भणतप---although-i-actually-tell-you-क--of-what-consequence-or-significance--know-that-7-e-be-sure-that-i-will-starve-myself-to-death-see-tant-i-p-44-and-note-thereon-faro-bis-mind-perturbed-or-distracted-by-anxiety&#34;&gt;P. 190. Of this sort, such. -a title of address indicative of affection. ffage-with feelings of joy, affectionately. -full of, saturated with, nectar.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-If you have anything to do with me, your wife, (if you at all care for me, or want me for your wife). -The tasting of nectar is supposed to grant immunity from old age or death. :-has become; is accepted as.&#xA;-Vain or foolish idea (or resolve or obstinacy. ) 6. The mother gives birth to one kind of brothers speech to another. The wise declare that the brother by speech is superior to ( is more important than) the brother by whole blood (lit. born of the same womb.)&#xA;-not complied with or disobeyed (i. e, you have ever complied with my request). ego-Out of love for her. -properly, in your true colours. (i. e. as faithless to me and loving another.)&#xA;7. प्रयच्छसि - goes with वचन and वान्छितं यत् goes with every sentence. Since you do not reply to me joyfully nor do you grant any of my desires; since, for the most part, you heave sighs (indicative of unbearable separation) in quick succession and hot (burning) like flames of fire durning nights, &amp;amp;c. ffo-slackness, coldness, eagerly, lovingly. -O cunning one, O deceiver. R-is certainly abiding in, has taken possession of.&#xA;&amp;ndash;who had flown&#xA;To-having seized or taken hold of his wife&amp;rsquo;s feet (as a mark of submission). into the highest pitch of anger. submissively,&#xA;i-very meekly or&#xA;443&#xA;P. 191. 8. O passionate one, when I have prostrated myself at your feet and have become your servant (am ready to minister to your desires like a slave) why do you, darling of my heart, get angry with me?&#xA;go-with her eyes flooded with tears.&#xA;9. O clever deceiver, that dearly loved one, on whom you have fastened a hundred sweet desires, is, indeed, sta- tioned in your heart, attractive (though she is ) by her feigned affection. One like myself has no admittance here (into your heart ); have done, therefore, with this mockery of falling at my feet.&#xA;t-moreover, another consideration is this that. भणितेपि - although I actually tell you. क:- of what consequence or significance. -know that (7. e. be sure that) I will starve myself to death. See Tant. I. p. 44 and note thereon, faro-bis mind perturbed or distracted by anxiety.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;-the diamond-cement, things joined by which remain indelibly together. See I. 263. u-lit. seizure, grasp; in the case of art it means-the idea they once entertain ( i. e. they never give it up). &amp;amp;c.-How can it be possible for me to kill him? full of dejection, sorrowful. far-long after the usual time, निष्ठुरत० - Very harsh. उपजीव्य - having lived on the bounty of. go-a return of the obligation. गृह० - Even by simply bringing him to our house. प्राय- Pro-There is no atonement (for the sin of this your ingratitude. )&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;An expiatory rite is prescribed by the good (ie. writers of Smrtis) for one who kills a Bráhmana&amp;hellip;for one who breaks his vows&amp;hellip;;but there is none such for the ungrateful, Râmà. IV. 34. 12. Cf. I. 278. The sl. occurs in Tantra 3rd also.&#xA;देवरं - Acc. sing. of देवॄ or देवर.&#xA;444&#xA;P. 192. कलहा०-pre. p. of the den. fr. कल ह. इयती- इयत्परिमाणमस्याः so much, g-Who has drawn the ornamental square figures in powder (of chalk, burnet chaff &amp;amp;c, called in Mar. f) which are usually drawn round the seat and dish or plaintain leaf (for-dining) of a distiguished guest &amp;amp;c. प्रगुणित &amp;amp;o. - who has put on her best ( प्रगुणित excellent ) garments, jewels, rubies and other ornamens suitable for the occasion (or which it is proper to wear &amp;amp;c.); or this may mean-who has kept ready &amp;amp;c. for presentation. In this case dissolve the compound as प्रगुणितानि आभरणानि यया । वन्द-&#xA;TT-A garland hung over a gateway like an arch. त्कण्ठा - उत्कण्ठया सहिता full of eager expectation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A man wiser (than others) should avoid a friend who is of the form of a weaver (i. e. selfish), who, being greedy always keeps pulling towards himself (i. e. secures his own interest). In the case of the weaver-who always draws towards himself the batten and the threads of the weft,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He (a friend is one who) gives and receives in his turn, tells his own secrets and asks (those of his friend), dines at the house of his friend and invites him to dine with himself. These are the six signs of friendship.&#xA;समुद्रान्ते&amp;ndash; On the other side of the sea. अकृतभयः &amp;ndash;with- ont entertaining any fear. Gogo-my body is washed over (deluged) with the billows or waves of water. : -has fallen into my power, is safe in my grip. तिलमात्रं - even a jot वाक्येन in compliance with my wife&amp;rsquo;s word. of-having secured your confidence (lit. having caused you to confide in me ).&#xA;-purified i. e. purged of its impurities; hence sweetened with. a strong desire; usually this means the desire or longing of pregnancy. प्रत्यु० - प्रत्युत्पन्ना मतिर्यस्य ready witted, possessed of presence of mind,&#xA;445&#xA;P. 193.&#xA;without the beart, not having the heart with me. शून्यमविद्यमानं हृदयं यस्य. अनश० तिष्ठति - lit. will rise from, will give up, her fasting. -who had promis- ed to various deities worship with proper materials (for the safety of his life). To-by a prodigious leap,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;aaa-is an anomalous form. It should pro- perly be fara. One should not trust an untrustworthy person, nor one in one&amp;rsquo;s confidence either; for the danger arising from confidence (i. e. a person enjoying one&amp;rsquo;s confidence) cuts off the very roots (of the confider). See Mah, Bha&amp;rsquo;. I. 142 63.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He who wishes to gain over (make friends with) a friend once estranged (lit. affected by ill-feeling, evil- disposed courts (invites) death like a female mule by conceiving.&#xA;&amp;ndash;with abashment, feeling ashamed of himself. afmo-The object I had at heart, my secret motive. if &amp;amp;c.-by some means comes to confide in me. हास्येन - by joking. ते अभि० -I ascertained what you would think of the matter.&#xA;-In the manner of a guest. (The Mara, word qgu is derived from this word; also occurring as प्राघुणे० प्राघुणकं &amp;amp;c.).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What sinful deed will a hungry man not do? Men reduced in wealth become cruel; good dame, tell Priyadar- shana that Ganga, will not again come to the well.&#xA;P. 194. -An introductory particle used at the beginning of tales. Originally it must have meant &amp;ldquo;There is-as the story goes, there lived &amp;amp;c. EPIRI:-ERHIGGà sia: lit, those who take (inherit) a share of the paternal estate; hence all one&amp;rsquo;s relations. See Ya&amp;rsquo;j. S. II. 263. fn:-ha- rassed or teased. T-having mounted on a bucket attached to the water-machine (Mar. 2). -How can I retaliate the injury.&#xA;446&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I consider that man to be born again (after having been dead, as it were, owning to the insults suffered ) who chastises (lit. wrongs in return) both the persons viz. him who has wronged him in times of adversity and him who has laughted at him when in straitened circumstan- ces. Cf. Tant. I. 339.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To gain one&amp;rsquo;s object one should set an enemy against an enemy; and against a powerful one, one more powerful still; for thus) there will be no trouble in bringing about his (the enemy&amp;rsquo;s) destruction; or, when the enemies are destroyed there will be no- (further) moles- tation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A wise ( diplomatic) man should eradicate (root ont) a powerful enemy, harassing him by a powerful one that he may gain happiness, as one removes a pointed (te) thorn by means of one (equally) pointed.&#xA;परिभाव्य - Having thus reflected in his mind. प्रियर्दशन- dear one (lit. one of charming aspect or one whose sight is longed for). -connection, ( bond of) friendship.&#xA;-in this hole serving me like a fortress,&#xA;whose&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One should not associate with a man character is not known &amp;amp;c. :-place of residence. To-A reputed writer on law and of a treatise on Niti (especially &amp;lsquo;distrust or afra).&#xA;-a reciter of (one who knows) the spell (of charming a serpent). -One skilled in the use of drugs which deaden a serpent. -taking his stand on his enemity i. e. wishing to have his enemity avenged. fago &amp;amp;c.-calls me that I should bite some one (his enemy ). er-what cannot be believed, this is incredible, that grass should come in contact with (seek the company of) fire.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He who is the victim of another never approaches&#xA;447&#xA;him, even in a dream; why do you talk unmeaningly thus!&#xA;-A natural enemy. qfto-owing to my having suffered insults at the hands of my enemies; being contemned or humiliated by my enemies.&#xA;P. 195. 22. When one&amp;rsquo;s all is going to be lost and even life is threatened (is in danger) one should bow even to one&amp;rsquo;s enemies and save life and wealth, a should be taken to mean is about to be lost.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;10-walled with stones piled up. ft &amp;amp;c.— I cannot find entrance there, a proper place, living&#xA;in which &amp;amp;c.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;That which it is possible to eat, which can be digested when eaten and which proves beneficial in the end (when assimilated in the system) a man, welfare, should eat.&#xA;ga-by easy means; easily.&#xA;the matter clear. तस्यi e of the well,&#xA;desirous of his&#xA;Thus, to make&#xA;जलोपान्ते - near&#xA;-Lit, the burn-&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-Sometimes and with difficulty.&#xA;the water. gero-contributing to happiness&#xA;ing charcoal to his family, the destroyer of his family ( :). This sometimes also means &amp;rsquo;the bane of one&amp;rsquo;s family ( कुले अंगार इव ).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The wise man who is reduced in strength (: aft- ar: whose life blood is sapped) and is without helpers should contrive to gain a livelihood which might prove to be the means of getting all kinds of happiness. Mah. Bha&amp;rsquo;. V. 34. 14.&#xA;तव वचनेन - According to your direction. अरषट्ट०&amp;ndash;by the passage afforded by the buckets attached to the water- wheel. &amp;ndash;having placed or lodged. -No more frogs being left. :o-extirpated.&#xA;P. 196.&#xA;(You have accomplished) the object&#xA;-Occupied.&#xA;or business of your friend.&#xA;To me who must stay here.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;towords&#34;&gt;quif-of your own class&#xA;448&#xA;(family). so-distracted or perplexed at heart. If I contradict or forbid him.&#xA;25. He, who forms friendship with his enemy who is his superior in valour, eats poison, no donbt, with his own hands.&#xA;26. Men of prudence (foresight) please with the gift of a part their enemy prepared to deprive them of their whole property as the sea does the sub-marine fire (with a small quantity of its water). Vâdava or Vâdavágni, also called Aurva (because produced from the wrath of that sage) was east into the ocean by Aurva where it dries up a space of twelve kosas in extent.&#xA;27. The weak man who does not yield up peacefully even a little to a stronger person when asked to do so,.or does not give what is pointed out to him, gives afterwards (when compelled to do so) a far greater quantity (lit. a Khári of flour). A Khâri is equal to a maund and a halt.&#xA;28. When the loss of the whole impends, a wise man parts with a half (to save the other half); and he gets his purpose served (or, his want satisfied) with the half; for the loss of the whole is difficult to be borne.&#xA;29. A talented man should not allow much to be sacrificed for the sake of little: true wisdom lies in this that much should be saved as the cost of a trifle. See I. 19.&#xA;30. Just as a man with dirty clothes sits any where he likes (without the fear of soiling his clothes) so a person fallen from a virtuous course of conduct does (not care to) keep up what little character he has.&#xA;P. 197. actor-in a loud voice.&#xA;-ince- ssantly uttering the cries of-fie upon me, woe me ! fa-&#xA;-i. e, continually kept on crying.&#xA;31. Why do you cry (now), you, whose cry is of no avail and who have brought down ruin on your family: when our partisans are destroyed who will save us !&#xA;Pro-. . how to effect your own escape and to encom&#xA;449&#xA;pass his death. गच्छता कालेन - In the course of time. कवलित Lit, made mouthfuls of, eaten up; a denom, fr. a mouth- ful. -While I live. Inst, Abs. fafatani-&#xA;Having promised to offer worship and presents to various deities तदाकांक्षया - eagerly expecting his return. गोधा- a lizard. स्तोक - a little, येन — by which you are to say. तव far-against yon i. e, do harm to you at &amp;amp;c.- Then I pledge (lit, place in the middle as a safe-guard) my religious merit. This is a sort of oath. He means- I won&amp;rsquo;t do you harm on pain of losing my religious merit. विरूपकरणे - In the matter of doing yon harm. निःशकन- with a mind free from all misgiving; fearless. :- When I have seen danger in it.&#xA;P. 198.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-Remove the blame of ingrati- tude attaching to me. He means-By my words I have appeared ungrateful to you. I wish to prove my gratitude. But that can be done only when you come to my house and return unharmed-all safe. Of course the Makara is trying to lure him into his snare again ). i-i. e. the sin will fall to your lot (for having forced me to have recourse to this).&#xA;33.&#xA;:-having neither ears (to hear) nor a heart (mind to think).&#xA;T-&#xA;करालकॅसर: - Lit. having a rugged mane. परिचारकः-a servant, a waiter on. :-strokes i, e. wounds. His throat parched with hunger; p. p. p. of à I. P. to waste away &amp;amp;c. अन्यस्मिन्न०- One day. अन्वेषयन् आससाइ- In the course of his search came to or reached. oqia- on the margin or border of, fo-the sprouts of the Durvâ grass thinly grown. -Uncle (Mar. HIAI). EM-&#xA;o-should be duly accepted (honoured), putting on me heavier loads than I can bear. ful of grass. bling (green like) running through it,&#xA;fantor-by -a hand-&#xA;-Abounding in tender grass resem- emerald. And with a river&#xA;450&#xA;P. 199. -grand, beautiful.&#xA;-Protected by the power of my arms. -owing to this&#xA;अनेनैव दोषेण&#xA;very want of good luck (viz. being ill-fed ).&#xA;:- ill treated (by washermen ). :-helpless; also, without a husband. ao-Lit. bursting with youth. -his limbs (body) being powerfully affected by passion.&#xA;34. Excepting (beyond) a fair woman there is nothing that may be called neetar or poison (i. e. a woman is both these ); by being in company with whom one lives or separated from whom one dies.&#xA;35. It is a wonder if one does not melt (is not affected with passion) on meeting with the glance of those (women) by &amp;ldquo;the mere mention of whose name passion is inflamed, without union or sight.&#xA;व्यथाकुलितः - afflicted or overpowered with pain. पला- -as he was running. -a stroke or slap 17-exertion or effort (proved fruit-&#xA;with his paw, less like ).&#xA;To-Of this sort i. e. so weak. -by force. fa- ao-with a smile of confusion or shame &amp;amp;c.-I had not put myself into an attacking posture (); I was not ready for the spring. the position of attack assumed by an animal, #TO-come within the reach of my spring or leap. -with his own eyes; actually.&#xA;P. 200.-i. e. the lion having assumed a position of attack, -grazing. go-I should have instant- ly perished or entered the jaws of death (had I not fled away) or it may mear-I was quickly led into the jaws of death, &amp;amp;c.—from the very fierce and thunderbolt- like stroke of whose band I escaped.&#xA;:-you fled&#xA;away through timidity. ao-To hold you back or&#xA;to stay you (from flying).&#xA;favour, or you will be pleased (to come).&#xA;-showing us&#xA;451&#xA;36. Those fools, wanting in good sense, who having left off the victorious banner of the god of love, in the shape of the woman, leading to the acquisition of wealth of every kind, (or, securing all desires and wealth), go in search of vain fruits (such as are obtained by leading a life of celibacy, by observing fasts &amp;amp;c.) are, by that very god, very mercilessly struck down and made (to wander about) naked and shaven (as Jaina and Buddha ascetics ), some again being turned into wearers of red garments, some of matted hair and others of human skulls. To-these are vagrant smarta ascetics. IT-so called because they wore garlands of human skulls and also carried a skull in their hand to gather their alms in &amp;amp;c. They formed a sect which worshipped S&amp;rsquo;iva and Durga in their terrific forms of Bhairava and Chandi, The verse attri- butes the asceticism of such mem to the anger of Cupid.&#xA;-as deserving of confidence, with faith,&#xA;37. A person does a reprehensible deed although knowing it to be so, being (entirely) led to it by desti- ny; else how can a man, in this world, like a deed de serv- ing condemnation? may also mean-a man of know- ledge.-under the influence of adverse fate.&#xA;P. 201. - guard. Fr-having appointed (to keep watch over the body). -should better be a. लौल्यो० - through the eagerness of greed. प्रतर्पित - Having satisfied his Pitrs (departed ancestors) with libations of water (i. 6. after having performed the Brahmayajna ).&#xA;N. B. The student should remember that these are the stories of human concerns, though animals take part in them. Hence the lion is represented here as offering worship to the gods &amp;amp;c., duties which propery belong to men only.&#xA;-Lit, with his soul entirely (R) in the power of anger, burning with anger, at reluced to452&#xA;the condition of being the residue of food eaten. For food is supposed to be defiled or rendered unfit for holy purposes when part of it is eaten. See I. p. 78. fat-humbly and respectfully. संविभज्य - dividing it with निःशंकितमना:- with a mind free from all suspicion (as to the corpse being de- filed by the jackal). fa-frustrated; foiled.&#xA;38. That imposter, who having given up his own in- terest (to the detriment of his interest) speaks the truth, is dull-headed (a fool); (for) he certainly fails to gain his ob- ject and is like a second Yudhishthira (the potter).&#xA;प्रमद:- deeply intoxicated. अर्धo-On the sharp point of a half-broken karpar (a kind of earthen pot; Mar aq). ft- point or end. qfe-wounded; lit, broken open or torn. - f-covered over, bathed in. 87770-On account of his having eaten unwholesome food. ai &amp;amp;c.&amp;ndash;The wound festered; lit. assumed a rugged surface, fanio-was heal- ed up. दुर्भिक्षपी० - The country being famine stricken. संमुखप्र- &amp;ndash;The stroke of a weapon when fighting an enemy face to face सकाशात् - In the presence of सविशेषेण &amp;amp;c. &amp;ndash; looked upon him with (i. e showed him) special favour.&#xA;P. 202. &amp;ndash;excess of, &amp;amp;c.&amp;ndash;although entertaining ousy. अन्यस्मिन्न०- One day.&#xA;exceptional, favour. qri&#xA;feelings of the greatest jeal- वीरसंभावनायां &amp;amp;c. -when honour was being done to the warriors (warlike men). futa- hostilities having arisen; when a war was imminent. - प्रक- &amp;ndash;were being arrayed (with respect to their strength, size &amp;amp;c.) and fitted up (for battle). Mo-were being covered with armours and equipped for war. gufto- when the warriors were being encouraged by being entrus ted with special offices for taking part in the coming war. gro-In a manner befitting the occasion; or in the course of the business in hand, निर्जने -in private. प्रहार- fo-the effect of i, e. the wound caused by the blow.&#xA;-being ashamed. aai &amp;amp;c.-Let him be quickly&#xA;453&#xA;turned out by being seized by the neck, a is more usual; see I. p. 23. ro-Lit. the skill of the hand; my skill in wielding the sword or using the bow.&#xA;39. Thou art brave; thou hast mastered the lores; and thou art handsome to look at, my boy! Nevertheless the family in which thou art born kills not (or, is not known to kill ) an elephant (lit. no elephant is killed by any one born in &amp;amp;c.)&#xA;वनोद्देश&amp;ndash;a region of the forest. अजीजनत् - gave birth to (two cubs), 3rd Aor. of caus,&#xA;-a hangs loose in the sentence and does not properly stand for सिंहः; it should be तं च ( शिशुं ). The reading in the foot-note is better.&#xA;P. 203.&#xA;ft-excepting.&#xA;40. Even when one&amp;rsquo;s life is in peril, one should not strike (dead, kill) a woman, an ascetic (or one bearing on his person the mark of a linga of S&amp;rsquo;iva), a Brahmana, a child, and especially those who have placed confidence&#xA;in one.&#xA;q-eat your food, have your meal (which is necessary for you).&#xA;41. An act which is unfit to be done should not at all be done (lit. cannot be fit to be done) even when there is imminent risk to life (lit. when the abandonment of life is at hand); nor should a duty be given up (lit. omitted to be done): such is the holy law that obtains for all times. -&amp;amp;c.-without mutually knowing the particular species to which they belonged. fafton &amp;amp;c.-they passed their childhood playing or sporting together. With angry or excited looks.&#xA;towords.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;scribed-the-action-of-c-that-he-fled-away-c&#34;&gt;110&#xA;-ran or marched&#xA;-just as they set out to attack. geg&#xA;The natural enemy of your race.&#xA;-On account of&#xA;2&#xA;454&#xA;their eidest brother taking to flight (lit. yielding to fear); or owing to the want of energy of.&#xA;-lost their&#xA;energy; their spirits flagged.&#xA;42. By reason of even one person, resolute and energetic, the whole army becomes energised (eager) for war; but by the break-down (or taking fright of one) it will break down (or lose courage).&#xA;43. Hence it is that kings desire to have warriors &amp;amp;c. &amp;ndash;firm-minded, resolute. -energetic or spirited. -discard, avoid.&#xA;-laughing at, deriding.&#xA;eg:-spoke of, de&#xA;scribed, the action of &amp;amp;c. that he fled away &amp;amp;c.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;c-they-were-received-with-great-honour&#34;&gt;with his leaf-like lower lip throbbing fari &amp;amp;c.-knit- ting his eye-brows; the three Sikhás are the two ends and the middle part raised up in the act of knitting. परुषतर&amp;ndash; very harsh.&#xA;or secluded place.&#xA;g-younger.&#xA;inferior.&#xA;P. 204.&#xA;save his life.&#xA;-having taken (him) to a private :-advised or remonstrated with, -exasperated with anger. हीनः &amp;ndash;&#xA;-desirous of his life i. e. wishing to ma in the midst of your own species. भयव्याकुल० - distracted with fear at heart. एतेषां स०&amp;ndash; from them; at their hands. as-disgrace, mortifi. cation.&#xA;-you were exposed, your real nature was known.&#xA;45. Parrots and starlings are confined (in cages) for the fault of their mouths (their power of speaking and singing). a crane. &amp;amp;c.-silence is golden (lit. leads to the accomplishment of all objects).&#xA;46. Although carefully guarded and presenting a horrid body, being dressed in a tiger&amp;rsquo;s skin, the ass was killed because of his voice (braying).&#xA;an ass.&#xA;as by cows &amp;amp;c.)&#xA;-grass (that is eaten in monthfuls&#xA;-A good thing has happened,&#xA;this is a god-send.&#xA;455&#xA;-corn-fields (a barley). -&#xA;-will not drive away or turn out.&#xA;P. 205. co-stout or fat in body. &amp;amp;c.-was even tied down with diffienlty (did not easily allow himself to be tied down).fad-to bray. o-striking him with sticks &amp;amp;c. -Name of a person.&#xA;धरापीठ - The surface of the earth. fortune यस्य. भाण्डपतिः - merchant&#xA;8&#xA;(i, e, without being invited).&#xA;मद्दा- महत् large धर्न&#xA;प्राघूर्णका:- as guests&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-They were received with great honour&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;-the-tem--ple-of-chandikà-the-goddess-durgá-in-her-fierce-form--there-a-voice-in-from--the-sky--was-suddenly-heard-a-in-accordance-with-the-decree-of&#34;&gt;and well treated with food, clothing &amp;amp;c. pleased (or, attracted) by the high honour or great recep- tion accorded to them. f &amp;amp;c.-what do you say to this? I think, they will not go without being insuked. ST-knowing i. e. feeling insulted.&#xA;(taking insult) at a small seat being given to him, -being served with coarse food. -since he&#xA;would not go.&#xA;47.-owing to the matter with regard to (water for) washing the feet. fat-the changed state of your feelings, you being altered.&#xA;48. A fool is quieted ( appeased) although sin ( wicked deed) be committed in his presence: a carpenter bore on his head his wife with her paramour.&#xA;garet-Lit. wandering to another man; a bad character; faithless to her husband.&#xA;P. 206.&#xA;was badly or scandalously talked of; was branded with infamy. -reflected or fell athink- ing as to how to test her ( chastity).&#xA;49. नदीनां - e. fathom the depth of rivers. कुलानां-&#xA;i. e. of the purity of the origin of.&#xA;mous (and therefore above such scrutiny ).&#xA;i-magnani-&#xA;50. The sage (Paràshara) had intercourse with (Satyavati) a fisherman&amp;rsquo;s daughter, born of the seed of&#xA;456&#xA;Vasu (one of the eight gods of that name ); and so (as the result of the connection) was born Vya&amp;rsquo;ss, the reposi- tory of hundreds of virtues; what more to say! He divided and arranged the Vedas; and yet he, the illustrious one, became the progenitor of the Kuru race when brought to a termination; alas! irreconcilable are the ways of destiny!&#xA;-Because Satyavatî was found in the belly of a fish by a fisherman. For the origin of Vyása and other things mentioned in the sl. see Mahábhárata Adip. 105, 6. व्यस्यन्— pre. p. of अस् with वि; lit, dividing for ar- rangement. fa-uneven, opposed in their nature.&#xA;goafa-As regards the statement (of sl. 49) that the origin of families should not be too closely examined. to-should be ascertained; should be pried into.&#xA;-born of the same mother (by different fathers). -Prep. p. of the pass, of age 1 A. to kindle;&#xA;when stirred up; when inquired into.&#xA;a number of blemishes or short-comings.&#xA;far about the statement-nt &amp;amp;c.&#xA;-discloses tf-80&#xA;51. -very hot. -the hare-marked, the moon ( शश: लाच्छनं यस्य ). दुर्जनो हितः - It a wicked man be ever well-disposed then chastity is possible in the case of women (women can be chaste ).&#xA;-still, following i. e. considering the talk of the people I will ascertain whether she is chaste or not.&#xA;52. What is not found in the Vedas or the S&amp;rsquo;ástras; what is neither seen or heard (in the world)-all that the people know; as also that which may exist in the world. i. c. people talk all manner of things without caring to to know the truth,&#xA;-Having come to this conclusion; thus resolved. कानिचिद्दिo some days will have to be passed there. पाथे-&#xA;457&#xA;-provisions for a journey.&#xA;eagerness. and sugar.&#xA;-through great&#xA;-Ready food mostly consisting of ghee&#xA;53. On a cloudy day, when there is dense darkness, when the streets of a city are difficult to pass through and when the husband is gone to a foreign country, great de- light is felt by a lewd woman. fae &amp;amp;c.-are to be taken as independent causes of the joy. Or afão &amp;amp;c. may be taken as qualifying fo; when there is darkness caused by the clouds (), when the streets &amp;amp;c.-( owing to the showers of rain;) cf. the reading auf which should be&#xA;preferred in this case.&#xA;कथंचित्- with great&#xA;प्रहसि० - प्रहसितं वदनं यस्याः with a smiling countenance. अङ्ग० — the decoration of the body. difficulty. faz-a paramour, a lover. &amp;ndash;( when the inmates of your house) will be in deep slumber or fast asleep. &amp;ndash;After things were thus arranged.&#xA;P. 207 -under the bed stead, fr-care- fully concealing himself. - v. 7. in the house, or the secret apartment, हेलया-easily. परं तावत् - But let me first (before I take any step). Pri fo-having made ( shut) the door fast. &amp;amp;c.-Surely it must be the vile or wicked carpenter (who lies thus concealed) to try me. -Pot. p. p. -I will make him get some idea of or understand in some measure what women&amp;rsquo;s actions are (what ready wit they possess ). To-who had formed the cavity of (folded) her hands. महाननुभावो यस्य 0 noble one ! पतित्रता० - devoted to my husband and highly chaste. To-I will completely reduce you to ashes. -with a mind entirely devoted to me i, e. with undivided attention.&#xA;-The tem- ple of Chandikà, the goddess Durgá in her fierce form. -There a voice in (from ) the sky () was suddenly heard. A-In accordance with the decree of&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;untains-a-female-mouse-accepted-one-of-her-species-ones-own-race-is-difficult-to-be-transgressed-i-e-it-is-diffi--cult-for-one-to-get-over-or-overcome-the-promptings-or-instincts-of-ones-race-&#34;&gt;458&#xA;fate; as ordained by providence.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-Although there is one (a remedy) still it is as good as non&amp;ndash;existent ( unavailable); since it depends upon you to make use of it (which you are not expected to do). for: &amp;amp;c.- If it can be used at the cost of my life, if it can be done at the sacrifice of my life. The untimely death impending on (threatening) your husband will be trans- ferred to him (the other man). -for that reason, with this object in view.&#xA;-will never be fal- :-After this the Nir. Ed. and Ms. read- तदुचितमाचचार which&#xA;11&#xA;sified. ततः ( तच्छ्रुत्वा Ms. ) अन्तर्द्धासविकाशमुखः स&#xA;(azgl&#xA;io-bis face goro-His body&#xA;Foo-&#xA;should have been inserted in the text. brightening with an internal smile. (marked) bristling with the hair standing on end. - the delighter of the family. दुर्जन०- दुर्ननानां वचनैः शक्ङ्कितं (ईका अस्य संजाना तत् ) हृदयं यस्य. With my heart ( mind ) ull of suspicion owing to &amp;amp;c. q-under the pretext of; pretending to go to.&#xA;P. 208.&#xA;-(see foot-note)-the vow of chastity. 9-even though you had to keep company with a stranger अनिच्छन्तमपि - even against his will. सूर्यध्वनि०- dancing to the sound of a túrya (a kind of musical instrn- ment). :-one in whom a change of feelings or affection is observed. -naturally wicked. feo- even through the company of a respectable man, TT- or rather. This is used to correct or modify a previous statement.&#xA;54. A wicked soul (an evil-natured man) whose pro- wess is exercised in doing sinful deeds never attains purity of intention (becomes a good-natured man) though properly advised by good men; just as a charcoal, how-so ever rubbed, never becomes white.&#xA;55. Having given up (discarded) Surya (the sun- god), the god of rain, Wind and the presiding deity of mo-&#xA;459&#xA;untains, a female-mouse accepted one of her species: one&amp;rsquo;s own race is difficult to be transgressed (i. e, it is diffi- cult for one to get over or overcome the promptings or instincts of one&amp;rsquo;s race, )&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;-unfit&#34;&gt;ada penance-forest (i. e. a forest inhabited by penance-practising sages) or grove, -as he was offering prayers to the sun.&#xA;with very sharp-pointed nails or talons.&#xA;Co-by a hawk&#xA;o-threw at him.ro-his senses overpowereed by the stroke go-with the fem. mouse dropping from his hold. o-at a loss to know what to do.&#xA;of.&#xA;having recovered his senses or regained consciousness,&#xA;P. 209. &amp;amp;c.-Are you not afraid of a breach of auty or an irreligious deed. प्रोवाच-sternly said विहंगा- Thon wretch of a bird; vile bird.&#xA;-irrelevant, nonsensical अनं - Vegetable food. विहिताः are design- ed as food.&#xA;56. What is ordained as one&amp;rsquo;s proper food does not make one guilty of sin; if one eats what is not proper for one to eat, there is great sin in it; therefore no exchange of duty should be caused (i. e. one should not ask another to do what is not proper to be done ).&#xA;57. Cons.:-nat negata Rafa&amp;amp;c.-As wine in the case of Brahmanas, as sacrificial food in the case of those habituated to drink wine, becomes unfit to be eaten though proper for others to eat, so is the case, oh Brahmana, with others also. In this sl. the ris explained. The meaning is-every one is justified in eating his proper food.&#xA;58. Good attends those who eat their proper food; what is improper to be eaten (if eaten ) leads to great sin; how can it be then proper for you to punish me as one acting improperly? Supply a after genan. It will be&#xA;460&#xA;better to read ago not acting improperly; or qua oh you who are not acting properly.&#xA;art &amp;amp;c.-Moreover, such is not the duty (i. e. to punish others) of sages; for they should consider what is seen as unseen, and what is heard as unheard, and be free from greediness and enmity: such conduct is com- mended for them.&#xA;59.-60. Of sages blameless (praiseworthy) and following the path of good conduct (virtue) he is esteemed the highest who is the same to friend or foe, who treats a lump of earth, a stone or gold as of equal value, who is indifferent to well-wishers and friends, who remains neutral towards those who are the object of hatred or relations and who regards equally the good and the sinful. A practiser of Yoga should always devote himself to ab- straction, remaining in a secret place.&#xA;These lines, with the exception of argai &amp;amp;c. are quoted from the Bhagavatgîtà but very indifferently. Thus the first line is made up of parts from XII. 18, and VI, 8; the two lines. -fasa make one sl. in the Gitá viz. VI. 9. and the line a forms part of the next sl. The line सुहृन्मित्रे is again changed, the original reading being सुहृन्मि- त्रार्युदासीनमध्यस्थद्वेष्य बन्धुषु ।&#xA;ETT: &amp;amp;c.-By this act you have fallen from your asceticism; you have lost the high virtue of your&#xA;penance,&#xA;61. Crying out let go your hold, let go your hold, one fell off from virtue, and another by saying &amp;lsquo;don&amp;rsquo;t let go&amp;rsquo;; seeing the fall of both (the third remained quiet): silence leads to the accomplishment of all objects. Or we may supply तृतीयः and अभजत; तृतीयः सर्वाथ० मौनमभजत the third had recourse to silence, the means of acquiring all objects.&#xA;461&#xA;P. 210. धौतपो०-washed garments. निरालम्बाः - निर्गत भालम्बो यासां without support. पतिता - The bawk means his interference with another&amp;rsquo;s duty lessened the stock of his religious merit and caused the fall of his garment. - To-distressed with the fear of that (i. e. the falling of his garment ). off-adv. silent. 919-even by talking with a sinner. Terro-by talking with one not respectable. To-through the fault of casting re- proach on a good man. पापात्मा - sinful by nature, कर्म &amp;amp;c.-one does not incur sin unless a deed is actually&#xA;done.&#xA;62. In the other ages (than Kali) the sins of men trans- ferred themselves to others (as by associating with a sinner &amp;amp;c. see next sl.); but in the Kali age which is full of sin, he alone stands guilty of sin who (actually) com- mits it.&#xA;63. In the Krta age sin travelled to (infected) an- other from his sitting or sleeping or going or associating or dining with (a sinner).&#xA;the&#xA;.&#xA;तत्किं टथा० - Why waste words on the subject? दाक्षिण्य०- full of kindness, or sympathy. -seeking protection. P. 211. (T):-2nd pers. sing. of the Aor. of 5,&#xA;being dropped after the prohibitive particle -a religious father (i, e. by a religious act). 64. These five, viz. the generator, he who performs the sacred thread-ceremony, he who imparts knowledge (educates), and he who protects from danger, are declared in Smritis to be fathers (i. e, to occupy the position of). cf. Rag. I. 24,&#xA;-the digit of the moon in the bright half of a month. cf. Kum. I. 25. aaaa quickly attained.&#xA;bordering on adolescence.&#xA;-unfit,&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;65&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The manes of him in whose house his unmarried daughter attains puberty, fall, although they be in heaven,462&#xA;owing to the demerit arising from that. कस्मैचित् &amp;amp;c. to some supereminent or distiguished bridegroom.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A girl chooses an excellent husband, the mother looks to wealth ( ornaments &amp;amp;c. ), the father to learning (the education of the bridegroom), the relatives to family (desire connection with a person of family) and other people to dainties (only).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One should get a daughter married before she begins to blush, while she plays with dust and while she stands on the path of cattle.&#xA;वृष्ट्वा&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;amp;c.-On seeing a girl in menses (before mar- riage).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;High family (nobility of birth ), good disposition, the state of having guardians (or supporters), scholarship, wealth, handsomeness of bodily make and (youthful) age:-having ascertained these seven qualities (necessary in a bridegroom) wise men should give away their daugh- ters other things need not be considered or inquired into.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Wise men should not give a daugher in marriage to those who live at a (great) distance, who are devoted to duties leading to absolution, who are (recklessly) brave and who are penniless.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;By a man desiring a happy result his daughter should not be given to a bridegroom who is not liked by her though he be endowed with beauty.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-What is wrong in this? What harm&#xA;is there!&#xA;P. 212.&#xA;of an exceedingly burning nature, उत्कृष्ट०—superior to. निस्पृह : - having no liking for her. ना- &amp;amp;c.-Not a trace of me is to be observed; I am tolally hidden. कृष्णवर्ण:- of a dark complexion. जडात्मा-जडः आत्मा यस्य dall by nature; also जलात्मा (डू and ॡ being interchange- able) composed of water. -in a thousand directions&#xA;or ways.&#xA;-most desirable,&#xA;E-being stopped&#xA;463&#xA;by whom I remain bound up in or confined to (one place). afro-hard in body. -steady, fixed in one place. affa-appear suitable to you, does he come up to your liking? quo-what is proper can be done. goo-decked with horripilation. -I will per-&#xA;स्वजाति० form the duties proper for or peculiar to my race. of-&#xA;-by him conversant with the duties of women.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Not gold, not jewels, not even the comforts of royalty women desire so much as they do a husband most coveted (or loved) by them.&#xA;P. 213. -the rank or position of a deity. - though favoured with friendship.&#xA;-you were spoiled or affected by the innate qualities of your race, gs-unduly fond of your wife, uxorious. if- Swayed or subdued by your wife. -i. e. for the sake of your wife.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;a-treats me with disgust, shrinks from me. -embraces. -O you who have done me an agreeable service; my benefactor. कामोप० कामेन उपहतं at q whose mind was overpowered (disturbed) by passion.&#xA;-married.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;शिरसि शिरोरुहाणां श्वेतं पदं वीक्ष्य &amp;amp;c - Beholding the white- ness of the hair on the head (lit. the whole place of hair on the head turned white )-and that is the great cause of men&amp;rsquo;s discomfiture-young women go far away avoiding (uch a man) as people do from a Chándàla&amp;rsquo;s well having a piece of bone suspended over it.&#xA;This is taken from Bhar. Vair. Sa&amp;rsquo;t, Mis. 38, where the reading for श्वेतं पदं is वर्णे सितम्. It was customary in ancient times to mark the wells set apart for the use of, or owned by, Chandalas to suspend a bone over them, that they might easily be recognised.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(In old age) the limbs are shrivelled, the gait falters, the teeth fall off, the eye-sight quivers (becomes unsteady), beauty itself wanes, the mouth dribbles caliys,&#xA;464&#xA;the relatives do not at all obey orders (or act up to one&amp;rsquo;s words), and the wife does not wait upon (or serve her husband): alas, oh pity! a man decrepit with (or broken down by) old age is despised even by his own sons!&#xA;This is also quoted from Bhar. with some change of readings; see Vair. 111. लालायते. denom fr. लाला. शुश्रूषते - desiderative of which is Atm. -A denom. fr. अवज्ञा. पराङ्मुखी &amp;amp;c. - पराङ्मुखं यस्याः while she lay with her face turned away from him.&#xA;P. 214.&#xA;पुलका० - पुलकैः अंकितानि सर्वाणि गात्राणि यस्याः सा with all her limbs marked with bristling hair, -oh wonder! fagrar-with skill i, e, minutely, with a search- ing glance. -in a part of a corner (of the room). एवं विवदत:- while he was thus disputing with him, त्वाय चि- रयति- -as you delayed. To-died from the disappoint- ment of (unrequited) love. (Depending on her love for you she sat down without food awaiting your return. Your not returning in time gave a shock to her feelings, too great for her to bear and she died).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A house is not a (real) home, they (the wise) say; it is the wife that is said to be (to constitute) the home: for a house without a wife surpasses even a forest (in drea- riness or desolation).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Where there is a beloved even at the root of a tree that is a home; even a palace without her is said to be like a wilderness.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bribery-a-gift&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;c.-To him a home is like a desert.&#xA;-and a slave of your wife, under her thraldom. -direct experience (now conviction is brought home to me). -when you should rejoice; instead of feeling delighted why do you feel grieved?&#xA;80. A wife, whose actions are wicked and who loves quarrelling, should be known by the wise to be (simply)&#xA;orrible old age in a wife&amp;rsquo;s form.&#xA;465&#xA;81. Therefore a man who desires happiness for self should, with every effort, avoid &amp;amp;c.&#xA;P. 215. 82. Who, indeed (or possibly), do not perish that, through misapprehension, (ur, a wrong notion) approach a beautiful woman (lit. with large hips) thinking her to be attractive, like moths flying towards the flame (of a lamp)?&#xA;83. For, these women are, by their very nature, in- wardly (at heart) full of poison and attractive (heart- bewitching) by their outward appearance, thus resembling the Gunja&amp;rsquo; fruits in form, fat-a grammatical in- accuracy; the correct form is-13.&#xA;84. That which is in their heart is not on their tongue; what is on their tongue is not in their expression; what they express they do not put into execution; strange is the behaviour of women !&#xA;83. do-cut into pieces, dismembered.&#xA;न वर्श -do not submit or yield (to the power of). erd:- by praises or flatteries,&#xA;86. Let this be aside; why talk of any other wickedness on the part of women? they kill, through the child of their womb. (lit. borne in anger, even the womb.)&#xA;87. A fool (one ignorant of the nature of women) will falsely attribute an affectionate good feeling to (or suppose it to exist in) a young woman who is unfeeling, great delicacy to her who is hard-hearted and sentiment to her who is destitute of it.&#xA;-two mishaps or calamities. To-the loss of home. afo-the severance of heart i, e. alienation of affection, loss of friendly feeling. to-condemned by&#xA;fate, those under the frown of fortune.&#xA;88. qi-cleverness, circumspection. &amp;amp;-&#xA;466&#xA;yours is doubly of the same sort. paramour nor &amp;amp;c. is left to you.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-neither the Afer-The Par, is&#xA;probably for the metre; the root is usually Atm.&#xA;-A couple of peasants. अन्य० - अन्यस्मिन् चित्तं यस्याः सा who thought of others; whose mind was attached to other persons (than her husband). remain steady. To-in search of, hunting for other uen. -who was in the habit of robbing others of their wealth. -a swindler, a rogue. fan-in private. सुभगे - Oh fortunate one, रूपं० - by seeing the loveliness of your form. to-the free gift of your love.&#xA;P. 216.&#xA;&amp;ndash;more delightful or prosperous,&#xA;fane-&#xA;having undertaken to do so.&#xA;&amp;ndash;on the border (last&#xA;stage) of youth.&#xA;-very difficult to cross.&#xA;mai-&#xA;your purse of wealth. उत्तार०-I will take you over. परिधा०-&#xA;-. e. without the fear&#xA;-to the place plauned or fixed&#xA;your wearing garments. of wetting them. upon.-placing her both hands on her neek. -full of grief, pensive. ao-having in her mouth a piece of flesh. उपाद० - ran or rushed towards. अवतीर्य- darting down from. -foiled in her efforts; whose efforts proved vain.&#xA;90.10-You who have lost the fish as well as &amp;amp;c. fay-who had lost both, her husband&amp;rsquo;s wealth &amp;amp;c.&#xA;P. 217. -by a powerful or huge alligator. -occupied, taken possession of. -to&#xA;निःसारयितुं&#xA;onst or drive him out. persecuted by fate.&#xA;93. My friend is turned to my misfortune (qt) &amp;amp;c.; store for me?&#xA;-My being struck down or&#xA;into an enemy: and to add&#xA;what further is there in&#xA;ST &amp;amp;c.-Or why, it is well&#xA;observed. co- Misfortunes never come single; misery follows upon misery.&#xA;467&#xA;r&amp;amp;c. (see foot-note )-Strokes fall again and again on a wound (a); gastric fire (hunger) increases when there is scarcity of food; enmities spring into existence (arise) in adversity; all this results when fate is adverse !&#xA;TT-by peaceful means. success see 1 sl. 481. p. 65.&#xA;For the four means of -having advised; see I.&#xA;-sowing seeds of or creating discord.&#xA;bribery; a gift.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;93&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hs who acts (lit. does a thing) having consulted those worthy persons (elders and friends) who are his well-wishers and whose advice is fit to be sought, meets with no obstacle (lit, obstacles do not come in his way) in any undertaking.&#xA;-Occupied.&#xA;fo-which should be employed in the present case (lit, which has scope here)!&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;amp;c.-To any man whatsover (i. e. indiscri- minately). fo-was deprived of her dwelling, was made homeless, see I p. 83.&#xA;कुलाय -&#xA;-a nest, &amp;amp;c.-Beaten by an untimely shower of rain and his body shaken by a violent wind. दन्तवी० - his teeth chattering. संकुचित-contracted, drawn in. go-pityingly.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;see I. 395.&#xA;P. 218. self-satisfied. herself airs.&#xA;o-pleased with his own good condition; Trio-thinks highly of herself; gives&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Who, indeed, has no pride caused by his own thoughts about himself? A lap-wing lies with feet up turned for fear of the sky falling down (or, giving way- that it might support it).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Yon needle-mouthed (uttering harsh words as piercing to the heart as the point of a needle), and ill-be-&#xA;468&#xA;haved wench, who consider herself wise, hold your tongue; else I will &amp;amp;c.&#xA;o-tired out his patience, troubled or teased him. go-taking into consideration our former friendship. -At the request (bidding) of. -dearer (the ab. लोकात् expresses the sense of the compa ). न हि त्रीणां &amp;amp;c.-One should not, under any circumstances, confide in women.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;She for whose sake I quitted my family and parted with half of my life, even she, setting aside her affection for me (or being cold-hearted) abandons me. Who can place confidence in women!&#xA;अतिप्रा० - the greatest darling of his heart. कढई- Ff-could never desist from or cease quarrelling with, always picked a quarrel with.&#xA;-out of his fondness or affection for विप्रकृष्ट distant, आर्यपु० - husband; (lit. the son of the father-in-law; a husband was thus addressed). -just as विषाद कुo-grieving for.&#xA;ge-having purified himself (by bathing or touching the cavities of the body with water &amp;amp;c ). Such purification is necessary for every religious act, such as a solemn gift &amp;amp;c.&#xA;P. 219. far: &amp;amp;c.-by repeating the words &amp;lsquo;I give three times-which is necessary for the solemnity of the act. Cf. the maxim- far: Taittirya Aranyaka II. 18. 6. -the moment the words were uttered.&#xA;-at the entrance (the border ground) of. &amp;amp; flower-garden. -turning, moving. foto-with a heavenly (ethereal) voice i. e. exquisitely melodious. gay-the (flower-arrowed), god of love. -smitten with love, arger-the sin of woman-murder cansed by my death.ou-broken down (disabled or enfeebled) by diseases, a companion to talk to.&#xA;-you are not able to walk, yourself (lit. to&#xA;469&#xA;carry or bear up your own self) what to say of-much less-this cripple.&#xA;-whose mind was deluded by her bypocritical (cunning) speech. no-he accept- ed her proposal, granted her request. To-who was attached to (deep in love with) the large man. - being pushed.go-for the purpose, or with the object, of guarding against or preventing the avoidance of the payment of the toll and other duties, fa-being snatched off or forcibly taken away. gg-closely&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;following the foot-steps of the royal officers. with my heart distracted owing to my affection for him.&#xA;P. 220.-The king was informed against him; he was accused before the king. He was or- dered to be put to death, -belonging to me, what was entirely mine. ce-a lover of justice (doing what is right). -Cau. of ; ask (compel) her to give it back. fan-given with a threefold declara- tion,&#xA;an anecdote, a minor story.&#xA;99. What will a man, earnestly asked by women not give or do? since in such cases those who are not horses neigh like a horse or on such an occasion the head is shaven! The fourth line should better have been farts- पर्वणि &amp;amp;c.&#xA;geo-whose strength and prowess were well known. -whose foot-stool was densely covered with the streaming rays of the diadems of numerous kings. :-whose fame was clear (spotless) like the rays of the autumnal moon. oqar-stretching to (bounded by). do-who had mastered all the prin- ciples of all the S&amp;rsquo;a&amp;rsquo;stras. :-Lit of fine taste. quq-Owing to a love-quarrel. -Although she was being propitiated in various ways. येन प्रकारेण- the means by which निश्चितं - surely. प्रसादा० - inclined to, ready to. ad-a bridle.&#xA;470&#xA;don P. 221. -Although I entertained thoughts -A good (effective) reme-&#xA;against your person.&#xA;dy. संविधास्यति - adopt or use it.&#xA;100. He, who, through folly (or, a wrong notion about himself) disregards (does not act upon) the advice given by the good (wise), does meet with destruction, as did the young camel at the hands of a lion,&#xA;स्वकर्मा - who did not know his profession well. अहर्नि- goes with q.&#xA;&amp;amp;c.-what is the use of other difficult professions!&#xA;P. 222. -welfare, happy maintenance. :-a kind of coin. (cf. Greek Drakhmè) equal in value to about four armas, sixteen drammas being equal to a nis&amp;rsquo;ka (a dra.= 16 panas; a pana=4 Kákinis; a Kàkini 20 vara&amp;rsquo;takas or kauris). 1 ft-i. e. by selling her. -to purchase young camels. निवेद्य - having assigned आदिष्टं- was ordered i. e. they were permitted to drink milk, r&#xA;To the garden in the vicinity of their residence, of-sportively, playfully. qo-the first-bred, (the eldest of them). Ho-through excess of youthful pride. -Coming afterwards (having lagged be- bind). To straying away from, f-within the sight of यावदु० - as he proceeded to go home. न कथंचित् &amp;amp;c.-could not by any means find his way. o-by following his voice. -having assumed an attacking posture. to- having jumped upon; a grammatical irregularity.&#xA;Men skilled in the S&amp;rsquo;a&amp;rsquo;stras say that friendship is formed after walking seven steps (with a person, or by&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
