<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 ILL-CONSIDERED ACTION on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 ILL-CONSIDERED ACTION on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE LOYAL MUNGOOSE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/01_THE_LOYAL_MUNGOOSE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/01_THE_LOYAL_MUNGOOSE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a Brahman named Godly in a certain town. His wife mothered a single son and a mungoose. And as she loved little ones, she cared for the mungoose also like a son, giving him milk from her breast, and salves, and baths, and so on. But she did not trust him, for she thought: “A mungoose is a nasty kind of creature. He might hurt my boy.” Yes, there is sense in the proverb:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 THE FOUR TREASURE-SEEKERS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/02_THE_FOUR_TREASURE-SEEKERS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/02_THE_FOUR_TREASURE-SEEKERS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town in the world were four Brahmans who lived as the best of friends. And being stricken with utter poverty, they took counsel together: “A curse, a curse on this business of being poor! For&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The well-served master hates him still;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;His loving kinsmen with a will&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Abandon him; woes multiply,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While friends and even children fly;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;His high-born wife grows cool: the flash&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of virtue dims; brave efforts crash —&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 THE LION-MAKERS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/03_THE_LION-MAKERS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/03_THE_LION-MAKERS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town were four Brahmans who lived in friendship. Three of them had reached the far shore of all scholarship, but lacked sense. The other found scholarship distasteful; he had nothing but sense.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day they met for consultation. “What is the use of attainments,” said they, “if one does not travel, win the favor of kings, and acquire money? Whatever we do, let us all travel.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But when they had gone a little way, the eldest of them said: “One of us, the fourth, is a dullard, having nothing but sense. Now nobody gains the favorable attention of kings by simple sense without scholarship. Therefore we will. not share our earnings with him. Let him turn back and go home.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 HUNDRED-WIT, THOUSAND-WIT, AND SINGLE-WIT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/04_HUNDRED-WIT_THOUSAND-WIT_AND_SINGLE-WIT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/04_HUNDRED-WIT_THOUSAND-WIT_AND_SINGLE-WIT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain pond lived two fishes whose names were Hundred-Wit and Thousand-Wit. And a frog named Single-Wit made friends with them. Thus all three would for some time enjoy at the water’s edge the pleasure of conversation spiced with witticism, then would dive into the water again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day at sunset they were engaged in conversation, when fishermen with nets came there, who said to one another on seeing the pond: “Look! This pond appears to contain plenty of fish, and the water seems shallow. We will return at dawn.” With this they went home.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 THE MUSICAL DONKEY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/05_THE_MUSICAL_DONKEY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/05_THE_MUSICAL_DONKEY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town was a donkey named Prig. In the daytime he carried laundry packages, but was at liberty to wander anywhere at night. One night while wandering in the fields he fell in with a jackal and made friends. So the two broke through a hedge into cucumber-beds, and having eaten what they could hold of that comestible, parted at dawn to go home.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One night the egotistical donkey, standing among the cucumbers, said to the jackal: “See, nephew! The night is marvelously fine. I will contribute a song. What sentiment shall my song express?” “Don’t, uncle,” said the jackal. “It might make trouble, seeing that we are on thieves’ business. Thieves and lovers should keep very quiet. As the proverb says:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 SLOW, THE WEAVER</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/06_SLOW_THE_WEAVER/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/06_SLOW_THE_WEAVER/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town lived a weaver named Slow. One day all the pegs in his loom broke. So he took an axe, and in his search for wood, came to the seashore. There he found a great sissoo tree, and he thought: “This seems a good-sized tree. If I cut it down, I can make plenty of weaving-tools.” He therefore lifted his axe upon it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now there was a fairy in the tree who said: “My friend, this tree is my home. Please spare it. For I live here in utter happiness, since my body is caressed by breezes cool from contact with ocean billows.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 THE BRAHMAN’S DREAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/07_THE_BRAHMANS_DREAM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/07_THE_BRAHMANS_DREAM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town lived a Brahman named Seedy, who got some barley-meal by begging, ate a portion, and filled a jar with the remainder. This jar he hung on a peg one night, placed his cot beneath it, and fixing his gaze on the jar, fell into a hypnotic reverie.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Well, here is ajar full of barley-meal,” he thought. “Now if famine comes, a hundred rupees will come out of it. With that sum I will get two she-goats. Every six months they will bear two-more she-goats. After goats, cows. When the cows calve, I will sell the calves. After cows, buffaloes; after buffaloes, mares. From the mares I shall get plenty of horses. The sale of these will mean plenty of gold. The gold will buy a great house with an inner court. Then someone will come to my house and offer his lovely daughter with a dowry. She will bear a son, whom I shall name Moon-Lord. When he is old enough to ride on my knee, I will take a book, sit on the stable roof, and think. Just then Moon-Lord will see me, will jump from his mother’s lap in his eagerness to ride on my knee, and will go too near the horses. Then I shall get angry and tell my wife to take the boy. But she will be busy with her chores and will not pay attention to what I say. Then I will get up and kick her.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 THE UNFORGIVING MONKEY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/08_THE_UNFORGIVING_MONKEY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/08_THE_UNFORGIVING_MONKEY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain city was a king named Moon, who had a pack of monkeys for his son’s amusement. They were kept in prime condition by daily provender and pabulum in great variety.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the amusement of the same prince there was a herd of rams. One of them had an itching tongue, so he went into the kitchen at all hours of the day and night and swallowed everything in sight. And the cooks would beat him with any stick or other object within reach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 THE CREDULOUS FIEND</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/09_THE_CREDULOUS_FIEND/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/09_THE_CREDULOUS_FIEND/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain city lived a king whose name was Fine-Army. He had a daughter named Pearl, blessed with the thirty-two marks of perfect beauty.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now a certain fiend, who wished to carry her off, came every evening and abused her, but he could not carry her off because she protected herself by drawing a magic circle. However, at the hour when he embraced her, she experienced trembling, fever, and the like, the feelings that arise in the presence of a fiend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 THE THREE-BREASTED PRINCESS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/10_THE_THREE-BREASTED_PRINCESS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/10_THE_THREE-BREASTED_PRINCESS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the north country was a city called Honey-Town, where the king was named Honey-Host. And once there was born to him a daughter with three breasts. As soon as he learned of the birth of a three-breasted girl, he summoned the chamberlain and said: “Sir, let this girl be exposed in the forest, so that not a single soul may learn the fact.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To this the chamberlain replied: “O king of kings, it is a well-known fact that a three-breasted daughter brings misfortune. In spite of this, the Brahmans should be summoned and their opinion asked, in order that no law be offended, whether human or divine. For the proverb says:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 THE FIEND WHO WASHED HIS FEET</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/11_THE_FIEND_WHO_WASHED_HIS_FEET/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/05_ILL-CONSIDERED_ACTION/11_THE_FIEND_WHO_WASHED_HIS_FEET/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain forest lived a fiend named Cruel. One day he met a Brahman in his wanderings, climbed on his shoulder, and said: “Now go ahead’&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So the terrified Brahman started off with him. But on observing that the fiend’s feet were soft as a lotus-heart he asked him: “Sir, why are your feet so tender?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And the fiend replied: “I am under a vow never to touch the ground with my feet until I have washed them.” Soon the Brahman, while meditating a plan of escape, came to a lake. Here the fiend said: “Sir, do not stir from this spot until I come forth from the lake after bathing and worshipping the god.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
