<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 CROWS AND OWLS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 CROWS AND OWLS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 HOW THE BIRDS PICKED A KING</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/01_HOW_THE_BIRDS_PICKED_A_KING/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/01_HOW_THE_BIRDS_PICKED_A_KING/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time the bird-clans gathered for consultation. There were swans and cranes and nightingales; there were peacocks, plovers, and owls; there were doves and pigeons and partridges; there were bluejays, vultures, skylarks; there were demoiselles and cuckoos and woodpeckers and many others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And they said: “We have in Garuda a king, to be sure. But he is ever intent on serving holy Vishnu, and pays no heed to us. What is the good of a sham king? He does not defend us when we are in genuine distress — when we are caught in traps, for instance. There is a saying:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 HOW THE RABBIT FOOLED THE ELEPHANT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/02_HOW_THE_RABBIT_FOOLED_THE_ELEPHANT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/02_HOW_THE_RABBIT_FOOLED_THE_ELEPHANT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a part of a forest lived an elephant-king named Four-Tusk who had a numerous retinue of elephants. His time was spent in protecting the herd.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now once there came a twelve-year drought, so that tanks, ponds, swamps, and lakes went dry. Then all the elephants said to the lord of the herd: “O King, our little ones are so tortured by thirst that some are like to die, and some are dead. Pray devise a method of removing thirst.” So he sent in eight directions elephants fleet as the wind to search for water.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 THE CAT’S JUDGMENT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/03_THE_CATS_JUDGMENT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/03_THE_CATS_JUDGMENT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At one time I was myself living in a certain tree. And beneath the same tree dwelt another bird, a partridge. So by virtue of our near neighborhood there sprang up between us a firm friendship. Every day after taking our meals and airings we spent the evening hours in a round of amusements, such as repeating witty sayings, telling tales from the old story-books, solving puzzles and conundrums, or exchanging presents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 THE BRAHMAN’S GOAT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/04_THE_BRAHMANS_GOAT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/04_THE_BRAHMANS_GOAT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town lived a Brahman named Friendly who had undertaken the labor of maintaining the sacred fire. One day in the month of February, when a gentle breeze was blowing, when the sky was veiled in clouds and a drizzling rain was falling, he went to another village to beg a victim for the sacrifice, and said to a certain man: “O sacrificer, I wish to make an offering on the approaching day of the new moon. Pray give me a victim.” And the man gave him a plump goat, as prescribed in Scripture. This he put through its paces, found it sound, placed it on his shoulder, and started in haste for his own city.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 THE SNAKE AND THE ANTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/05_THE_SNAKE_AND_THE_ANTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/05_THE_SNAKE_AND_THE_ANTS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain ant-hill lived a prodigious black snake, and his name was Haughty. One day, instead of following the beaten path out of his hole, he tried to crawl through a narrower crevice. In doing so, he suffered a wound, because his body was huge, and the opening was small, and fate willed it so.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then the ants gathered about him, drawn by the odor of blood from the wound, and drove him frantic. How many did he kill? Or how many crush? Yet their uncounted phalanx stung him in every member, and enlarged the numerous wounds. And Haughty perished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 THE SNAKE WHO PAID CASH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/06_THE_SNAKE_WHO_PAID_CASH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/06_THE_SNAKE_WHO_PAID_CASH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a Brahman in a certain place. His time was wholly spent in unproductive farming.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now one day, toward the end of summer, the heat was too much for him, and he dozed in the shade of a tree in the middle of his field. Not far away he saw, peering over an ant-hill, a terrifying snake that thrust forward a great, swelling hood. And he reflected: “Surely, this is the guardian deity of the field, and I never paid him honor. That is why my farm-work is unproductive. I will pay him honor.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 THE UNSOCIAL SWANS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/07_THE_UNSOCIAL_SWANS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/07_THE_UNSOCIAL_SWANS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a king named Gay-Chariot in a certain place. He owned a lake named Lotus Lake, which his soldiers guarded carefully. For many golden swans lived there, and they gave one tail-feather apiece every six months.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now to that lake came a great bird, all of gold. And they told him: “You cannot live among us. For we have rented this lake at the rate of a tail-feather for six months.” And so, to cut a long story short, a dispute arose.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 THE SELF-SACRIFICING DOVE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/08_THE_SELF-SACRIFICING_DOVE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/08_THE_SELF-SACRIFICING_DOVE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A ghastly fowler plied his trade&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of horror in a forest; made&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All living creatures hold their breath:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He seemed to them the god of death.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He had no comrade on the earth,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No friend, no relative by birth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They all renounced him; he had made&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Them do so by his horrid trade.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For you know&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The dreadful wretches bringing death On those who love their living breath,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With natural repulsion (like&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 THE OLD MAN WITH THE YOUNG WIFE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/09_THE_OLD_MAN_WITH_THE_YOUNG_WIFE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/09_THE_OLD_MAN_WITH_THE_YOUNG_WIFE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once an aged merchant in a certain town, and his name was Lovelorn. To such an extent had love clouded his reason that, when his wife died, he gave much money in order to marry the daughter of a penniless shopkeeper. But the girl was heartbroken and could not bear to look at the old merchant. This, indeed, might have been anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The silvered head will sue in vain,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 THE BRAHMAN, THE THIEF, AND THE GHOST</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/10_THE_BRAHMAN_THE_THIEF_AND_THE_GHOST/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/10_THE_BRAHMAN_THE_THIEF_AND_THE_GHOST/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a poor Brahman in a certain place. He lived on presents, and always did without such luxuries as fine clothes and ointments and perfumes and garlands and gems and betel-gum. His beard and his nails were long, and so was the hair that covered his head and his body. Heat, cold, rain, and the like had dried him up.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then someone pitied him and gave him two calves. And the Brahman began when they were little and fed them on butter and oil and fodder and other things that he begged. So he made them very plump.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 THE SNAKE IN THE PRINCE’S BELLY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/11_THE_SNAKE_IN_THE_PRINCES_BELLY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/11_THE_SNAKE_IN_THE_PRINCES_BELLY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain city dwelt a king whose name was God-like. He had a son who wasted daily in every limb because of a snake that used his belly as a home instead of an ant-hill. So the prince became dejected and went to another country. In a city of that country he begged alms, spending his time in a great temple.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now in that city was a king named Gift who had two daughters in early womanhood. One of these bowed daily at her father’s feet with the greeting: “Victory, O King,” while the other said: “Your deserts, O King.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 THE GULLIBLE CARPENTER</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/12_THE_GULLIBLE_CARPENTER/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/12_THE_GULLIBLE_CARPENTER/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a carpenter in a certain village. His wife was a whore, and reputed to be such. So he, desiring to test her, thought; “How can I put her to the test? For the proverb says:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Fire chills, rogues bless, and moonlight burns&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before a wife to virtue turns.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Now I know from popular gossip that she is unfaithful. For the saying goes:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All things that are not seen or heard&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 MOUSE-MAID MADE MOUSE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/13_MOUSE-MAID_MADE_MOUSE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/13_MOUSE-MAID_MADE_MOUSE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The billows of the Ganges were dotted with pearly foam born of the leaping of fishes frightened at hearing the roar of the waters that broke on the rugged, rocky shore. On the bank was a hermitage crowded with holy men devoting their time to the performance of sacred rites — chanting, self-denial, self-torture, study, fasting and sacrifice. They would take purified water only, and that in measured sips. Their bodies wasted under a diet of bulbs, roots, fruits, and moss. A loin-cloth made of bark formed their scanty raiment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 THE BIRD WITH GOLDEN DUNG</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/14_THE_BIRD_WITH_GOLDEN_DUNG/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/14_THE_BIRD_WITH_GOLDEN_DUNG/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a great tree on a mountain side. On it lived a bird in whose dung gold appeared.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day a hunter came to the spot, and directly in front of him the bird dropped its dung, which at the moment of falling turned to gold. At this the hunter was amazed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Well, well!” said he. “For eighty years, man and boy, I have had bird-trapping on the brain, and I never once saw gold in a bird’s dung.” So he set a snare in the tree. And the bird, fool that he was, forgot the danger, and perched on the customary spot. Of course, he was caught immediately.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 THE CAVE THAT TALKED</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/15_THE_CAVE_THAT_TALKED/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/15_THE_CAVE_THAT_TALKED/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a lion in a part of a forest, and his name was Rough-Claw. One day he found nothing whatever to eat in his wanderings, and his throat was pinched by hunger. At sunset he came to a great mountain cave and went in, for he thought: “Surely, some animal will come into this cave during the night. I will hide and wait.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Presently the owner of the cave, a jackal named Curd-Face, came to the door and began to sing: “Cave ahoy! Cave aho-oy!” Then after a moment’s silence, he continued in the same tone: “Hello! Don’t you remember how you and I made an agreement that I was to speak to you when I came back from the world outside, and that you were to sing out to me? But you won’t speak to me today. So I am going off to that other cave, which will return my greeting.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 THE FROGS THAT RODE SNAKEBACK</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/16_THE_FROGS_THAT_RODE_SNAKEBACK/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/16_THE_FROGS_THAT_RODE_SNAKEBACK/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once an elderly black snake in a certain spot, and his name was Slow-Poison. He considered the situation from this point of view: “How in the world can I get along without overtaxing my energies?” Then he went to a pond containing many frogs, and behaved as if very dejected.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As he waited thus, a frog came to the edge of the water and asked: “Uncle, why don’t you bustle about today for food as usual?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 THE BUTTER-BLINDED BRAHMAN</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/17_THE_BUTTER-BLINDED_BRAHMAN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/03_CROWS_AND_OWLS/17_THE_BUTTER-BLINDED_BRAHMAN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a Brahman named Theodore in a certain town. His wife, being unchaste and a pursuer of other men, was forever making cakes with sugar and butter for a lover, and so cheating her husband.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now one day her husband saw her and said: “My dear wife, what are you cooking? And where are you for ever carrying cakes? Tell the truth.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But her impudence was equal to the occasion, and she lied to her husband. “There is a shrine of the blessed goddess not far from here. There I have undertaken a fasting ceremony, and I take an offering, including the most delicious dishes.” Then she took the cakes before his very eyes and started for the shrine of the goddess, imagining that after her statement, her husband would believe it was for the goddess that his wife was daily providing delicious dishes. Having reached the shrine, she went down to the river to perform the ceremonial bath.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
