<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 THE LOSS OF FRIENDS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 THE LOSS OF FRIENDS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE WEDGE-PULLING MONKEY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/01_THE_WEDGE-PULLING_MONKEY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/01_THE_WEDGE-PULLING_MONKEY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was a city in a certain region. In a grove near by, a merchant was having a temple built. Each day at the noon hour the foreman and workers would go to the city for lunch.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now one day a troop of monkeys came upon the half-built temple. There lay a tremendous anjana-log, which a mechanic had begun to split, a wedge of acacia-wood being thrust in at the top.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 THE JACKAL AND THE WAR-DRUM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/02_THE_JACKAL_AND_THE_WAR-DRUM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/02_THE_JACKAL_AND_THE_WAR-DRUM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain region was a jackal whose throat was pinched by hunger. While wandering in search of food, he came upon a king’s battle ground in the midst of a forest. And as he lingered a moment there he heard a great sound.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This sound troubled his heart exceedingly, so that he fell into deep dejection and said: “Ah me! Disaster is upon me. I am as good as dead already. Who made that sound? What kind of a creature?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 MERCHANT STRONG-TOOTH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/03_MERCHANT_STRONG-TOOTH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/03_MERCHANT_STRONG-TOOTH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a city called Growing City on the earth’s surface. In it lived a merchant named Strong-Tooth who directed the whole administration. So long as he handled city business and royal business, all the inhabitants were satisfied. Why spin it out? Nobody ever saw or heard of his like for cleverness. For there is much wisdom in the proverb:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Suppose he minds the king’s affairs,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The common people hate him;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 GODLY AND JUNE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/04_GODLY_AND_JUNE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/04_GODLY_AND_JUNE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain district there was a monastery in a secluded spot. In it lived a holy man named Godly, who in course of time acquired a great sum of money by selling finely woven garments, the numerous offerings of the faithful for whom he performed sacrifices. As a result, he trusted no man, and kept his treasure under his arm by night and day. For there is wisdom in the proverb:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 THE JACKAL AT THE RAM-FIGHT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/05_THE_JACKAL_AT_THE_RAM-FIGHT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/05_THE_JACKAL_AT_THE_RAM-FIGHT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now Godly sat down perfectly carefree, for his disciple’s countless virtues had lulled his suspicions. As he rested, he saw a herd of rams, and two of them fighting. These two would angrily draw apart and dash together, their slablike foreheads crashing so that blood flowed freely. This spectacle attracted a jackal whose soul was in the fetters of carnivorous desire, and he stood between the two, lapping up the blood.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 THE WEAVER’S WIFE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/06_THE_WEAVERS_WIFE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/06_THE_WEAVERS_WIFE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now as he walked along, Godly spied a weaver who with his wife was on his way to a neighboring city for liquor to drink, and he called out: “Look here, my good fellow! I come to you a guest, brought by the evening sun. I do not know a soul in the village. Let me receive the treatment due a guest. For the proverb says&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No stranger may be turned aside&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 HOW THE CROW-HEN KILLED THE BLACK SNAKE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/07_HOW_THE_CROW-HEN_KILLED_THE_BLACK_SNAKE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/07_HOW_THE_CROW-HEN_KILLED_THE_BLACK_SNAKE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain region grew a great banyan tree. In it lived a crow and his wife, occupying the nest which they had built. But a black snake crawled through the hollow trunk and ate their chicks as fast as they were born, even before baptism. Yet for all his sorrow over this violence, the poor crow could not desert the old familiar banyan and seek another tree. For&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Three cannot be induced to go—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 THE HERON THAT LIKED CRAB-MEAT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/08_THE_HERON_THAT_LIKED_CRAB-MEAT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/08_THE_HERON_THAT_LIKED_CRAB-MEAT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a heron in a certain place on the edge of a pond. Being old, he sought an easy way of catching fish on which to live. He began by lingering at the edge of his pond, pretending to be quite irresolute, not eating even the fish within his reach.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now among the fish lived a crab. He drew near and said: “Uncle, why do you neglect today your usual meals and amusements?” And the heron replied: “So long as I kept fat and flourishing by eating fish, I spent my time pleasantly, enjoying the taste of you. But a great disaster will soon befall you. And as I am old, this will cut short the pleasant course of my life. For this reason I feel depressed.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 NUMSKULL AND THE RABBIT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/09_NUMSKULL_AND_THE_RABBIT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/09_NUMSKULL_AND_THE_RABBIT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a part of a forest was a lion drunk with pride, and his name was Numskull. He slaughtered the animals without ceasing. If he saw an animal, he could not spare him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So all the natives of the forest—deer, boars, buffaloes, wild oxen, rabbits, and others came together, and with woe-begone countenances, bowed heads, and knees clinging to the ground, they undertook to beseech obsequiously the king of beasts: “Have done, O King, with this merciless, meaningless slaughter of all creatures. It is hostile to happiness in the other world. For the Scripture says:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 THE WEAVER WHO LOVED A PRINCESS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/10_THE_WEAVER_WHO_LOVED_A_PRINCESS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/10_THE_WEAVER_WHO_LOVED_A_PRINCESS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Molasses Belt is a city called Sugarcane City In it lived two friends, a weaver and a carpenter. Since they were past masters in their respective crafts, they had earned enough money by their labors so that they kept no account of receipt and expenditure. They wore soft, gaily colored, expensive garments, adorned themselves with flowers and betel-leaves, and diffused odors of camphor, aloes, and musk. They worked nine hours a day, after which they adorned their persons and met for recreation in such places as public squares or temples. They made the rounds of the spots where society gathered—theaters, &lt;em&gt;conversaziones&lt;/em&gt;, birthday parties, banquets, and the like—then went home at twilight. And so the time passed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 THE UNGRATEFUL MAN</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/11_THE_UNGRATEFUL_MAN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/11_THE_UNGRATEFUL_MAN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town lived a Brahman whose name was Sacrifice. Everyday his wife, chafing under their poverty, would say to him: “Come, Brahman! Lazybones! Stony-Heart! Don’t you see your babies starving, while you hang about, mooning? Go somewhere, no matter where, find some way, any way, to get food, and come back in a hurry.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At last the Brahman, weary of this refrain, undertook a long journey, and in a few days entered a great forest. While wandering hungry in this forest, he began to hunt for water. And in a certain spot he came upon a well, overgrown with grass. When he looked in, he discovered a tiger, a monkey, a snake, and a man at the bottom. They also saw him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 LEAP AND CREEP</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/12_LEAP_AND_CREEP/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/12_LEAP_AND_CREEP/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the palace of a certain king stood an incomparable bed, blessed with every cubiculary virtue. In a corner of its coverlet lived a female louse named Creep. Surrounded by a thriving family of sons and daughters, with the sons and daughters of sons and daughters, and with more remote descendants, she drank the king’s blood as he slept. On this diet she grew plump and handsome.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While she was living there in this manner, a flea named Leap drifted in on the wind and dropped on the bed. This flea felt supreme satisfaction on examining the bed-the wonderful delicacy of its coverlet, its double pillow, its exceptional softness like that of a broad, Gangetic sand-bank, its delicious perfume. Charmed by the sheer delight of touching it, he hopped this way and that until-fate willed it so-he chanced to meet Creep, who said to him: “Where do you come from? This is a dwelling fit for a king. Begone, and lose no time about it.” “Madam,” said he, “you should not say such things. For&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 THE BLUE JACKAL</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/13_THE_BLUE_JACKAL/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/13_THE_BLUE_JACKAL/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a jackal named Fierce-Howl, who lived in a cave near the suburbs of a city. One day he was hunting for food, his throat pinched with hunger, and wandered into the city after nightfall. There the city dogs snapped at his limbs with their sharp-pointed teeth, and terrified his heart with their dreadful barking, so that he stumbled this way and that in his efforts to escape and happened into the house of a dyer. There he tumbled into a tremendous indigo vat, and all the dogs went home.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 PASSION AND THE OWL</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/14_PASSION_AND_THE_OWL/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/14_PASSION_AND_THE_OWL/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Within a certain forest was a broad expanse of lake. There lived a king-swan named Passion, who spent his days in a great variety of pastimes. One day death, fatal death visited him in the person of an owl. And the swan said: “This is a lonely wood. Where do you come from?” The owl replied: “I came because I heard of your virtues. Furthermore,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In search of virtue roaming&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 UGLY’S TRUST ABUSED</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/15_UGLYS_TRUST_ABUSED/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/15_UGLYS_TRUST_ABUSED/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain city lived a merchant named Ocean, who loaded a hundred camels with valuable cloth and set out in a certain direction. Now one of his camels, whose name was Ugly, was overburdened and fell limp, with every limb relaxed. Then the merchant divided the pack of cloth, loaded it on other camels, and because he found himself in a wild forest region where delay was impossible, he proceeded, leaving Ugly behind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 THE LION AND THE CARPENTER</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/16_THE_LION_AND_THE_CARPENTER/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/16_THE_LION_AND_THE_CARPENTER/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain city lived a carpenter named Trustgod. It was his constant habit to carry his lunch and go with his wife into the forest, where he cut great anjana logs. Now in that forest lived a lion named Spotless, who had as hangers-on two carnivorous creatures, a jackal and a crow.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day the lion was roaming the wood alone and encountered the carpenter. The carpenter for his part, on beholding that most alarming lion, whether considering himself already lost or perhaps with the ready wit to perceive that it is safer to face the powerful, advanced to meet the lion, bowed low, and said: “Come, friend, come! Today you must eat my own dinner which my wife—your brother’s wife—has provided.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 THE PLOVER WHO FOUGHT THE OCEAN</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/17_THE_PLOVER_WHO_FOUGHT_THE_OCEAN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/17_THE_PLOVER_WHO_FOUGHT_THE_OCEAN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A plover and his wife once lived by the shore of the sea, the mighty sea that swarms with’ fish, crocodiles, turtles, sharks, porpoises, pearl oysters, shellfish, and other teeming life. The plover was called Sprawl, and his wife’s name was Constance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In due time she became pregnant and was ready to lay her eggs. So she said to her husband: “Please find a spot where I may lay my eggs.” “Why,” said he, “this home of ours, inherited from our ancestors, promises progress. Lay your eggs here.” “Oh,” said she, “don’t mention this dreadful place. Here is the ocean near at hand. His tide might some day make a long reach and lick away my babies.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 SHELL-NECK, SLIM, AND GRIM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/18_SHELL-NECK_SLIM_AND_GRIM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/18_SHELL-NECK_SLIM_AND_GRIM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain lake lived a turtle named Shell-Neck. He had as friends two ganders whose names were Slim and Grim. Now in the vicissitudes of time there came a twelve-year drought, which begot ideas of this nature in the two ganders: “This lake has gone dry. Let us seek another body of water. However, we must first say farewell to Shell-Neck, our dear and long-proved friend.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When they did so, the turtle said: “Why do you bid me farewell? I am a water-dweller, and here I should perish very quickly from the scant supply of water and from grief at loss of you. Therefore, if you feel any affection for me, please rescue me from the jaws of this death. Besides, as the water dries in this lake, you two suffer nothing beyond a restricted diet, while to me it means immediate death. Consider which is more serious, loss of food or loss of life.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 FORETHOUGHT, READYWIT, AND FATALIST</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/19_FORETHOUGHT_READYWIT_AND_FATALIST/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/19_FORETHOUGHT_READYWIT_AND_FATALIST/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a great lake lived three full-grown fishes, whose names were Forethought, Readywit, and Fatalist. Now one day the fish named Forethought overheard passers-by on the bank and fishermen saying: “There are plenty of fish in this pond. Tomorrow we go fishing.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On hearing this, Forethought reflected: “This looks bad. Tomorrow or the day after they will be sure to come here. I will take Readywit and Fatalist and move to another lake whose waters are not troubled.” So he called them and put the question.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 THE DUEL BETWEEN ELEPHANT AND SPARROW</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/20_THE_DUEL_BETWEEN_ELEPHANT_AND_SPARROW/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/20_THE_DUEL_BETWEEN_ELEPHANT_AND_SPARROW/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a dense bit of jungle lived a sparrow and his wife, who had built their nest on the branch of a tamal tree, and in course of time a family appeared.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now one day a jungle elephant with the spring fever was distressed by the heat, and came beneath that tamal tree in search of shade. Blinded by his fever, he pulled with the tip of his trunk at the branch where the sparrows had their nest, and broke it. In the process the sparrows’ eggs were crushed, though the parent-birds—further life being predestined—barely escaped death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 THE SHREWD OLD GANDER</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/21_THE_SHREWD_OLD_GANDER/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/21_THE_SHREWD_OLD_GANDER/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a part of a forest was a fig tree with massive branches. In it lived a flock of wild geese. At the root of this tree appeared a creeping vine of the species called &lt;em&gt;koshambi&lt;/em&gt;. Thereupon the old gander said: “This vine that is climbing our fig tree bodes ill to us. By means of it, someone might perhaps climb up here some day and kill us. Take it away while it is still slender and readily cut.” But the geese despised his counsel and did not cut the vine, so that in course of time it wound its way up the tree.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 THE LION AND THE RAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/22_THE_LION_AND_THE_RAM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/22_THE_LION_AND_THE_RAM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a part of a forest was a ram, separated from his flock. In the armor of his great fleece and horns, he roamed the wood, a tough customer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now one day a lion in that forest, who had a retinue of all kinds of animals, encountered him. At this unprecedented sight, since the wool so bristled in every direction as to conceal the body, the lion’s heart was troubled and invaded by fear. “Surely, he is more powerful than I am,” thought he. “That is why he wanders here so fearlessly.” And the lion edged away.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 SMART, THE JACKAL</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/23_SMART_THE_JACKAL/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/23_SMART_THE_JACKAL/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a part of a forest lived a lion named Thunder-Fang, in a company with three counselors, a wolf, a jackal, and a camel, whose names were Meat-Face, Smart, and Spike-Ear. One day he fought with a furious elephant whose sharp-pointed tusk so tore his body that he withdrew from the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then, suffering from a seven-day fast, his body lean with hunger, he said to his famished advisers: “Round up some creature in the forest, so that, even in my present condition, I may provide needed nourishment for you.” The moment he issued his orders, they roamed the wood, but found nothing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 THE MONK WHO LEFT HIS BODY BEHIND</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/24_THE_MONK_WHO_LEFT_HIS_BODY_BEHIND/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/24_THE_MONK_WHO_LEFT_HIS_BODY_BEHIND/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Koshala country is a city called Unassailable. In it ruled a king named Fine-Chariot, over whose footstool rippled rays of light from the diadems of uncounted vassal princes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day a forest ranger came with this report: “Master, all the forest kings have become turbulent, and in their midst is the forest chief named Vindhyaka. It is the king’s affair to teach him modest manners.” On hearing this report, the king summoned Counselor Strong, and despatched him with orders to chastise the forest chieftains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 THE GIRL WHO MARRIED A SNAKE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/25_THE_GIRL_WHO_MARRIED_A_SNAKE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/25_THE_GIRL_WHO_MARRIED_A_SNAKE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Palace City lived a Brahman named Godly, whose childless wife wept bitterly when she saw the neighbors’ youngsters. But one day the Brahman said: “Forget your sorrow, mother dear. See! When I was offering the sacrifice for birth of children, an invisible being said to me in he clearest words: ‘Brahman, you shall have a son surpassing all mankind in beauty, character, and charm.’ “&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When she heard this, the wife felt her heart swell with supreme delight. “I only hope his promises come true,” she said. Presently she conceived, and in course of time gave birth to a snake. When she saw him, she paid no attention to her companions, who all advised her to throw him away. Instead, she took him and bathed him, laid him with motherly tenderness in a large, clean box, and pampered him with milk, fresh butter, and other good things, so that before many days had passed, he grew to maturity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 POOR BLOSSOM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/26_POOR_BLOSSOM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/26_POOR_BLOSSOM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;God Indra once had a parrot named Blossom. He enjoyed supreme beauty, loveliness, and various graces, while his intelligence was not blunted by his extensive scientific attainments.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day he was resting on the palm of great Indra’s hand, his body thrilling with delight at that contact, and was reciting a variety of authoritative formulas, when he caught sight of Yama, lord of death, who had come to pay his respects at the time appointed. Seeing the god, the parrot edged away. And all the thronging immortals asked him: “Why did you move away, sir, upon beholding that personage?” “But,” said the parrot, “he brings harm to all living creatures. Why not move away from him?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 THE UNTEACHABLE MONKEY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/27_THE_UNTEACHABLE_MONKEY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/27_THE_UNTEACHABLE_MONKEY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a part of a forest was a troop of monkeys who found a firefly one winter evening when they were dreadfully depressed. On examining the insect, they believed it to be fire, so lifted it with care, covered it with dry grass and leaves, thrust forward their arms, sides, stomachs, and chests, scratched themselves, and enjoyed imagining that they were warm. One of the arboreal creatures in particular, being especially chilly, blew repeatedly and with concentrated attention on the firefly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 RIGHT-MIND AND WRONG-MIND</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/28_RIGHT-MIND_AND_WRONG-MIND/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/28_RIGHT-MIND_AND_WRONG-MIND/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain city lived two friends, sons of merchants, and their names were Right-Mind and Wrong-Mind. These two traveled to another country far away in order to earn money. There the one named Right-Mind, as a consequence of favoring fortune, found a pot containing a thousand dinars, which had been hidden long before by a holy man. He debated the matter with Wrong-Mind, and they decided to go home, since their object was attained. So they returned together.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 A REMEDY WORSE THAN THE DISEASE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/29_A_REMEDY_WORSE_THAN_THE_DISEASE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/29_A_REMEDY_WORSE_THAN_THE_DISEASE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A flock of herons once had their nests on a fig tree in a part of a forest. In a hole in the tree lived a black snake who made a practice of eating the heron chicks before their wings sprouted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At last one heron, in utter woe at seeing the young ones eaten by a snake, went to the shore of the pond, shed a flood of tears, and stood with downcast face. And a crab who noticed him in this attitude, said: “Uncle, why are you so tearful today?” “My good friend,” said the heron, “what am I to do? Fate is against me. My babies and the youngsters belonging to my relatives have been eaten by a snake that lives in a hole in the fig tree. Grieved at their grief, I weep. Tell me, is there any possible device for killing him?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 THE MICE THAT ATE IRON</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/30_THE_MICE_THAT_ATE_IRON/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/30_THE_MICE_THAT_ATE_IRON/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town lived a merchant named Naduk, who lost his money and determined to travel abroad. For&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The meanest of mankind is he&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Who, having lost his money, can&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Inhabit lands or towns where once&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He spent it like a gentleman.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And again:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The neighbor gossips blame&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;His poverty as shame&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Who long was wont to play&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Among them, proud and gay.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In his house was an iron balance-beam inherited from his ancestors, and it weighed a thousand pals. This he put in pawn with Merchant Lakshman before he departed for foreign countries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 THE RESULTS OF EDUCATION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/31_THE_RESULTS_OF_EDUCATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/31_THE_RESULTS_OF_EDUCATION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a part of a mountain a hen-parrot brought two chicks into the world. These chicks were caught by a hunter when the mother had left the nest to search for food. One of them — since fate decreed it — contrived to escape, while the other was kept in a cage and taught to speak. Meanwhile, the first chick encountered a wandering holy man, who caught him, took him to his own hermitage, and gave him kindly care.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 THE SENSIBLE ENEMY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/32_THE_SENSIBLE_ENEMY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/32_THE_SENSIBLE_ENEMY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a prince who made friends with a merchant’s son and the son of a man of learning. Every day the three found entertainment in various diversions, flirtations, and pastimes in public squares, parks, and gardens. Every day the prince showed his aversion to the science of archery, to equitation and elephant-riding, to driving and hunting. At last, when his father one day gave him a wigging, telling him that he showed no aptitude for kingly pursuits, he disclosed to his two friends the injury inflicted on his self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 THE FOOLISH FRIEND</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/33_THE_FOOLISH_FRIEND/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/01_THE_LOSS_OF_FRIENDS/33_THE_FOOLISH_FRIEND/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this spot they sold all three gems, the merchant’s son serving as their agent. The considerable capital thus obtained he laid before the prince, who, having appointed the son of the man of learning his prime minister, planned to seize the kingdom of the monarch of that country, and made the merchant’s son his secretary of the treasury. He then, by offering double pay, assembled an army of picked elephants, horse, and infantry, began hostilities with a prime minister intelligent in the six expedients, killed the king in battle, seized his kingdom, and himself became king. Next he delegated all burdensome administrative functions to his two friends and consulted his ease in a life of graceful luxury.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
