<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Meta on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/ujjvala-nIla-maNiH/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Meta on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/ujjvala-nIla-maNiH/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>intro</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/ujjvala-nIla-maNiH/meta/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/pAtrANi/articles/ujjvala-nIla-maNiH/meta/intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Only two editions have been used to produce this edition of Ujjvala-nīlamaṇi: Pandit Durga Prasad and Vasudeva Lakshman Shastri Panshikar’s 1932 Nirnaya Sagara Press Kavyamala #95, reprinted by Chowkhamba in 1985, which contains Jiva Goswami’s &lt;em&gt;Locana-rocanī&lt;/em&gt; and Vishwanath’s &lt;em&gt;Ānanda-candrikā&lt;/em&gt; commentaries. This was published in Devanagari script. The second is Haridas Das’ 1955 edition, the second edition of which was edited by Kanai Lal Adhikari in 1964. This invaluable text contains the commentary of Vishnu Das, &lt;em&gt;Svātma-pramodinī,&lt;/em&gt; which was discovered in the Govindaji library in Jaipur by Haridas Das and was previously little known in the Vaishnava world. Vishnu Das was a disciple of Krishna Das Kaviraj, so his commentary comes chronologically between those of Jiva and Vishwanath. However, I have decided to place his commentary after the other two since Vishwanath is often engaged in fierce debate with Jiva, while Vishnu Das stands completely outside the discussion of many of the theological points (primarily the debate over the svakīyā-parakīyā issue) that are of major interest to these two giants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
