<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;राजचूडामणिदीक्षितः on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/AtmA_rasAdi/rAjachUDAmaNidIxitaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;राजचूडामणिदीक्षितः on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/AtmA_rasAdi/rAjachUDAmaNidIxitaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>काव्यदर्पणः (प्रथमो भागः)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/AtmA_rasAdi/rAjachUDAmaNidIxitaH/kAvyadarpaNaH_prathamo_bhAgaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kathA/AtmA_rasAdi/rAjachUDAmaNidIxitaH/kAvyadarpaNaH_prathamo_bhAgaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[काव्यदर्पणः (प्रथमो भागः)&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=MjQ2ODkxMzE0MzMwNzc1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOREWORD.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;MISSING_FIG href=&amp;quot;../books_images/U-IMG-1726837910m.png&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;strong&gt;NDIAN&lt;/strong&gt; Poetics have not yet received that due meed of world-recognition which it so richly and amply deserves. It comes next only to Indian philosophy in its complex and manifold affluence of subtle and delicate loveliness. It has received an illuminating elaboration from many gifted and penterative minds in the course of many centuries. It has been the fashion of late to cry down Sanskrit poetry as a barren Sahara of conceits and Sanskrit poetics as a barren Sahara of rules. But a close study of the best and highest works of Indian poesy and poetics shows that each of these branches of art— the creative and the critical— is a veritable mine of gold. Mr. A. B. Keith says well: &amp;ldquo;The theorists never forgot that genius was necessary for the highest poetry, as they show by the extraordinary fondness they show for citing Kalidasa and the premier rank they assign to him.&amp;rdquo; A nation that has produced Valmiki and Kalidasa among poets and Anandavardhana and Mammata among critics will easily get the highest seat of honour in the realms of creation and creative criticism by the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
