<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 PEACE on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 PEACE on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Treaty Between the Peacocks and the Swans</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/01_The_Treaty_Between_the_Peacocks_and_the_Swans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/01_The_Treaty_Between_the_Peacocks_and_the_Swans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;So soon as King Jewel-plume had retreated, the first care of King Silver-sides was the discovery of the treason that had cost him the fort.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Goose,&amp;rsquo; he said to his Minister, &amp;lsquo;who put the fire to our citadel, think you? Was it an enemy or an inmate?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Sire,&amp;rsquo; replied the Goose, &amp;lsquo;Night-cloud and his followers are nowhere to be seen—it must needs be his work.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;It must needs be,&amp;rsquo; sighed the King, after a pause; &amp;lsquo;but what ill-fortune!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Tortoise and the Geese</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/02_Tortoise_and_the_Geese/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/02_Tortoise_and_the_Geese/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There is a pool in South Behar called the &amp;lsquo;Pool of the Blue Lotus,&amp;rsquo; and two Geese had for a long time lived there. They had a friend in the pool who was a Tortoise, and he was known as &amp;lsquo;Shelly-neck.&amp;rsquo; It chanced one evening that the Tortoise overheard some fishermen talking by the water. &amp;lsquo;We will stop here to-night,&amp;rsquo; they said, &amp;lsquo;and in the morning we will catch the fish, the tortoises, and such like.&amp;rsquo; Extremely alarmed at this, the Tortoise repaired to his friends the Geese, and reported the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Fate and the Three Fishes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/03_Fate_and_the_Three_Fishes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/03_Fate_and_the_Three_Fishes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It was just such a pool as this, and on the arrival at it of just such men as these fishermen, that three fishes, who had heard their designs, held consultation as to what should be done.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;I shall go to another water,&amp;rsquo; said &amp;ldquo;Time-not-come,&amp;rdquo;[^1] and away he went.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Why should we leave unless obliged?&amp;rsquo; asked &amp;ldquo;Quick-at-peril.&amp;rdquo; &amp;lsquo;When the thing befalls I shall do the best I can—&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Who deals with bad dilemmas well, is wise.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The merchant&amp;rsquo;s wife, with womanly device,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kissed—and denied the kiss—under his eyes.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Unabashed Wife</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/04_Unabashed_Wife/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/04_Unabashed_Wife/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There was a trader in Vikrama-poora, who had a very beautiful wife, and her name was Jewel-bright. The lady was as unfaithful as she was fair, and had chosen for her last lover one of the household servants. Ah! womankind!—&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Sex, that tires of being true,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Base and new is brave to you!&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like the jungle-cows ye range,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Changing food for sake of change.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now it befell one day that as Jewel-bright was bestowing a kiss on the mouth of the servant, she was surprised by her husband; and seeing him she ran up hastily and said, &amp;lsquo;My lord, here is an impudent varlet! he eats the camphor which I procured for you; I was actually smelling it on his lips as you entered.&amp;rsquo; The servant catching her meaning, affected offence. &amp;lsquo;How can a man stay in a house where the mistress is always smelling one&amp;rsquo;s lips for a little camphor?&amp;rsquo; he said; and thereat he was for going off, and was only constrained by the good man to stay, after much entreaty. &amp;lsquo;Therefore,&amp;rsquo; said Quick-at-peril, &amp;lsquo;I mean to abide here, and make the best I can of what befalls, as she did.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Herons and the Mongoose[^2]</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/05_Herons_and_the_Mongoose2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/05_Herons_and_the_Mongoose2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Among the mountains of the north there is one named Eagle-cliff, and near it, upon a fig-tree, a flock of Herons had their residence. At the foot of the tree, in a hollow, there lived a serpent; and he was constantly devouring the nestlings of the Herons. Loud were the complaints of the parent birds, until an old Heron thus advised them:—&amp;lsquo;You should bring some fishes from the pool, and lay them one by one in a line from the hole of yonder Mongoose to the hollow where the Serpent lives. The Mongoose will find him when it comes after the fish, and if it finds him it will kill him.&amp;rsquo; The advice seemed good, and was acted upon; but in killing the Snake the Mongoose overheard the cry of the young Herons; and climbing the tree daily, he devoured all that the Snake had left. Therefore,&amp;rsquo; concluded the Geese, &amp;lsquo;do we bid you look well into your plan: if you should open your mouth, for instance, as we carry you, you will drop and be killed.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Recluse and the Mouse</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/06_Recluse_and_the_Mouse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/06_Recluse_and_the_Mouse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the forest of the Sage Gautama there dwelt a Recluse named Mighty-at-Prayer. Once, as he sat at his frugal meal, a young mouse dropped beside him from the beak of a crow, and he took it up and fed it tenderly with rice grains. Some time after the Saint observed a cat pursuing his dependent to devour it, whereupon he changed the mouse into a stout cat. The cat was a great deal harassed by dogs, upon which the Saint again transformed it into a dog. The dog was always in danger of the tigers, and his protector at last gave him the form of a tiger—considering him all this while, and treating him withal, like nothing but a mouse. The country-folk passing by would say, &amp;lsquo;That a tiger! not he; it is a mouse the Saint has transformed.&amp;rsquo; And the mouse being vexed at this, reflected, &amp;lsquo;So long as the Master lives, this shameful story of my origin will survive!&amp;rsquo; With this thought he was about to take the Saint&amp;rsquo;s life, when he, who knew his purpose, turned the ungrateful beast by a word to his original shape. Besides, your Majesty,&amp;rdquo; continued the Vulture, &amp;ldquo;it may not be so easy to take in Camphor-island—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Crane and the Crab</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/07_Crane_and_the_Crab/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/07_Crane_and_the_Crab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There was an old Crane at a mere called Lily-water, in Malwa, who stood one day in the shallows with a most dejected look and drooping bill. A Crab observed him and called out, &amp;lsquo;Friend Crane! have you given up eating, that you stand there all day?&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Nay, sir!&amp;rsquo; replied the old Crane; &amp;lsquo;I love my dish of fish, but I have heard the fishermen say that they mean to capture every one that swims in this water; and as that destroys my hope of subsistence, I am resigning myself to death.&amp;rsquo; All this the fishes overheard. &amp;lsquo;In this matter certainly,&amp;rsquo; they said, &amp;lsquo;his interest is ours; we ought to consult him; for it is written—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Brahman and the Pans</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/08_Brahman_and_the_Pans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/08_Brahman_and_the_Pans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There was a Brahman in the city of Vána, whose name was Deva Sarman. At the equinoctial feast of the Dussera, he obtained for his duxina-gift a dish of flour, which he took into a potter&amp;rsquo;s shed; and there lay down in the shade among the pots, staff in hand. As he thus reclined he began to meditate, &amp;lsquo;I can sell this meal for ten cowrie-shells, and with them I can purchase some of these pots and sell them at an advance. With all that money I shall invest in betel-nuts and body-cloths and make a new profit by their sale; and so go on trafficking till I get a lakh of rupees—what&amp;rsquo;s to prevent me? Then I shall marry four wives—and one at least will be beautiful and young, and she shall be my favorite. Of course the others will be jealous; but if they quarrel, and talk, and trouble me I will belabor them like this—and this&amp;rsquo;—and therewith he flourished his staff to such a purpose as to smash his meal-dish and break several of the potter&amp;rsquo;s jars. The potter, rushing out, took him by the throat, and turned him off; and so ended his speculations. I smiled, my Liege,&amp;rsquo; concluded the Vulture, &amp;lsquo;at your precipitancy, thinking of that story.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 The Duel of the Giants</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/09_The_Duel_of_the_Giants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/09_The_Duel_of_the_Giants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Long ago, my Liege, there were two Daityas named Sunda and Upasunda, the which with penance and fasting worshipped that God who wears the moon[^5] for his forehead-jewel; desiring to win his favor, and thereby the lordship of the Three Worlds. At last the God, propitiated by their devotion, spake thus unto them:—&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;I grant a boon unto ye—choose what it shall be.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;And they, who would have asked dominion, were suddenly minded of Saraswati[^6]—who reigns over the hearts and thoughts of men—to seek a forbidden thing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Brahman and the Goat</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/10_Brahman_and_the_Goat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/10_Brahman_and_the_Goat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Brahman that lived in the forest of Gautama, your Majesty. He had purveyed a goat to make pooja,[^11] and was returning home with it on life shoulder when he was descried by three knaves. &amp;lsquo;If we could but obtain that goat,&amp;rsquo; said they, &amp;lsquo;it would be a rare trick&amp;rsquo;; and they ran on, and seated themselves at the foot of three different trees upon the Brahman&amp;rsquo;s road. Presently he came up with the first of them, who addressed him thus: &amp;lsquo;Master! why do you carry that dog on your shoulder?&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Dog!&amp;rsquo; said the Brahman, &amp;lsquo;it is a goat for sacrifice!&amp;rsquo; With that he went on a coss,[^12] and came to the second knave; who called out—&amp;lsquo;What doest thou with that dog, Master?&amp;rsquo; The Brahman laid his goat upon the ground, looked it all over, took it up again upon his back, and walked on with his mind in a whirl; for—&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 Camel, the Lion, and His Court</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/11_Camel_the_Lion_and_His_Court/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/11_Camel_the_Lion_and_His_Court/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Camel, may it please you,&amp;rdquo; replied Night-cloud, &amp;ldquo;who strayed away from a kafila,[^13] and wandered into the forest. A Lion, named &amp;lsquo;Fierce-fangs,&amp;rsquo; lived in that forest; and his three courtiers, a Tiger, a Jackal, and a Crow, met the Camel, and conducted him to their King. His account of himself was satisfactory, and the Lion took him into his service under the name of Crop-ear. Now it happened that the rainy season was very severe, and the Lion became indisposed, so that there was much difficulty in obtaining food for the Court. The courtiers resolved accordingly to prevail on the Lion to kill the Camel; &amp;lsquo;for what interest have we,&amp;rsquo; they said, &amp;lsquo;in this browser of thistles?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 Frogs and the Old Serpent</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/12_Frogs_and_the_Old_Serpent/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/hitopadeshaH/en/edwin-arnold/04_PEACE/12_Frogs_and_the_Old_Serpent/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In a deserted garden there once lived a Serpent, &amp;lsquo;Slow-coil&amp;rsquo; by name; who had reached an age when he was no longer able to obtain his own food. Lying listlessly by the edge of a pond, he was descried by a certain Frog, and interrogated—&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Have you given up caring for food, Serpent?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Leave me, kindly Sir,&amp;rsquo; replied the subtle reptile; &amp;rsquo;the griefs of a miserable wretch like me cannot interest your lofty mind.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
