<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;सदास्वादः on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;सदास्वादः on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2012-09-29__1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-09-29__1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-09-29__1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-09-29, 21:22:24 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/iRivTBtYKVY&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hello, and welcome to the first edition of Sadāsvāda, an attempt at exploring the perennial pleasures of Sanskrit literature. We hope to look at one beautiful Sanskrit phrase every edition, with a morsel of information about its origin and context. While the futility of trying to drink an ocean by sampling drops here and there is not lost on us, we take some solace in the success of predecessors in this path, from Proust to Penzias. Without much further ado then, or as our Sanskrit plays would put it, अलम् अतिविस्तरेण (alam ativistareṇa), let us begin:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-10-03__2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-03__2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-03__2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-10-03, 22:12:15 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/GxK13Ty-Ujg&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the second edition ofSadāsvāda, an attempt at exploring the perennial pleasures of Sanskrit literature.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;एक-विक्रमाक्रान्त-सकल-भुवन-तल&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(eka-vikramā-&amp;lsquo;krānta-sakala-bhuvana-tala)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;one-stride-overcome-all-world-plane&amp;rdquo;, meaning &amp;ldquo;He who covered all worlds with just one stride&amp;rdquo;. &amp;lsquo;vikrama&amp;rsquo; also means &amp;lsquo;courage&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;strength&amp;rsquo;, and coupled with &amp;rsquo;eka&amp;rsquo; can also be understood to mean &amp;ldquo;He who conquered all worlds with his strength alone&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from Banabhatta&amp;rsquo;s Kadambari (Sentence 2 of the prose). Banabhatta is widely regarded as the greatest writer of ornate Sanskrit prose, and the Kadambari his magnum opus. The story of the Kadambari, an incredibly engrossing love-tale covering multiple &lt;em&gt;janmas&lt;/em&gt; (rebirths) of its characters, comes from the ancient epic stream of the Brhat-katha. While the tale itself can rank among the jewels of world literature, it is Bana&amp;rsquo;s breathtaking genius in composing majestic Sanskrit prose that makes the Kadambari irresistible. Descriptions of the minutest details - like say the footstool of a king - involve such brilliant wordplay, metaphors and cultural references that one is left wondering how &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; could &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; know so much, be so talented and observe so keenly.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The story begins by introducing the great King Shudraka. After describing him with sentence so ornate that it could make even the most manifestly powerful emperor blush, Bana does a second take with a line that is much shorter, but one which probably packs an even stronger punch. He says of Shudraka:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;नम्नैव यो निर्भिन्नाराति-हृदयो विरचित-नारसिंह-रूपाडम्बरम्, एक-विक्रमाक्रान्त-सकल-भुवन-तलो विक्रम-त्रयायासितं जहास इव वासुदेवम् |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;namnaiva yo nirbhinnārāti-hṛdayo viracita-nārasiṃha-rūpāḍambaram, eka-vikramākrānta-sakala-bhuvana-talo vikrama-trayāyāsitaṃ jahāsa iva vāsudevam.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;namna-eva - With just his name&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nirbhinna-arāti-hṛdayo - Break apart enemies&amp;rsquo; hearts&lt;br&gt;&#xA;viracita-nārasiṃha-rūpāḍambaram - Taken on the loud bombast of a half-man, half-lion form&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vikrama-trayāyāsitaṃ - Who tired himself with three steps&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;quot; The King, who could break apart enemies&amp;rsquo; hearts with just the mention of his name, and who conquered all worlds with just one stride (or, &amp;lsquo;with his strength alone&amp;rsquo;), seemed as if to laugh at poor Vishnu, who had to take on the loud, bombastic form of Narasimha, and who tired himself with &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; steps (as Vamana).&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;One pun, two mythological references, four BahuvrIhi&amp;rsquo;s each deserving a page of commentary, untranslateably brilliant choice of words (rūp&lt;strong&gt;āḍambaram,&lt;strong&gt;vikrama-tray&lt;/strong&gt;āyāsitaṃ&lt;/strong&gt;) - all in a nonchalant second sentence of an introduction. Truly, the pleasures of Bana are divine.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-10-10__3</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-10__3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-10__3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-10-10, 20:52:12 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/T7G1UGxOSKc&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;मत्तेभेन्द्र-विभिन्न-कुम्भ-पिशित-ग्रासैक-बद्ध-स्पृहः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(mattebhendra-vibhinna-kumbha-piśita-grāsaika-baddha-spṛhaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;rutting elephant king-broken-forehead-meat-mouthful-only-tied-desire&amp;rdquo;, meaning &amp;ldquo;He whose only desire is a mouthful of meat torn from the forehead of a rutting tusker&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from Bhartṛhari&amp;rsquo;s Nītiśatakam. Chances are, if you have ever enjoyed a subhāṣita in theśārdūlavikrīḍita metre, you&amp;rsquo;ve seen a glint ofBhartṛhari&amp;rsquo;sgenius. This philosopher-king distinguished himself with his eloquence, clarity of thought and wordsmithery in his famous three&lt;br&gt;&#xA;śatakas.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This line appears in a verse describing the self-respect of a lion, as an allegory to the conduct of self-respecting men:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;क्षुत्क्षामोऽपि जराकृशोऽपि शिथिलप्रायोऽपि कष्टां दशाम्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;आपन्नोऽपि विपन्न-दीधितिरपि प्राणेषु नश्यत्स्वपि ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;मत्तेभेन्द्र-विभिन्न-कुम्भ-पिशित-ग्रासैक-बद्ध-स्पृहः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;किं जीर्णं तृणमत्ति मानमहताम् अग्रेसरः केसरी ॥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kṣutkṣāmo&amp;rsquo;pi jarākṛśo&amp;rsquo;pi śithilaprāyo&amp;rsquo;pi kaṣṭāṃ daśām&lt;br&gt;&#xA;āpanno&amp;rsquo;pi vipanna-dīdhitirapi prāṇeṣu naśyatsvapi |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;mattebhendra-vibhinna-kumbha-piśita-grāsaika-baddha-spṛhaḥ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kiṃ jīrṇaṃ tṛṇamatti mānamahatām agresaraḥ kesarī ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(śārdūlavikrīḍitametre, 19 syllables per line)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Tormented by hunger, weak with age, brittle all over, facing difficult times, his majesty lost, his very breath close to ceasing - even in such a situation, does a lion, the foremost of all self-respecting beings,whose only desire is a mouthful of meat torn from the forehead of a rutting elephant, stoop to eating withered grass?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This poem is ripe with implications (ध्वनि) - the meat of a &lt;em&gt;rutting elephant&lt;/em&gt;, not, say, that of a doe; from the elephant&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;forehead&lt;/em&gt;, presumably after having killed it in a straight confrontation, not a sly attack from behind.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;At another level, the very structure of the poem resonates with the implication - the first two lines, describing the lion&amp;rsquo;s old age and physical frailty, are all composed of short words that break up over and over. In contrast, the third line roars powerfully, a &lt;em&gt;single 19-syllable bahuvrIhi compound&lt;/em&gt;, when the lion&amp;rsquo;s temperament is described. The contrast is so sharp that the 4th line need barely be said aloud - the majesty of the lion&amp;rsquo;s temperament has already made its physical weaknesses irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-10-18__4</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-18__4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-18__4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-10-18, 02:03:45 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/OSQ8JRtRa68&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अतिमानुषचेष्टित:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ati-mānuṣa-ceṣṭitaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;beyond-human-behavior&amp;rdquo;, meaning &amp;ldquo;One who has acted in a manner beyond the capacity of humans&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from the Mahābhārata, from a story called śuka-śakra-saṃvāda (parrot-Indra-conversation) in theAnuśāsana-parva. Where can one even begin describing the greatness of this epic? We would only begin to scratch the surface if we described it as the aggregated voice of the Indian thought-space speaking across millennia. Let us therefore focus quickly on today&amp;rsquo;s little gem: as tributaries to the central narrative of the Pāṇḍavas and the Kauravas, the epic has hundreds upon hundreds of stories that exemplify morals and offer reflection. This line is taken from one such minor story.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In a dense forest in the province of Kāśī, there was a large tree that offered shelter to hundreds of small animals and birds. One day, a hunter, looking to kill a deer, fired a poison arrow into the root of the tree. The poison was unexpectedly strong, and the tree slowly lost all its leaves and withered away. All the birds which had made their nests in it abandoned it. All, except for one little parrot.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Day after day, the little parrot continued to stay by the tree&amp;rsquo;s side, even as it got weaker and weaker. Then,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तमुदारं महासत्त्वम्&lt;strong&gt;अतिमानुषचेष्टितम्&lt;/strong&gt;।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;समदुःखसुखं दृष्ट्वा विस्मितःपाकशासनः॥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tam udāraṃ mahā-sattvam&lt;strong&gt;ati-mānuṣa-ceṣṭitam&lt;/strong&gt;|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sama-duḥkha-sukhaṃ dṛṣṭvā vismitaḥpāka-śāsanaḥ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(anuṣṭupmetre, 8x4 syllables)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;On seeing that noble bird, made of superior stuff, which had acted in a manner beyond mere humans, which was equanimuos to joy and sorrow, Indra himself, the king of the Gods and the slayer of Pāka, was amazed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra comes down in the form of a Brāhmaṇa, and asks the bird why it is choosing to wither along with the tree. There were so many fruit-laden trees in the forest, full of nests and welcoming shade, why wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it leave this dead wood (&amp;ldquo;gatāyuṣam asāmarthyaṃ kṣīṇasāraṃ hataśriyaṃ&amp;rdquo;) and find itself a nice home?&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The little parrot&amp;rsquo;s reply is the stuff of legend:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अस्मिन्नहं द्रुमे जातः साधुभिश्च गुणैर्युतः ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;बालभावे च संगुप्तः शत्रुभिश्च न धर्षितः ॥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;asminnahaṃ drume jātaḥ sādhubhiśca guṇairyutaḥ |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;bālabhāve ca saṃguptaḥ śatrubhiśca na dharṣitaḥ ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;I was born in this tree, and learnt every good thing I know from it. It kept me safe as a child, and protected me from enemies.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;नार्हसि त्वं सहस्राक्ष द्रुमं त्याजयितुं चिरात् !&lt;br&gt;&#xA;समर्थम् उपजीव्येमं त्यजेयं कथमद्य वै ?&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nārhasi tvaṃ sahasrākṣa drumaṃ tyājayituṃ cirāt !&lt;br&gt;&#xA;samartham upajīvyemaṃ tyajeyaṃ kathamadya vai ?&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;It is&lt;strong&gt;not in your authority&lt;/strong&gt;, O King of the Gods, to make me leave this tree. I lived with it when it was strong, how can I leave it today?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra, presumably not used to being spoken to like this, particularly from insignificant little birds, is even more stunned, and supremely delighted. He asks the bird to ask for any boon of its choice, and &amp;hellip; read theMahābhāratato find out! :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-10-23__Romanthaḥ - 1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-23__romanthaH_-_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-23__romanthaH_-_1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-10-23, 23:02:03 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/rGTEIIOHtsc&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear reader,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Our sincere thanks for your interest in our humble endeavor; our mailing list has grown to nearly 50 members in the short space of a month, and we&amp;rsquo;re overjoyed at this response. We thought this would be a good time to share some of the feedback, corrigenda and suggestions we&amp;rsquo;ve received.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh, a sahṛdaya-suhṛd-ratna to whom we are indebted in more ways than we can recount here, sends his regards and appreciation, in particular for edition #2 (Bhartṛhari&amp;rsquo;s hungry lion verse) and #4 (The parrot and Indra). He recounts several more subtle features of the hungry lion verse that make it a refined piece of art, no less: the repeated use of the single samuccayārthaka (conjunctive) word &amp;ldquo;api&amp;rdquo; six times, &amp;lsquo;building a case&amp;rsquo; as it were; the suggestion behind the sounds like agr&amp;quot;E&amp;quot;saraḥ k&amp;quot;E&amp;quot;sarī, with the long &amp;lsquo;E&amp;rsquo; in consonance with the unified majesty of the lion of the 3rd line, all the schools of sāhityaśāstra (guṇa, rīti, alaṃkāra, dhvani, vakrokti and aucitya) coming one after the other to enhance the Rasa.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;P.K.Ramakrishnan comments on the &amp;lsquo;Thought for today&amp;rsquo; of the second edition: we had written,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kiṃ vāsasā-iti-atra vicāraṇīyam&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vāsaḥ pradhānaṃ khalu yogyatāyai |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pītāmbaraṃ vīkṣya dadau svakanyām&lt;br&gt;&#xA;digambaraṃ vīkṣya viṣaṃ samudraḥ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;He notes that the last line might better read as, &amp;ldquo;carmāmbaraṃ vīkṣya viṣaṃ samudraḥ&amp;rdquo;. The contrast between wearing a hide and wearing silk is more apt than the contrast between being naked and wearing silk; the former is more in the same &amp;lsquo;category&amp;rsquo;. We thank Mr. Ramakrishnan for this suggestion, and welcome any such thoughts from him and you all. Please email us at &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;kvm&amp;hellip;.@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;shree&amp;hellip;@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-10-24__5</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-24__5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-24__5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-10-24, 19:53:37 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/LrhT-wKboZ4&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सुभगंमन्यमानः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(subhagaṃ-manyamānaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;fortunate-thinking&amp;rdquo;, meaning &amp;ldquo;One who thinks himself fortunate&amp;rdquo;, usually with a hint that one has thought so wrongly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from Daṇḍin&amp;rsquo;s Daśakumāracarita, from Chapter 7 (Apahāravarmacarita). Flip to any page of this prose work, and in the space of two pages you&amp;rsquo;ll be accosted bytigers, elephants, thieves, bad brahmins, good brahmins, piśācas, sundry ākāśavāṇīs - you might start to think this was an action movie that somehow traveled back in time! This story of 10 princes&amp;rsquo; adventures is incredibly fast-paced, and yet gives ample space for the author to display his famedpada-lālitya. Cute motifs pervade the work - for instance the poet never seems to miss an opportunity to describe sunsets over and over again with the inventive, topical and striking metaphors.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A common theme in the story is a beautiful, cunning woman cheating a naive man, and one of the heroes outwitting her and setting everything right (in addition to falling in love with a couple of noble women, rescuing old men and babies, killing wild beasts, taking trips to the underworld, freeing slaves, you know, all in a day&amp;rsquo;s work). In this scene, the current hero bumps into a naked, weeping Jain monk, and asks him what is wrong. The monk sighs, and relates a long story that starts with him as a rich, generous man. Many twists follow, and the last one involves him falling in love with a courtesan, who to his incredible joy accepts him. Then,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;सुभगंमन्यमानेन च मया स्वधनस्य स्वगृहस्य स्वगणस्य स्वदेहस्य स्वजीवितस्य च सा एवईश्वरीकृता | कृतः च अहम् अनया मलमल्लकशेषः |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;subhagaṃ-manyamānena ca mayā sva-dhanasya sva-gṛhasya sva-gaṇasya sva-dehasya sva-jīvitasya ca sā eva īśvarī-kṛtā | kṛtaḥ ca aham anayā malamallaka-śeṣaḥ |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Thinking myself fortunate [to have won her affection], I made her the Queen of my money, my home, my followers, my body, even my very life. She left me with just my loincloth.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;malamallaka-śeṣaḥ is literally &amp;ldquo;loincloth-remaining&amp;rdquo; - &amp;ldquo;one who has only his loincloth left&amp;rdquo;, and was itself a tough contender for today&amp;rsquo;s spot! :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-10-30__6</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-30__6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-10-30__6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-10-30, 21:37:12 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/TtbYQ3gQ1B4&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पीतोदका, जग्धतृणा, दुग्धदोहा&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(pītodakā jagdhatṛṇā dugdhadohā)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;drunk-waters, eaten-grass, milked-milk&amp;rdquo;, meaning &amp;ldquo;They who have drunk their (final) waters, eaten their (last) grass, had their milk (completely) milked&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; ultimately meaning &amp;ldquo;old, withered and barren&amp;rdquo;. This degree of &amp;lsquo;inference&amp;rsquo; in a Bahuvrīhi almost borders on being idiomatic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from the Kaṭhopaniṣad, the second verse of the first chapter. This upaniṣad is one of the ten principal ones, and involves several all-time blockbusters of Indian philosophical thought &amp;ndash; the conversation between Naciketa and Yama, the distinction between preyas (the pleasurable) andśreyas (the good) and the idea of an eternal, indestructible soul that Death merely transforms.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;King Vājaśravasa had a young son named Naciketa. One day, the king was donating cows as charity. Naciketa then noticed,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पीतोदका जग्धतृणा दुग्धदोहा निरिन्द्रियाः |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अनन्दा नाम ते लोका ये स गच्छति ता ददत् ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pītodakā jagdhatṛṇā dugdhadohā nirindriyāḥ |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;anandā nāma te lokā ye sa gacchati tā dadat ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;These (cows) have drunk their waters, eaten their grass and have had their last milk milked. They are old and barren. One will get nothing but unhappiness if one gives them away as charity.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In a poignant move that has been debated for centuries, Naciketa asks his father, &amp;ldquo;Tāta, kasmai māṃ dāsyasi?&amp;rdquo; (Father, who will you give me away to?).Vājaśravasa ignores him, but he asks him again and again. The king gets irritated, and shouts, &amp;ldquo;Mṛtyave tvā dadāmi!&amp;rdquo; (I give you to Death!). We don&amp;rsquo;t know if he regretted his rash action right afterward, but Naciketa dutifully set out to the South to meet Yama, the god of Death. Their conversation is the content of the rest of the Upaniṣad.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-11-05__7</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-05__7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-05__7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-11-05, 20:12:31 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/0bw62VLsG4Y&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अविदितगतयामा [रात्रिः]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(avidita-gata-yāmā [rātriḥ])&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;unknowingly-gone-hours [night]&amp;rdquo; , meaning &amp;ldquo;[The night] whose course/hours passed unknowingly&amp;rdquo;. Yāma means both &amp;lsquo;course&amp;rsquo; as well as a unit of 3 hours used most commonly when measuring night times (for example a synonym for night is triyāma, &amp;rsquo;the one with lasting 3yāmas&amp;rsquo;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from Bhavabhūti&amp;rsquo;s play Uttararāmacaritam, first act verse 27. It&amp;rsquo;s often said that there is no greater delight than theUttararāmacaritam for a mind with a taste forpathos (karuṇā). The content of the play derives from the Rāmāyaṇa and involves events after the war with Rāvaṇa.Rāma makes the harsh decision of abandoning a pregnant Sītā in response to slander against her character, and the story continues with the birth and ascent of his sons Lava and Kuśa.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Bhavabhūti is often placed beside Kālidāsa in lists of Sanskrit&amp;rsquo;s greatest playwrights; in fact, there is an entire genre of writing that involves fictional stories of these two poets sparring with each other.Bhavabhūti is depicted as an learned, passionate, highly emotional poet who nevertheless is just a shade lesser than thebalanced, effortlessly brilliantKālidāsa whose simplicity is beyond genius. The modern historical view is that they were not contemporaries at all, but that is a minor nitpick compared to the poetic and entertainment value of these imagined contests :-)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;TheUttararāmacaritam begins withRāma having his daily meetings withSītā by his side. Several attendants come in with news and personal messages from well-wishers and this sets the scene. In classic fashion, there are several forebodings of what is to come, but of course the characters are unaware of that. Lakṣmaṇa then enters, and escorts the couple to a newly completed picture gallery which has portraits of events from Rāma&amp;rsquo;s life. The trio chat heartily as they move from picture to picture, fromRāma&amp;rsquo;s birth, Viśvāmitra&amp;rsquo;s arrival,Rāma winningSītā and his victorious arrival into the city, etc. The poet cleverly uses this to sketchRāma&amp;rsquo;s dignity and appropriateness for which this play is famous; for example, when the trio comes to a picture of Kaikeyi,Rāma makes up an quick excuse and moves on.Rāma andSītā&amp;rsquo;s mutual love is also brought out beautifully.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The trio then come to a picture of the Prasravaṇa mountain in the Janasthāna forest. This is last time the couple was happy together in the forest.Rāma reminisces about those wonderful nights, and asksSītā if she remembers the time when:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;किमपि किमपि मन्दं मन्दमासक्तियोगात्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अविरलितकपोलं जल्पतोरक्रमेण |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अशिथिलपरिरम्भव्यापृतैकैकदोष्णो:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;अविदितगतयामा&lt;/strong&gt;रात्रिरेव व्यरंसीत् ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kimapi kimapi mandaṃ mandam āsaktiyogāt&lt;br&gt;&#xA;aviralita-kapolaṃ jalpator-akrameṇa |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;aśithila-parirambha-vyāpṛt-aikaika-doṣṇoḥ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;avidita-gata-yāmā&lt;/strong&gt;rātrireva vyaraṃsīt ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(mālinī metre, 15 syllables per line)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;We were sitting close together, our cheeks touching and arms in a tight embrace, chatting aimlessly about all kinds of things &amp;ndash; the night itself went by before we knew it!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This is probably the most famous verse of the work because of a cute story: In one of the fictionalBhavabhūti vs Kālidāsa tales, it&amp;rsquo;s said thatBhavabhūti had originally written the 4th line as &amp;ldquo;avidita-gata-yāmārātrireva&lt;strong&gt;ṃ&lt;/strong&gt;vyaraṃsīt&amp;rdquo; - it&amp;rsquo;s still in the same metre, but means &amp;ldquo;the night&lt;em&gt;thus&lt;/em&gt;passed unknowingly&amp;rdquo;. He goes toKālidāsa to get his play reviewed.Kālidāsa is (as can be expected) in a state of general bliss, calmly chewing his betel leaf after his meal. He reads the play, smiles atBhavabhūti and hands him a betel leaf with a big circle of slaked lime in its middle. He tells him, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t you think that&amp;rsquo;s a little too much lime?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Bhavabhūti goes home, and tries to decipher this. &amp;ldquo;Too much lime? Maybe he means I&amp;rsquo;m overpowering the mood somewhere. But where? Why would he give me a betel leaf? Well typically a betel leaf is chewed after a hearty meal, in a calm, serene, happy setting. The only such moods in my work are at the happy ending and the happy beginning. Happy endings are fine &amp;ndash; let me check my beginning again&amp;rdquo;. Lo and behold! He finds this verse, and sees that removing theanusvāra (the circle) would make the line go from the bald journalistic tone of&amp;quot;the night&lt;em&gt;thus&lt;/em&gt;passed unknowingly&amp;quot; to the beautifully poetic &amp;ldquo;the night&lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt;passed unknowingly&amp;rdquo; :-)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This is a major turning point in the play. That event was the last time the couple were together in the forest, and is now the last time they are together in their adulthood. What happens next? Read theUttararāmacaritam to find out, and to develop a most vile distaste for public opinion!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-11-12__8</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-12__8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-12__8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-11-12, 19:50:02 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/el3bOFvRmEY&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;चरणार्धरुद्धवसुधः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(caraṇa-ardha-ruddha-vasudhaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;foot-half-pressed down-earth&amp;rdquo; , meaning &amp;ldquo;(He who is) pressing down on the earth with half his foot&amp;rdquo; or more simply, &amp;ldquo;standing tip-toed&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from a verse in the Amaruśatakaṃ, one of the finest collections of love poetry in Sanskrit. The origin of this work (anthology?) is steeped in legend and the mists of time; attributions range from a unknown King Amaru of Kashmir, toŚaṃkarācārya in a daredevil body-swapping adventure. A wide variety of themes are seen &amp;ndash; longing to lovers&amp;rsquo; quarrels to separation; devious schemes designed at lightning speed to stop the house parrot from squeaking out the night&amp;rsquo;s secrets in front of parents, to a new vision of Advaita, where only She appears wherever the poor Mumukṣu looks; the lady&amp;rsquo;s anger expressed at one time with excess courtesy, and in another by kicking away her beloved grovelling at her feet, with a subtle hint that the former was more hurtful. In all, a thoroughly enjoyable and revisitable masterpiece.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In what is in our opinion the most beautifully meditative verse of the collection, a traveler&amp;rsquo;s tiny gesture is captured in a picture-in-words:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;देशैरन्तरिता शतैश्च सरितामुर्वीभृतां काननैः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;यत्नेनापि न याति लोचनपथं कान्तेति जानन्नपि ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;उद्ग्रीव&lt;strong&gt;श्चरणार्धरुद्धवसुधः&lt;/strong&gt;कृत्वाश्रुपूर्णां दृशं&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तामाशां पथिकस्तथापि किमपि ध्यायंश्चिरं वीक्षते ॥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;deśair-antaritā śataiś-ca saritām urvībhṛtāṃ kānanaiḥ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;yatnenāpi na yāti locana-pathaṃ kānteti jānann-api |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;udgrīvaś&lt;strong&gt;caraṇārdha-ruddha-vasudhaḥ&lt;/strong&gt;kṛtvāśrupūrṇāṃ dṛśaṃ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tāmāśāṃ pathikastathāpi kimapi dhyāyaṃściraṃ vīkṣate ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(śārdūlavikrīḍita, 19 syllables per line)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Hundreds of kingdoms and forests and rivers and mighty mountains separate them,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;there&amp;rsquo;s no way he can possibly see her &amp;ndash; even though he knows this,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Neck upturned, tip-toed, with teary eyes,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;the traveler thoughtfully gazes homeward.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In some of the best writtenśārdūlavikrīḍitas, the first two lines set the context, and the third line (and sometimes the fourth) contain the soul of the poem. Here, the first two lines are nice and do their job, but the third one, especially today&amp;rsquo;s phrase, is what pushes this into the realm of genius. Consider just that phrase.Thesamāsa, of course, transmits several more hints than can be captured in one paragraph, let alone by the bald phrase &amp;ldquo;tip-toed&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; the incongruity (intrepid or foolish or timorous?) of pressing down on the mighty earth with not even the whole of his foot; of pressing downwith his footon&lt;em&gt;vasudhā&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;the bearer of riches&amp;rdquo; and not earth by some other denotation like bhūmi or pṛthvī &amp;ndash; perhaps signifying a conflict in himself for having left his beloved for the sake of mere money (the main purpose of travel in these poems was to earn money); &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;ruddha&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; &amp;ndash; he didn&amp;rsquo;t raise himself up, he&lt;em&gt;pushed the earth down&lt;/em&gt;, an act which we guess was easier than supporting up the weight he bears in his heart. Need we say more? :-)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The image sets our mind racing in multiple directions. In just that tiny detail of a tip-toe, that conscious, incremental, quivering tip-toe, is contained the audacity of hope, the irrationality that is the very essence of the human condition, the vulnerability that is the soul of love and longing, and a gentle reminder of our stark loneliness in a pitilessly indifferent universe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-11-15__Romanthaḥ - 2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-15__romanthaH_-_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-15__romanthaH_-_2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-11-15, 19:26:58 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/qlrSksOjaaU&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear reader,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;It is already time for our second reminiscence! Many thanks once again for your continued encouragement and interest.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;First, an administrative matter: it was brought to our attention that because of a default setting of the new Google Groups, many of you may have inadvertently signed up with a &amp;lsquo;No Email&amp;rsquo; option and haven&amp;rsquo;t been aware of any activity at all! To rectify this, we have set all &amp;lsquo;No Email&amp;rsquo; memberships to &amp;lsquo;Email&amp;rsquo; memberships. If you had deliberately selected and wish to continue with the &amp;lsquo;No email&amp;rsquo; option,our sincere apologies &amp;ndash;please let us know and we&amp;rsquo;ll switch you back. You can of course change your preferences any time on the Google Groups site:&lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/group/sadaswada&#34;&gt;https://groups.google.com/group/sadaswada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ms Sudha Raghuraman,Dr. P. Narayanan and Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh correctly identified the phrase &amp;ldquo;X Y Z&amp;rdquo; in edition #5. The verse in question was,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-11-21__9</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-21__9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-21__9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-11-21, 21:01:27 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/eGwY0dFfzq8&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;कैलसे नवनीतति, क्षितितले प्राग्जग्धमृल्लोष्टति, क्षीरोदे निपीतदुग्धति&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(kailase navanītati, kṣititale prāgjagdhamṛlloṣṭati, kṣīrode nipītadugdhati)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;Just as Mount Kailasa became a lump of butter&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;As the Earth became a mouthful of mud&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;As the Milk Ocean became a gulp of milk&amp;rdquo;. Actually, these are all in the 7th (locative) case, so they read as &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;In&lt;/em&gt;the Kailasa [which was] becoming butter&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; this is the famed Sati Saptamī construction, one of the most distinctive idiomatic constructions of Sanskrit, where &amp;ldquo;In X&amp;rdquo; is read as &amp;ldquo;When X had happened&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Just as X happened&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-11-27__10</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-27__10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-11-27__10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-11-27, 20:19:19 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/l7v50dwL5jQ&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;मनोजिघ्रः सपत्नीजनः, श्वश्रूःइङ्गितदैवता, नयनयोः ईहालिहःयातरः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(mano-jighraḥsapatnī-janaḥ, śvaśrūḥ iṅgita-daivatā, nayanayoḥ īhā-lihaḥyātaraḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;[My] co-wives [are] mind-smellers&amp;rdquo; (i.e so sensitive that they can&lt;em&gt;smell&lt;/em&gt;thoughts), &amp;ldquo;[My] mother-in-law [is] intent-worshiping&amp;rdquo; (she is&lt;em&gt;devoted&lt;/em&gt;to finding intent), and &amp;ldquo;[Our] guests lick in desires with just their eyes&amp;rdquo; (So thorough at identifying desires that they almost seem to lick them in with just their eyes), all meaning &amp;ldquo;They are keenly observant&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-12-05__11</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-05__11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-05__11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-12-05, 20:53:27 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/6NTWhoHZhVM&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सापराधतया मयापि न वारिताऽतिभयेन&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(sāparādhatayā mayāpi na vāritā&amp;rsquo;tibhayena)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;By my guilt, [she wasn&amp;rsquo;t] stopped by me by fear&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; i.e., &amp;ldquo;I didn&amp;rsquo;t even stop her, out of guilt and fear&amp;rdquo;. By a deft use of the tṛtīyā (instrumental) case, the poet makes a statement using mainly adjectival nouns, giving it both a dense, descriptive flair and a natural rhyme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To place today&amp;rsquo;s phrase in context, we&amp;rsquo;ll follow a somewhat circuitous route. The reader would surely have encountered a &amp;ldquo;map of connections&amp;rdquo; like the one below:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;style=&amp;ldquo;text-align:left;font-family:arial,sans-serif;font-size:13px&amp;rdquo;&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://ci4.googleusercontent.com/proxy/Kf2LFfrhUL7u52aqXYe02wj-SJKx0YDKO7OSNjSmn2fk7JbInuPc4OjVykDwRE_su1YQiADpA9QsgJ-QIzufqI-1H-Jw8M87YMNGSUXym915aMysDqxDLmbez2NnXgzbToq3xoa1U7TZFO2iUrcfaMwQvhhH2DVlgnKHYep8qKkASVIEC3-56Vxb2jSou-L4TdE4gqMdzA6ZV_Gm4aIrdQ=s0-d-e1-ft#https://mail.google.com/mail/u/0/?ui=2&amp;amp;ik=a50ebdf342&amp;amp;view=att&amp;amp;th=13b674d6eb737826&amp;amp;attid=0.1&amp;amp;disp=emb&amp;amp;realattid=ii_13b5ddab54081362&amp;amp;zw&amp;amp;atsh=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://ci4.googleusercontent.com/proxy/Kf2LFfrhUL7u52aqXYe02wj-SJKx0YDKO7OSNjSmn2fk7JbInuPc4OjVykDwRE_su1YQiADpA9QsgJ-QIzufqI-1H-Jw8M87YMNGSUXym915aMysDqxDLmbez2NnXgzbToq3xoa1U7TZFO2iUrcfaMwQvhhH2DVlgnKHYep8qKkASVIEC3-56Vxb2jSou-L4TdE4gqMdzA6ZV_Gm4aIrdQ=s0-d-e1-ft#https://mail.google.com/mail/u/0/?ui=2&amp;amp;ik=a50ebdf342&amp;amp;view=att&amp;amp;th=13b674d6eb737826&amp;amp;attid=0.1&amp;amp;disp=emb&amp;amp;realattid=ii_13b5ddab54081362&amp;amp;zw&amp;amp;atsh=1&#34; alt=&#34;Inline image 1&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Now imagine we drew a &amp;ldquo;map of inspirations&amp;rdquo; for the world of Indian arts. Each point would be a great artist, and lines going out of the point would mean causing inspiration while lines going in would mean receiving inspiration. Someone like Kalidasa would be the center of a dense network, but mostly within the realm of literature. While he is perhaps Sanskrit&amp;rsquo;s greatest poet, his influence is relatively little outside of literature. Someone like Bana would have a dense &amp;ldquo;incoming&amp;rdquo; network from every imaginable field of art &amp;ndash; his alankaras alone are enough to index several facets of classical art forms of his time, but his active &amp;lsquo;outgoing&amp;rsquo; influence is again quite within literature.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;If we did indeed draw such a map, one poet-point would be resplendent above all others, having actively influenced, sometimes even&lt;em&gt;shaped&lt;/em&gt;myriad art forms ranging from music to dance to painting to sculpture. A modern chronicler would unfailingly see in his work the first &amp;lsquo;viral hit&amp;rsquo; of the subcontinent, unleashing the creativity of readers with scant regard to the constraints of time and space. This ever-shining beacon of Sanskrit literature is Jayadeva, and his medium was the Gita Govinda.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Jayadeva was a poet of the 12th century, hailing from today&amp;rsquo;s Orissa. His Gita Govinda is a work of Sanskrit love poetry and song, centered around its most famous components, 24 Ashtapadis (songs with 8 couplets). These Ashtapadis are about different moods in the love between Krishna and Radha &amp;ndash; some are almost hymns, listing Krishna&amp;rsquo;s achievements in this and earlier births; some are glimpses into Krishna&amp;rsquo;s or Radha&amp;rsquo;s minds at times of separation, anger or reconciliation; some others are the words of messengers sent to each other, urging mercy and to swallow pride. There is a nod to the concept of &amp;lsquo;Ashta-nayika&amp;rsquo;, an idea from Bharata&amp;rsquo;s Natyashastra about 8 situations a heroine in love finds herself in. There is, naturally, a spiritual interpretation to all this, with Radha as the jivatma and Krishna as the paramatma, adding a wholly new dimension to Krishna sporting with several gopis.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;These Ashtapadis are not particularly distinguished for their&lt;em&gt;literary&lt;/em&gt;qualities &amp;ndash; the samāsas, sentence structure and figures of speech are all quite common, sometimes even ordinary. But a very alluring mixture of context, melody, simplicity, and really, a certain&lt;em&gt;je ne sais quoi&lt;/em&gt;have made them Sanskrit literature&amp;rsquo;s greatest cross-platform blockbuster hit. From the easternmost corner of Manipur and Assam, where it spawned a tradition of dance and singing; to Bengal, where this was an essential element of Sri Chaitanya&amp;rsquo;s movement; down to Orissa, where even today virtually every art form from Odissi dance to music to temple sculpture revolves around it; to Andhra, where it is the soul of several Kuchipudi dance compositions; down to Tamil Nadu, where Carnatic music rejoices in newer and newer tunings of its lyrics, tens of Sanskrit treatises elaborate on how it can be performed in dance, Tanjore paintings celebrate its scenes, and temple traditions make Bhajans out of it; to Kerala, where the dance form Mohiniattam derived great inspiration, and an entire genre of music, Sopana Sangeetham, was born as these Ashtapadis were sung on the temple stairs; up to the coast of Karnataka, where it inspires Yakshagana dances to this day; up to Maharashtra and Gujarat, where it was a key nucleator of the Krishna-Bhakti traditions; to Rajasthan, the central territories and the Gangetic plain, all the way up to Kashmir where several hundred derivative works have appeared in Sanskrit, Prakrit, and local languages. To even comprehend the Gita Govinda&amp;rsquo;s reach would require some level of mastery of every facet of Indian art! What&amp;rsquo;s more, a large portion of this conquest happened within just a century after its composition. Political and geographical fragmentation seems to have been a trivial barrier for this cultural unity to envelop the whole of the subcontinent!&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Today&amp;rsquo;s phrase is from the 7th Ashtapadi, often titled &amp;ldquo;Mamiyam Chalita&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Hari Hari&amp;rdquo;. It reads almost like a diary entry of a very disturbed Krishna. Radha saw him playing with a whole group of gopis, and stormed away in anger. He was too afraid to stop her then, and now he&amp;rsquo;s worried what she&amp;rsquo;ll do. A pensive Krishna thinks to himself:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;मामियं चलिता विलोक्य वृतं वधू-निचयेन ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;सापराधतया मयापि न वारिताऽतिभयेन ॥&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;mām iyaṃ calitā vilokya vṛtaṃ vadhū-nicayena |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;sāparādhatayā mayāpi na vāritā&amp;rsquo;tibhayena ||&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-12-11__12</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-11__12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-11__12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-12-11, 18:46:25 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/I86F_6F2uIo&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;हिक्काकुलः शिशुरसौ स्मरणे ममास्तु&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(hikkākulaḥ śiśur asau smaraṇe mamāstu)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;Let this hiccuping infant stay in my thoughts&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; there&amp;rsquo;s something of a self-perpetuating loop here, because a poetic myth prevalent virtually everywhere in India says that you gets hiccups whenever someone thinks of you!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In today&amp;rsquo;s tombolo edition, where we move on from our Krishna-kavya run while hoping to retain it in our minds, we feature a verse from Dr. Shridhar Bhaskar Warnekar&amp;rsquo;s short workVātsalya-rasāyanam (&amp;ldquo;The elixir of parental love&amp;rdquo;). The work is a Śataka on Krishna&amp;rsquo;s childhood, where the idea of an all-knowing supreme being in the form of a child is explored. Dr.Warnekarwas a modern Sanskrit poet, born in the village of Warne in Satara, Maharashtra in 1918. In a rebellion against the British education system of the time, his father sent him to a traditional Sanskrit teacher whomouldedthe young Shridhar&amp;rsquo;s poetic instincts. One of his important works is the much acclaimedŚrī-śiva-rājyodayam, a mahakavya on Shivaji. More details are available on a website maintained by his grandchildren &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/a/warnekar.net/warnekar-s-network/pradnyabharati&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In today&amp;rsquo;s verse, the poet paints a picture, and devises a clever ploy to keep the picture evergreen both in the poet&amp;rsquo;s world and ours:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;राधादिगोपवनिताभिरसंख्यवारम्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;स्वप्नेशु जागरसुषुप्तिषु चिन्त्यमानः ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;वात्सल्यतः प्रणयतो दृढभक्तितश्च&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;हिक्काकुलः शिशुरसौ स्मरणे ममास्तु ॥&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rādhādi-gopa-vanitābhir asaṃkhya-vāram&lt;br&gt;&#xA;svapneśu jāgara-suṣuptiṣu cintyamānaḥ |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vātsalyataḥ praṇayato dṛḍha-bhaktitaśca&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;hikkākulaḥ śiśurasau smaraṇe mamāstu ||&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(Vasantatilaka metre, 14 syllables per line)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Whom Radha and other gopis, over and over again&lt;br&gt;&#xA;remember in their dreams, active thoughts, and even in their deepest slumbers,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;with affection, love or devotion:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;May that hiccuping infant stay in my thoughts&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poor infant is hiccuping presumably because he&amp;rsquo;s so constantly being remembered. The poet joins in, and sets up a perpetual loop :-)The last line is completely unexpected &amp;ndash; if the thing to remember there was &amp;lsquo;That Lord&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;That Krishna&amp;rsquo;, or even &amp;lsquo;That infant&amp;rsquo;, it&amp;rsquo;d have been a dull &lt;em&gt;stava&lt;/em&gt;, getting all of its (meagre) strength from a reference to the Vedantic triad of &amp;lsquo;jāgrat-svapna-suṣupti&amp;rsquo; states. But &amp;rsquo;that &lt;em&gt;hiccuping&lt;/em&gt; infant&amp;rsquo; supersedes all Vedantic ideas in the poem, just as he is reputed to do so elsewhere :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-12-19__13</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-19__13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-19__13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-12-19, 21:42:03 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/qUbBYNXXCP8&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पूर्वसुकृतासंगेन निःसंगया भक्त्या कार्यधुरं वहन्ति&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(pūrva-sukṛtā-saṃgena niḥsaṃgayā bhaktyā kāryadhuraṃ vahanti)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, &amp;ldquo;(Driven) by the bonds of good deeds done to them in the past, they bear the yoke of duty with selfless devotion&amp;rdquo;. The bonds of gratefulness are strong, while those of selfishness are absent. The conciseness of Sanskrit shines through!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s phrase is taken from the play Mudrārākṣasa written byViśākhadatta. The play is set around time of Alexander&amp;rsquo;s invasion, and is full of plot-twists, spy games and an intense interplay of a bunch of very smart characters. As is usual with Sanskrit authors, little is known ofViśākhadatta except that he lived a little after the golden age of the Guptas, and that he was a &amp;lsquo;man of the world&amp;rsquo;, probably an administrator, before writing this play.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The central plot revolves around Cāṇakya, the brilliant minister (formerly teacher at Takṣaśila), who has just established 20-year-old Candragupta Maurya as the emperor of an India united for the first time in recorded history, and Rākṣasa, the equally brilliant minister of the now-completely-vanquished Nanda dynasty.Rākṣasa is on the run after his master&amp;rsquo;s fall, but loyalty being his only motivation to live, he has sworn to depose and kill Candragupta. In the character ofCāṇakya however,the playwright makes a brilliant choice that elevates every character and the entire play to a wholly new realm:Cāṇakya doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to eliminateRākṣasa &amp;ndash; he wants to &lt;em&gt;win him over&lt;/em&gt;. He knowsRākṣasa is the most intelligent, loyal and capable minister in the land, and would be an invaluable asset in the court ofCandragupta. What&amp;rsquo;s more, Cāṇakya deeply respectsRākṣasa&amp;rsquo;s abilities, and genuinely admires him as a person. This creates a natural, beautiful tension in the plot, andViśākhadatta&amp;rsquo;s genius has been in fulfilling this tension to the satisfaction of readers of fifteen hundred years and counting.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Today&amp;rsquo;s phrase appears in the 14th verse of the first act, and succinctly capturesCāṇakya&amp;rsquo;s admiration of the enemy as he thinks to himself:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ऐश्वर्यादनपेतमीश्वरमयं लोकोऽर्थतः सेवते&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तं गच्छन्त्यनु ये विपत्तिषु पुनस्ते तत्प्रतिष्ठाशया |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;भर्तुर्ये प्रलयेऽपि &lt;strong&gt;पूर्वसुकृतासंगेन निःसंगया&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;भक्त्या कार्यधुरं वहन्ति&lt;/strong&gt; बहवस्ते दुर्लभास्त्वादृशाः ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;aiśvaryād anapetam īśvaram ayaṃ loko&amp;rsquo;-rthataḥ sevate&lt;br&gt;&#xA;taṃ gacchantyanu ye vipattiṣu punas te tat pratiṣṭh-āśayā |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;bhartur ye pralaye&amp;rsquo;pi &lt;strong&gt;pūrva-sukṛtā-saṃgena niḥsaṃgayā&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;bhaktyā kārya-dhuraṃ vahanti&lt;/strong&gt; bahavas te durlabhās tvādṛśāḥ ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(Śārdūlavikrīḍita metre, 19 syllables per line)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;With many motives, this world serves a man who hasn&amp;rsquo;t yet lost his mastery;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;They who remain after it&amp;rsquo;s gone stay with a hope that it&amp;rsquo;ll come back;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;But even after their master&amp;rsquo;s utter ruin,(driven) by the bonds of good deeds done to them in the past,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;they who bear the yoke of duty with selfless devotion &amp;ndash; ah, my dearRākṣasa, people like you are rare indeed!&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This relentless, faithful, devoted pursuit is really the soul of &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; ideal, andViśākhadatta captures it with a succinctness possible only in Sanskrit. For those of you who are interested, Dr. Chandraprakash Dwivedi&amp;rsquo;s very well made TV series based on the play is available with English subtitles for free on Youtube:&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/chanakya&#34;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/user/chanakya&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-12-19__Romanthaḥ - 3</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-19__romanthaH_-_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-19__romanthaH_-_3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-12-19, 03:35:50 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/IGe2Me37-qw&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear reader,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;We&amp;rsquo;ve chugged along to our third review! A warm welcome to all of you who joined in the last month. All past postings are available in the archive here:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/sadaswada&#34;&gt;https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/sadaswada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Please feel free to invite your friends to join as well.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As usual, we&amp;rsquo;ve received a lot of feedback and are very grateful for it.Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh wrote in with a alternate interpretation for the verse in edition #7. We had translated &amp;ldquo;avidita-gata-yāmā rātrireva vyaraṃsīt&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;the night &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; went by before we knew it&amp;rdquo;. However, the word &amp;rsquo;eva&amp;rsquo; also means &amp;lsquo;only&amp;rsquo;. The phrase can also be translated as &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Only&lt;/em&gt; the night went by [all the good things about it remained with us]&amp;rdquo;, giving it a permanence and connection to the moment it is spoken in the play. Many thanks for this interpretation!&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In edition #9, we had translated Yashoda&amp;rsquo;s wail, &amp;ldquo;&amp;ldquo;नष्टाऽस्मि! दृष्टः कया! धू धू वत्सक! जीव! जीव चिरम्!&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;Oh no! Whose evil eye was this! Spit it out, quickly, quickly! Oh my dear, my dear!&amp;rdquo;. There is another element to this that is hard to capture in a translation: a common way to ward off an evil eye is to spit on the ground while uttering some auspicious words. If only we had a picture of Yashodha in this moment!&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dr. R. Ganesh mentioned that one element we&amp;rsquo;d missed pointing out was that the same verse had the very scholarly use of &lt;em&gt;pratyaya&lt;/em&gt;s like &amp;rsquo;navanītat&amp;rsquo; as well as meaningless sounds like &amp;lsquo;dhū dhū&amp;rsquo;. Again, the priorities of a mother are highlighted!&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In edition #10, we had translated &amp;lsquo;yātaraḥ&amp;rsquo; as &amp;lsquo;guests&amp;rsquo;. The word literally means &amp;ldquo;husband&amp;rsquo;s brothers&amp;rsquo; wives&amp;rdquo;, and in a joint family they were very likely all living under the same roof. The poor gopi now also has to contend with a whole world of domestic politics arising from this. Don&amp;rsquo;t blame us, we tried :-)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In edition #11, in the thought for the day we had discussed a verse connected with Bāṇabhattathat had a stiff, plain upper half and a melodious, intricate lower half. We have received intelligence, as if from the angry descendants of Bhushanabhatta&amp;rsquo;s estranged elder brother, that there&amp;rsquo;s more to the story :-) An alternative version of the same verse is below:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;शुष्को वृक्षस्तिष्ठत्यग्रे | तस्मिंस्तिष्ठति कृष्णस्सर्पः ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;नीरसतरुरिह विलसति पुरतः | तस्मिन्निवसति कालभुजङ्गः ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Here, the two halves mean &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt;the same: &amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s a dry tree in front. On it sits a black snake&amp;rdquo;. The two halves differ only in style, not in content.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In edition #12, even though the thought of the day (&amp;ldquo;mā yāhīty-apamaṅgalaṃ&amp;rdquo;) is known to have been written by a Krishna-bhakta poet, the version we&amp;rsquo;ve included is actually generic &amp;ndash; there is nothing indicating that it&amp;rsquo;s Radha speaking to Krishna, except that it fits the context like a hand in a glove.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2012-12-28__14</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-28__14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2012-12-28__14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2012-12-28, 05:08:59 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/ZxtKsrwLz2Y&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;स्मर्तव्योऽस्मि कथान्तरेषु भवता &amp;ndash; स्वात्माऽपि विस्मर्यते?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(smartavyo&amp;rsquo;smi kathāntareṣu bhavatā &amp;ndash; svātmā&amp;rsquo;pi vismaryate?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Śārdūlavikrīḍita line has two dialogues embedded in it, and can be translated as &amp;ldquo;Remember me, won&amp;rsquo;t you? &amp;ndash; Can I forget my own self?&amp;rdquo;. The first half is spoken by Cārudatta bidding goodbye, and the second is the reply by Āryaka. Many distinctly idiomatic features of both the language and etiquette of the times are seen: the use of the passive voice and &amp;lsquo;bhavat&amp;rsquo; even by the nobleman doing the favor; &amp;lsquo;kathāntareṣu&amp;rsquo; is literally &amp;lsquo;in the middle of words&amp;rsquo;, but it can&amp;rsquo;t be translated to English &amp;ndash; its net effect is to reduce the intensity of the &amp;lsquo;smartavya&amp;rsquo; demand, hinting thatCārudatta doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to make even this trivial request binding; in the reply, the use &amp;lsquo;api&amp;rsquo; as a question-mark; the essence of considering his very self indebted toCārudatta for his timely help &amp;ndash; all this in 19 syllables!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-01-03__15</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-03__15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-03__15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-01-03, 17:49:07 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/m8k_e5OklE0&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तदिह सुकरतायामावयोस्तर्कितायां &amp;ndash; मयि पतति गरीयान् अम्ब ते पक्षपातः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(tadiha sukaratāyām āvayos tarkitāyāṃ &amp;ndash; mayi patati garīyān amba te pakṣapātaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a setup-punchline combination in the sati-saptami construction, meaning &amp;ldquo;When the relative ease [of my brother&amp;rsquo;s task and mine] is considered &amp;ndash; surely mother, you favor me more&amp;rdquo;. This construction is one of the most succinct ways of setting up a punch line, and the punch line itself has several idiomatic elements. It literally means, &amp;ldquo;Your partiality falls heavier on me&amp;rdquo;, where &amp;lsquo;partiality&amp;rsquo; is just the gloss of &amp;lsquo;pakṣapāta&amp;rsquo;, literally &amp;lsquo;side-fall&amp;rsquo; to which the verb patati (&amp;lsquo;falls&amp;rsquo;) fits perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-01-10__16</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-10__16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-10__16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-01-10, 22:51:21 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/tYo9Ia3R7EU&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अगूढभावापि विलोकने सा न लोचने मीलयितुं विषेहे&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(agūḍha-bhāvāpi vilokane sā na locane mīlayituṃ viṣehe)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Even though her look hid no secrets, [Draupadi] couldn&amp;rsquo;t even bear to blink&amp;rdquo;. This is a classic contrast set-up, with one half of the contrast being described with an adjectival noun, and the second half with a normal verb. &amp;ldquo;vilokane agūḍha-bhāvā&amp;rdquo; is literally &amp;ldquo;[She whose] look hid no emotion&amp;rdquo;. The emotion was unrestrained in expression, but the &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt; feeling it was so restrained that &amp;rsquo;locane api na mīlayituṃ viṣehe&amp;rsquo; (&amp;ldquo;couldn&amp;rsquo;t even bear to blink&amp;rdquo;). Why? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-01-18__Romanthaḥ - 4</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-18__romanthaH_-_4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-18__romanthaH_-_4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-01-18, 21:23:07 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/Vz0yjciOF5Q&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear reader,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Welcome to our fourth review! As always, we&amp;rsquo;re very grateful for your continued patronage and feedback. The eagle-eyedŚatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh noticed an error in edition #16, the one on Kirātārjunīya, where we had written that the Pandavas were exiled for 14 years; the Pandavas exile was actually for 12 years, it was Rama who was exiled for 14.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Also in the &amp;lsquo;Thought for the day&amp;rsquo; in the same edition, we&amp;rsquo;d written &amp;ldquo;śvaśura-gṛha-nivāsaṃ&amp;rdquo;.nivāsa (house) is masculine, not neuter; it ought to read &amp;ldquo;śvaśura-gṛha-nivāsaḥ&amp;rdquo;. Our sincere thanks to Dr. Ganesh for lavishing on our humble enterprise such keen attention!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-01-19__17</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-19__17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-19__17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-01-19, 21:45:09 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/NdRTtE0HEUM&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;गन्तव्यमस्ति कियदित्यसकृत्ब्रुवाणा रामाश्रुणःकृतवती प्रथमावतारम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(&amp;ldquo;gantavyam asti kiyad?&amp;rdquo; ity-asakṛt bruvāṇā rāmāśruṇaḥ kṛtavatī prathamāvatāram)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;lsquo;How much farther?&amp;rsquo; &amp;ndash; asking thus again and again, she [Sītā] caused Rāma to weep for the first time.&amp;quot; In the first half &amp;lsquo;she&amp;rsquo; is actually &amp;lsquo;she who was speaking thus&amp;rsquo;, which compresses an entire sentence into one participle; in the second, &amp;lsquo;causeRāma to weep&amp;rsquo; is literally &amp;lsquo;caused the descent ofRāma&amp;rsquo;s tears for the first time&amp;rsquo;. This gives a lot of hints: presumably, they were already welling up andRāma was holding them back for some reason; or perhaps whatSītāsaid touched a part ofRāma&amp;rsquo;s mind and he couldn&amp;rsquo;t hold back his emotions. How? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-01-25__18</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-25__18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-25__18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-01-25, 21:56:28 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/SWFPAAQucpM&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;धन्या सा स्त्री यां तथा वेत्ति भर्ता /भर्तृस्नेहात् सा हि दग्धाऽप्यदग्धा&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(dhanyā sā strī yāṃ tathā vetti bhartā /bhartṛ-snehāt sā hi dagdhā&amp;rsquo;pyadagdhā)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A lady whose husband knows her so well is indeed fortunate &amp;ndash; because of his love, she lives on even though she&amp;rsquo;s passed&amp;rdquo;. While writing verses with long compounds is a challenge, it&amp;rsquo;s as hard to write verses with short words. No word above is longer than 2 syllables! Also, apun can operate in the second part, because &amp;lsquo;sneha&amp;rsquo; both means &amp;rsquo;love&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;balm&amp;rsquo;. &amp;lsquo;dagdhā&amp;rsquo; literally means &amp;lsquo;burnt&amp;rsquo;, which has a connotation in the context.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-01-30__19</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-30__19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-01-30__19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-01-30, 07:27:54 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/Hw1uDGfmufs&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;श्री-निर्मिति-प्राप्त-घुण-क्षतैक- / -वर्णोपमा-वाच्यम् अलं ममार्ज&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(śrī-nirmiti-prāpta-ghuṇa-kṣataika- / -varṇopamā-vācyam alaṃ mamārja)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;[Brahma] washed himself clean of the allegation that his creation ofŚrī (Lakṣmī) was a fluke.&amp;rdquo; The original carries very many more reverberations: first, what we&amp;rsquo;ve glossed as &amp;lsquo;fluke&amp;rsquo; is actually &amp;lsquo;ghuṇa-kṣataika-varṇa&amp;rsquo;, a famousnyāya (aphorism) that talks of a particular form of coincidence. &amp;lsquo;ghuṇa&amp;rsquo; means termite, &amp;lsquo;kṣata&amp;rsquo; cut, and &amp;lsquo;varṇa&amp;rsquo; letter. When termites eat into wood, sometimes their cuts appear to be forming a letter of the alphabet. The termites have no clue of this, of course. &amp;lsquo;Ghuṇa-kṣataika-varṇa nyāya&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;ghuṇākṣara nyāya&amp;rsquo; warns us against attributing intent to just random chance. By using just 1 samāsa, the poet makes us imagine that when Lakṣmī was born, people were so amazed by her beauty that they couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe that Brahma could actually create something somarvelous, and so agreed to call it a lucky fluke. At last, he&amp;rsquo;s cleansed himself of this ignominy. How? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-02-18__21</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-02-18__21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-02-18__21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-02-18, 01:57:22 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/hwF4RxCDi9A&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;दीपे प्रज्वलिते प्रणश्यति तमः किं दीपमात्रं तमः ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(dīpe prajvalite praṇaśyati tamaḥ kiṃ dīpamātraṃ tamaḥ ?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Darkness is destroyed by a lit lamp &amp;ndash; isn&amp;rsquo;t all darkness then just a matter of one lamp?&amp;rdquo;. The first half uses the sati saptami construction, which gives a meaning of either &amp;ldquo;When a lamp is lit, [darkness is destroyed]&amp;rdquo;, or a more urgent &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Just&lt;/em&gt; as a lamp is lit&amp;rdquo;. The second half involves an difficult-to-translate use of &amp;lsquo;mātra&amp;rsquo;.&amp;lsquo;mātra&amp;rsquo; is a generic word with many meanings in context. Commonly, it gives a sense of &amp;lsquo;only&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;after all&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo;the same measure as&amp;rsquo;. Here, &amp;lsquo;dīpamātra&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;just a matter of one lamp&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo;entirely measurable/manageable by one lamp&amp;rsquo;. In totality, the line gives a David-vs-Goliath sense, of a tiny lamp being enough to destroy mighty all-enveloping darkness. Whence does this arise, and who is saying these brave words? Or, in the style of today&amp;rsquo;s feature,कथम् एतत्? (katham etat?)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-02-24__22</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-02-24__22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-02-24__22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-02-24, 04:30:39 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/SXE6j1aWUG8&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;भव्यानां भवशान्तिचिन्तनफला भूत्यै भवत्येव धीः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(bhavyānāṃ bhava-śānti-cintana-phalā bhūtyai bhavaty-eva dhīḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;For the good, wisdom arises from thinking about how to ease life&amp;rsquo;s problems, and leads to prosperity&amp;rdquo;. All the lead words are derived from the root bhū, &amp;rsquo;to exist&amp;rsquo;, and it is surprising how vast a range of meanings they have acquired: &amp;lsquo;bhavya&amp;rsquo; is a good/great person or thing, &amp;lsquo;bhava&amp;rsquo; is life or existence (usually focusing on its problems), &amp;lsquo;bhūti&amp;rsquo; is prosperity. Aside from alliteration, this line is remarkable in how it describes dhī, wisdom/intelligence: as being born of trying to improve the world. Where does this incredibly progressive line of thinking come from?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-03-04__23</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-04__23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-04__23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-03-04, 19:57:05 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/QR8vXVPqUco&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;लब्ध्वापि कामधेनुं ते लाङ्गले विनियुञ्जते&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(labdhvāpi kāmadhenuṃ te lāṅgale viniyuñjate)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Having gotten Kāmadhenu itself, they yoke it to a plow!&amp;rdquo;. TheKāmadhenu is of course the celestial wish-giving cow. It would be the heights of stupidity, short-sightedness and total lack of any sense of value to yoke that divine being to till a field! You could ask it for a decade&amp;rsquo;s harvest and you&amp;rsquo;d have it in an instant! Who could be so idiotic? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-03-12__24</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-12__24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-12__24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-03-12, 00:44:00 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/uC9G5o1Ldsk&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;आश्वासयेत् क इव कोसल-वासिनस्तान् सीतेव चेत् त्वमपि साहसवृत्तिरासीः ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(āśvāsayet ka iva kosala-vāsinas tān sīteva cet tvamapi sāhasavṛttir āsīḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Who would have consoled the residents of Kosala, if you too had been as obstinate as Sītā?&amp;rdquo; The meaning flows so simply that one almost forgets that the line is in metre! Who is this, being praised for being more accommodating thanSītā herself? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s phrase is taken from the Pādukā-sahasra of Vedānta Deśika.Vedānta Deśikawas a great Śrīvaiṣṇava ācārya in the line of Rāmānuja, and lived about 700 years ago in Tamil Nadu. He was a poet, philosopher and teacher, and wrote tens of works in both Sanskrit and Tamil. He was an incredibly gifted scholar &amp;ndash; by his late teens he had mastered several śāstras, had been awarded the title of &amp;lsquo;kavi-tārkika-kesari&amp;rsquo;and by age 27 was already hailed as an ācārya, one of the highest grades in the teaching line &amp;ndash; and yet was known for his humility and grace. He was one of the foremost of southern Bhakti poets, and many of his works are popular to this day.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ThePādukā-sahasra is a great example of his poetic prowess. In this devotional poem,Vedānta Deśika has composed 1008 verses on the subject of Lord Ranganātha&amp;rsquo;s pādukas (a type of footwear). Just consider that for a moment &amp;ndash; if a verse is approximately 20 words, how many of us could even write a 20,000 word essay in &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; language on &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; topic and remain coherent, not to mention the constraints of metre and uniformity of style?! It is all the more amazing that the poet manages to do so about just thepādukas, and in a manner that has survived the test of centuries.He justly became famous in Tamil, by a quotation of AppayyaDīkṣita,as &amp;ldquo;oru śāṇ kaṭṭaiyil āyiram thuḷaigaḷ poṭṭa thūppul piḷḷai-epiḷḷai&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;The man from Thūppul [his birthplace] who wrote a thousand verses on a half-foot piece of wood &amp;ndash; only he is a poet&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;For sure, thePādukā-sahasra is a very different kind of poetry than the kāvya we&amp;rsquo;ve seen so far. Whilekāvya is usually meant to be read and enjoyed alone, with an all-out focus on literary merit, this work has an incredibly rich social history that upholds it more than its poetic merit does. It starts from its very origin &amp;ndash; there are many legends on howVedānta Deśika composed this. One of them goes like this: WhenVedānta Deśikawas in the temple-island of Sri-ranga, he was forced into a poetry contest by a rival group. Whoever made the highest number of verses on their chosen topic in &lt;em&gt;one night&lt;/em&gt; was to be the winner.Vedānta Deśika humbly chose the pāduka of the Lord as his subject, while the rival chose the Lord himself. In just one quarter of the night,Vedānta Deśika finished his composition of 1008 verses, whereas the competitor even after having chosen a much easier subject could barely eke out 300! Another legend goes that theŚrīvaiṣṇava community at Sri-ranga wanted a solid work of poetry to call their own, complete in every embellishment considered elite, including forms like citrakāyva. Those were times of great political turmoil and invasions, and they wanted to establish the greatness of the temple for all time in the world of literature.Vedānta Deśika obliged, and in one night made a contribution so steady that even centuries of ravages have been unable to shake it. Remember that 20,000 word essay you had to write? Add constraints of having to do it in one night and having to last several centuries, and you start to get a picture of what our poet has accomplished :-)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This automatically presents another contrast. Whilekāvya is meant to be universal, this work is quite closely tied with a specific history, location and mindset. Further, while there has raged a great debate about traditional forms vs. subject-driven forms, thePādukā-sahasra falls heavily on the side of a very ossified traditional form. For example, a modern reader will be bewildered by the nearly FOUR HUNDRED verses describing just the jewels on the pāduka &amp;ndash; to understand and appreciate this, one must have a taste for the tradition of describing specific items that developed following Bhāravi and Māgha. Throughout the poem, the predominant emotion of bhakti is so intense that one must be quite familiar and sympathetic to the social context and culture to enjoy it.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In summary, whereas the &lt;em&gt;method&lt;/em&gt; thatVedānta Deśika has applied to &amp;lsquo;solve the problem&amp;rsquo; is very clever and universal, the &lt;em&gt;actual solution&lt;/em&gt; is one that has several pre-conditions on taste in order to be enjoyed fully. Let us consider both of these as we explore a couple verses.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;First off,Vedānta Deśika&amp;rsquo;s endearing humility pervades the work. At the outset, he comments:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;मित-प्रेक्षा-लाभ-क्षण-परिणमत्-पञ्चश-पदा&lt;br&gt;&#xA;मद्-उक्तिस्त्वय्येषा महित-कवि-संरम्भ-विषये ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;न कस्येयम् हास्या हरि-चरण-धात्रि! क्षिति-तले&lt;br&gt;&#xA;मुहुर्वात्याधूते मुख-पवन-विस्फूर्जितम् इव |12|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;mita-prekṣā-lābha-kṣaṇa-pariṇamat-pañcaśa-padā&lt;br&gt;&#xA;mad-uktis tvayy eṣā mahita-kavi-saṃrambha-viṣaye |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;na kasyeyam hāsyā hari-caraṇa-dhātri! kṣiti-tale&lt;br&gt;&#xA;muhur vātyādhūte mukha-pavana-visphūrjitam iva |12|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(śikhariṇī metre, 17 syllables per line)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;With my limited intellect, my speech can perhaps muster a few words in a flash of inspiration. You are worthy of being a subject of a much greater poet! Surely I will be ridiculed, as one who tried to puff at a mighty tree that only a hurricane can move!&amp;rdquo;. Anyone who has tried to describe something of tremendous value, be it a beloved or a beloved object of worship, can empathize with the poet&amp;rsquo;s felt incapacity!&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As an aside, the tone of humility continues till the end, and even has several clever moments where any slip is requested to be corrected by the pāduka itself. For example,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;हरि-चरण-सरोजे भक्ति-भाजाम् जनानाम्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अनुकरण-विशेषैः आत्मनैवोपहास्यम् ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;परिणमय दयार्द्रा पादुके! तादृशम् माम्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;भरत-परिषद्-अन्तर्वर्तिभिः प्रेक्षणीयम् |991|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;hari-caraṇa-saroje bhakti-bhājām janānām&lt;br&gt;&#xA;anukaraṇa-viśeṣaiḥ ātmanaivopahāsyam |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pariṇamaya dayārdrā pāduke! tādṛśam mām&lt;br&gt;&#xA;bharata-pariṣad-antarvartibhiḥ prekṣaṇīyam |991|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(mālinī metre, 15 syllables per line)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Oh grace of the Lord&amp;rsquo;s feet, I have merely tried to imitate the devotion of true saints, not even to my own satisfaction. Please instill in me the sincerity worthy of the noble.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Coming back to the main narrative, after several general verses of praise, the poet introduces a very interesting twist. He praises the pādukas as the same ones that Rāma had given to Bharata to console him. This opens up an entirely new vista of literary references, and the poet does a great job of employing them. Today&amp;rsquo;s phrase appears in verse 107:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;रामे वनम् व्रजति पङ्क्ति-रथे प्रसुप्ते&lt;br&gt;&#xA;रज्यापवद-चकिते भरते तदानीम् ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;आश्वासयेत् क इव कोसल-वासिनस्तान्&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;सीतेव चेत् त्वमपि साहसवृत्तिरासीः&lt;/strong&gt; ।107।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rāme vanam vrajati paṅkti-rathe prasupte&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rajyāpavada-cakite bharate tadānīm |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;āśvāsayet ka iva kosala-vāsinas tān&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;sīteva cet tvamapi sāhasavṛttir āsīḥ&lt;/strong&gt; |107|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(vasanta-tilaka metre, 14 syllables per line)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;As Rāma was heading to the forest, as Daśaratha lay dead, as Bharata was plunged into dilemmas &amp;ndash; who would have consoled the residents of Kosala, if you too had been as obstinate as Sītā?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This is a very famous scene in the Rāmāyaṇa, pregnant with meaning. Consider the emotions of everyone involved. Rāma answers to a higher principle, and foremost in his mind is adherence to Dharma.He unhesitatingly gives up the pleasures of the kingdom, as he is most concerned with keeping his father&amp;rsquo;s promises.He certainly is aware of the people&amp;rsquo;s grief at his leaving, but he wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be the puruṣottama that we know him to be if he was swayed just by public opinion. However, even if he doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to rule himself, it is his dharma to ensure that the kingdom is ruled well. How does he reconcile these conflicting duties?&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Daśaratha has died of grief, after committing a great injustice to Rāma, all to keep a promise he had made in extraordinary circumstances. How many of us toil away like this, trying to please people we don&amp;rsquo;t even like, all because of an imagined constraint or indecision? Reminds us of an old Will Rogers&amp;rsquo; line, &amp;ldquo;Too many people spend money they haven&amp;rsquo;t earned, to buy things they don&amp;rsquo;t want, to impress people they don&amp;rsquo;t like.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Bharata is a good man placed in a bad situation. He has no desire for the kingdom himself, and yet his mother has handed it to him on a platter. Should he accept? That would seem like he was just playing innocent! Should he reject it? Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t that be ungrateful, and wouldn&amp;rsquo;t that make his father&amp;rsquo;s death and mother&amp;rsquo;s life go in vain? What should he think of his mother Kaikeyi? As a loving mother who just wants the best for her son, or a scheming villain who cheated the most noble, most deserving Rāma of his kingdom? Of course she is both! What should he do?&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Next we have Sītā, who at the same time acts perfectly according to her character, and surprisingly against it, by obstinately insisting on accompanying Rāma to the forest. Perfectly according to her character, because can we possibly imagine aSītā who &lt;em&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; follow Rāma no matter what his hardships are? On the other hand, imaginingSītā, the treasure-trove of endurance and good conduct, as obstinate and directly opposing Rāma&amp;rsquo;s wishes does require one to stretch one&amp;rsquo;s imagination. What was going through her mind?&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vedānta Deśika&amp;rsquo;s brilliance is in tapping into this emotional mother-lode, and suggesting that a personified Padukā-devi solved everyone&amp;rsquo;s problems by being accommodating. Firstly, Bharata could rest content that he was not forced by circumstances to play a role he would be ashamed of; he would rule under the symbolic superiority of Rāma, and would be more than happy to discharge his duties free of the taint of lusting after power. Next, Rāma could rest assured that Bharata&amp;rsquo;s humility and superior mettle were firmly established, and that someone who could achieve the delicate balance of employing power without abusing it would surely augur well for the kingdom. In Kālidasa&amp;rsquo;s words, he could be described as &amp;ldquo;असक्तः सुखम् अन्वभूत्&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;He enjoyed pleasure without being enslaved to it&amp;rdquo;). The citizens of Kosala could ease their fears about anarchy.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;All this because of a 6-inch piece of wood &amp;ndash; one almost starts wondering why one underestimated its poetic potential in the first place! :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-03-21__25</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-21__25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-21__25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-03-21, 19:48:59 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/1heScHt28TA&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;लोकस्य स्व-सुखोपलिप्त-मनसो वीक्ष्येति निःस्नेहतां&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(lokasya sva-sukhopalipta-manaso vīkṣyeti niḥsnehatāṃ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;After having seen the utter apathy of this self-interested world&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sva-sukhopalipta-manas is a beautiful contraction, meaning &amp;ldquo;One whose mind is smeared in his own pleasures&amp;rdquo;. Who saw this utter apathy, and what did he do next? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s phrase is taken from the Rājataraṅgiṇī of Paṇḍita Kalhaṇa.Kalhaṇawas a Kashmiri poet who lived about 900 years ago, and is distinguished as one of the countably few (and arguably the greatest) ancient/medieval historians writing in Sanskrit, or for that matter any Indian language. Even though he wrote at a time when Sanskrit literature was well past its peak, it is surprising that he was almost the first writer to speak about chronological, historical narration and fact-checking in sources. He writes in one of the first verses:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;श्लाघ्यः स एव गुणवान् रागद्वेष बहिष्कृता ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;भूतार्थकथने यस्य स्थेयस्येव सरस्वती ।1.7।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ślāghyaḥ sa eva guṇavān rāgadveṣa bahiṣkṛtā |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;bhūtārthakathane yasya stheyasyeva sarasvatī |1.7|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Among the chroniclers of the past, he alone deserves praise, who discarding alike favor and displeasure, writes with the impartiality of a judge&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Contrast this with the Greeks, Romans or Chinese, who had their written histories starting almost together with their literary works. Also given the fact that the prodigality and level of refinement achieved in Sanskrit literature was far ahead of them in comparable times, the lacuna seems even stranger.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;TheRājataraṅgiṇī is a treatise that describes several hundred kings of Kashmir. It covers a period of almost 3000 years, in about 8000 (mostly śloka) verses split across 8 taraṅgas or books. Till about 600 AD (which occupy the first thousand odd verses), that is about 500 years before his time, the narration is rather untrustworthy, sketchy and quite dry. After that however, it settles into a steady rhythm:Kalhaṇa describes the circumstances of a king&amp;rsquo;s rise, the people surrounding him and the conspiracies they hatch, anecdotes describing the king&amp;rsquo;s good and bad qualities, and finally the ever-troublesome act of succession.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kalhaṇa&amp;rsquo;s work might be compared to Gibbon&amp;rsquo;s masterful &lt;em&gt;Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire&lt;/em&gt;, but on several counts it comes up rather short in both form and content. However, this is only when compared whole; in short bursts,Kalhaṇa can be as trenchant and incisive as Gibbon in his observations and insights. In story after story, king after king, into the tens and hundreds, the nature of power is laid bare. Its irresistible allure; its tail-wags-the-dog relation to wealth; its countless suitors, secret and not; its rank carelessness in choosing one; and having once chosen, its fickleness in moving on to the next suitor.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;For example, in the beginning of the 6th book, we hear the story of King Yaśaskara. He became King by the end of the 5th book, around 939 CE, by a sequence of extremely fortunate events. He was not born in a royal family, and because of poverty had gone abroad for work soon after getting a good education. He happened to come back at a time when a council of Brahmaṇas were trying to appoint a new King (this too happened after a very coincidental set of events). He met them by chance, and impressed by his eloquence, they immediately crowned him King.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;He started out very well. As soon as he became King, he made this humble but firm request to them:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;राज्य-दानाभिमानेन वर्तिष्यत मदोद्धताः ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;यत्कार्यकालाद्अन्यत्र नागन्तव्यं मदन्तिकम् ।6.4।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rājya-dānābhimānena vartiṣyata madoddhatāḥ |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;yatkāryakālād anyatra nāgantavyaṃ madantikam |6.4|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;You have granted me this kingdom, and your pride will lead you to take undue advantage. Therefore, you are not to come to me unless on official business&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Sir M. Visvesvaraya, one of the true builders of modern India, whose labours a century ago were so great that they are still the foundation of the prosperity of Karnataka, and whose dedication to duty was so steadfast that decade upon decade of abject misrule has yet to nullify its effects, also is renowned for a similar act. The very first thing he did upon being appointed the Diwan of Mysore was to gather together all his relatives, and tell them that he would accept the post only if they promised never to ask for personal favours.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The King put the old laws back into implementation, and took control. His good governance started to have its effects:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अचौराभूत् तथा भूमिःयथा रात्रौ वणिक्पथाः ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अतिष्ठन् विवृतद्वारा मार्गाः चाविघ्निनिताध्वगाः ।6.7।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;acaurābhūt tathā bhūṃiḥ yathā rātrau vaṇikpathāḥ |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;atiṣṭhan vivṛtadvārā mārgāḥ cāvighninitādhvagāḥ |6.7|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;The land became so free of thieves that merchants kept their doors open at night in the markets, and the roads were made secure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Given that this was rather close to Kalhaṇa&amp;rsquo;s time, we have every reason to accept this as accurate and not an exaggeration.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A very interesting incident then comes up. A distraught man comes to the King, and tells him that he has been cheated. Twenty years previously, the man had been in a difficult financial situation and decided to seek employment in foreign lands. As his future was uncertain, he made arrangements for his wife to stay back. In order to give her a source of livelihood, he sold to a merchant his house and everything in it except for a water-well, which he gave to his wife so that she could make a living selling water in the dry months.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;He had come back now, and to his shock discovered that the merchant had forcefully acquired the water-well and driven his wife into servitude. He went to the local judges, but on examining the sale deed, they found no discrepancies and threw out his case. He came to the King as a last appeal, and threatened to kill himself if he did not get justice.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The King pacified him, and called a court himself the next morning, and spent many hours amusing all the judges and even the defendant. Slyly, he collected all their rings as if preparing for a game. He then secretly sent a servant with the defendant merchant&amp;rsquo;s ring to the merchant&amp;rsquo;s accounts-keeper, and asked for all detailed accounts of 20 years ago.Convinced by the ring that the request was from the merchant,the accounts-keeper gave it to the servant.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;सोपानकूपसहितं विक्रीतं गृहमित्यथ ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;राजा विक्रयपत्रस्थान् स्वयं वर्णान् अवाचयत् ।6.30।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sopāna-kūpa-sahitaṃ vikrītaṃ gṛhamityatha |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rājā vikrayapatrasthān svayaṃ varṇān avācayat |6.30|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;The house has been sold with the stair-well&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; the King himself had the sale deed read aloud.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The king then went through the transaction, and found that 1000 dināras had been paid for the seal, an abnormally high amount.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तस्मै मितधनार्हाय बहुमूलार्पणात् नृपः ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;रेफे सकारं वणिजा कारितं निश्चिकाय सः ।6.39।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tasmai mitadhanārhāya bahumūlārpaṇāt nṛpaḥ |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rephe sakāraṃ vaṇijā kāritaṃ niścikāya saḥ |6.39|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;For such a small transaction, such a huge fee had been paid. [It could only have been for a bribe.] Clearly, the King decided, the &amp;lsquo;ra&amp;rsquo; had been changed to a &amp;lsquo;sa&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;. sopāna-kūpa-&lt;strong&gt;ra&lt;/strong&gt;hitaṃ in the original had been changed to sopāna-kūpa-&lt;strong&gt;sa&lt;/strong&gt;hitaṃ by the merchant! Can you believe a thousand years have passed since this happened?! The King immediately gave the house back to the man, and exiled the merchant. Kalhaṇa also mentions another similar case to hold up the King&amp;rsquo;s firm justice.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;However, Kalhaṇa&amp;rsquo;s impartiality soon shows itself. In spite of such an interest in upholding justice, the king had several fatal blind spots.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;इत्थं जनं सविनयन् हास्योऽभूत् निज-दुर्नयैः।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;परस्योपदिशन्पथ्यम्अपथ्याशीव रोगहृत्।6.68।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;itthaṃ janaṃ savinayan hāsyo&amp;rsquo;bhūt nija-durnayaiḥ |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;parasyopadiśan pathyam apathyāśīva rogahṛt |6.68|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Thus while he was guiding his subjects well, he still became an object of their ridicule because of his personal foibles, like a physician prescribing a diet for others, but himself eating bad food.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The foremost of these foibles was his extreme attachment to his wife, who the whole kingdom knew was unfaithful to him. In spite of the evidence staring in his face, he refused to even let go of her, let alone punish her per the law. He developed several diseases, and made fatal mistakes in choosing a successor. A host of vultures in the form of ministers, led by one Parvagupta, were waiting on his every mistake, and capitalized on each of them. He was soon killed, and the kingdom continued as if he was never there.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;There are many parallels we can draw with the life of the greatest Roman emperor, Marcus Aurelius. Although Marcus Aurelius was a much more superior man and commanded a much more powerful empire, his fall too came with his blindness to his wife Faustina&amp;rsquo;s widely perceived missteps, and the choice of Commodus as his successor. In one generation, Rome had gone from being the pride of the earth to an empire in inexorable decline.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;s the same story with the great Krishnadevaraya of Vijayanagara and his minister Timmarasu. The king had the loyal minister, who was responsible for much of the prosperity of the empire, blinded and incapacitated because of succession problems.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Later in the 7th book, Kalhaṇa writes in great detail the story of Harṣa (different from the one described by Bana and others). This King matched the Roman emperor Elegabalus in his depravity, and if one even reads of his acts, nothing of the present day will appear shocking. A sad fact of history seems to be that the cruelest tyrants often enjoy their heydays the most. As a Woody Allen quote goes, &amp;ldquo;It seemed the world was divided into good and bad people. The good ones slept better&amp;hellip; while the bad ones seemed to enjoy the waking hours much more.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As if for some consolation, their fall is proportionally hard, and the poet makes today&amp;rsquo;s phrase&amp;rsquo;s poignant remark when Harṣa, too, died a horrid death. One can almost see through the yawning gap of a millennium that the poet was very disturbed himself when he wrote this:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तावत्यपि*अवरोधिका-परिकरे नैकापिचक्रन्द तं&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-03-30__Romanthaḥ - 6</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-30__romanthaH_-_6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-30__romanthaH_-_6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-03-30, 02:10:33 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/yBw3u03Fqvw&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear reader,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;We&amp;rsquo;re past a quarter century of posts, and up to 77 readers! Many of you have been constantly writing in with your feedback, opinions and suggestions, and we&amp;rsquo;re very grateful for that.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh, as always, is a constant source for encouragement and wrote in with a few comments: in edition #21 on the Pancatantra, he particularly highlighted the vast sweep of Vishnusharma&amp;rsquo;s references, drawing freely from books on Sangeeta Shastra, Shakuna Shastra, Vedanta, etc. Their delicious use in the mouths of all kinds of characters &amp;ndash; precise, learned and correct Sangeeta Shastra exposition by a donkey, for example &amp;ndash; suffuses a gentle humour throughout the work.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In edition #22, it was a difficult choice landing on which work to choose from Kshemendra&amp;rsquo;s prolific output. We just picked one, and will surely return to him in future editions.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;We received a lot of positive responses to #23 on Nilakantha Diksita and the puzzles, and want to express our sincere thanks for it. We will feature similar light works more often in the future.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In edition #25 on the Rajatarangini, we had mentioned that &amp;ldquo;the nature of power is laid bare&amp;rdquo;. That power has a single, unified nature is itself an insightful observation. Anthony Jay, one of the co-creators of the incredibly successful political satire Yes Minister, and a very keen observer of the political realm, recently mentioned this:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-03-31__26</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-31__26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-03-31__26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-03-31, 18:01:52 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/Tm1OPZNr9CE&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;आशा-पाश-निबद्ध-जीवविहगो वृद्धो गृहे ग्लायति&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(āśā-pāśa-nibaddha-jīvavihago vṛddho gṛhe glāyati)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;With his life-bird restrained by the cords of desire, the old man slumps at home&amp;rdquo;. The essence of life is commonly depicted as a bird in the cage of the body. We all know that every self-respectingvillainous&lt;em&gt;mantra-vadi&lt;/em&gt; would make sure to magically lock his own life-bird up in a cave on a distant island, of course :-) However, this particular bird is bound by a rather more abstract and much stronger bond, that of desire. The very word pāśa (cord) contains āśa in it, as if to remind the reader what it&amp;rsquo;s most powerfulform is. &amp;lsquo;glāyati&amp;rsquo; can mean &amp;lsquo;slumps&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;withers&amp;rsquo; &amp;ndash; a decadent state of little respect. The old man seems to be holding on for no higher reason than mere desire. What is this all about? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-04-06__27</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-06__27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-06__27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-04-06, 21:19:31 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/PnPx9gluF-4&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;स्वेच्छा-भङ्गुर-भाग्य-मेघ-तडितः शक्या न रोद्धुं श्रियः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(svecchā-bhaṅgura-bhāgya-megha-taḍitaḥ śakyā na roddhuṃ śriyaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Riches are like strokes of lightning, which originate on the rain-clouds of luck, and which bend and twist by only their own will; they cannot be controlled.&amp;rdquo; This is an incredible dense image in &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; very tightsamāsa. First, rain-clouds are themselves dynamic, short-lived and unpredictable. On them are even more dynamic, short-lived and unpredictable bursts of lightning. These bursts are bent and twisted in unimaginable ways, and at this level of detail one can only say that they have a life of their own. Riches are like these bursts of lightning, and by now the poet has set it up so well with this one word that he barely even needs to finish the sentence! Who is this wordsmith? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-04-13__28</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-13__28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-13__28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-04-13, 01:27:37 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/oNSRitSUkCw&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;गेहे किं बहुनाऽधुना गृहपतेः चौराः चरन्त्याखवः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(gehe kiṃ bahunā&amp;rsquo;dhunā gṛhapateḥ caurāḥ caranty॰ākhavaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What more is there to say? Thieving rats now rove around the master&amp;rsquo;s house.&amp;rdquo; &amp;lsquo;kiṃ bahunā&amp;rsquo; is an expression of resignation, and is frequently used to shift the focus from causes to effects. The phrase automatically brings a wistful sigh with it, and is used to great effect. So what are these rats doing, and why is the poet so dejected?Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-04-21__Romanthaḥ - 7</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-21__romanthaH_-_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-21__romanthaH_-_7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-04-21, 22:07:54 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/DCDx_oeydTs&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Many thanks for your continued support, and for writing back with feedback, opinions and suggestions. We&amp;rsquo;re very grateful for the interest shown in our humble endeavor!&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In #28, when talking about all-powerful Fate, we had referred toBhartrhari&amp;rsquo;s verse &amp;ldquo;रात्रिर्गमिष्यति भविष्यति सुप्रभातम्&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and some of you asked for details. The full verse is:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;रात्रिर्गमिष्यति भविष्यति सुप्रभातम्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;भास्वान् उदेष्यति हसिष्यति पङ्कजश्रीः।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;इत्थं विचिन्तयति कोशगते द्विरेफे&lt;br&gt;&#xA;हा हन्त हन्त नलिनीं गज उज्जहार॥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;style=&amp;ldquo;font-size:12.727272033691406px;font-family:arial,sans-serif&amp;rdquo;&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;rātrir gamiṣyati bhaviṣyati suprabhātam&lt;br&gt;&#xA;bhāsvān udeṣyati hasiṣyati paṅkajaśrīḥ|&lt;br&gt;&#xA;itthaṃ vicintayati kośa-gate dvirephe&lt;br&gt;&#xA;hā hanta hanta nalinīṃ gaja ujjahāra||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;style=&amp;ldquo;font-size:12.727272033691406px;font-family:arial,sans-serif&amp;rdquo;&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;style=&amp;ldquo;font-size:12.727272033691406px;font-family:arial,sans-serif&amp;rdquo;&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A bee is inside a lotus when nightfall happens, and the lotus flower closes. The bee is gentle, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to bore its way out. It starts thinking,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;This night will pass; a beautiful morning will dawn&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The sun will rise and the beauty of this lotus will smile again&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ndash; Just as the bee was thinking thus,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Oh! No! No! An elephant tore away everything.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The bee and its melodious plans (all in the future tense, with a sonorous repetition of -ishya) represent man&amp;rsquo;s fond dreams for the future. The elephant is all-powerful fate. In just one line (the 4th), the mood changes from one of fond expectation to a poignant tragedy. This is easily one of the most fascinating portraits-in-verse in Sanskrit!&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh commented that Bhallata had a very unique style of handling the Sanskrit idiom. The combination of incisive observation, legerdemain with ornate writing and multiple layers of suggestion place him among the all-time greats like Bana and Bharavi.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In version #27, in an aside, we had mentionedVijñāneśvara&amp;rsquo;s commentaryMitākṣara was &amp;ldquo;meant to be an academic exercise where the author explained his interpretation of the text&amp;rdquo;. Naturally, when talking of completely different eras, the connotations of a phrase like &amp;lsquo;academic exercise&amp;rsquo; become crucial. The tail begins to wag the dog, and hidden meanings become more important than original ones &amp;ndash; today, &amp;lsquo;academic&amp;rsquo; is often a code-word to mean &amp;lsquo;useless&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;isolated in an ivory tower&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; disconnected from the real world&amp;rsquo;; this is not true when it comes to the Mitākṣara. This commentary had a multitude of inputs from the customs and traditions of the day, and was very much linked to the reality and perceptions of its time. Many thanks to Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh for his suggestions into this.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As always, we welcome any thoughts, feedback and suggestions from you all. Please email us at&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;kvm&amp;hellip;.@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;and&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;shree&amp;hellip;@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-04-22__29</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-22__29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-22__29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-04-22, 18:19:09 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/o7hdz2oGkBU&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;प्रसादवन्तो न कृशानवन्तु परन्तु विश्वावसवन्तु सन्तः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(prasādavanto na kṛśānavantu parantu viśvāvasavantu santaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;May the good men be pleased, and not &amp;lsquo;Kṛśānu&amp;rsquo; my work; instead may they &amp;lsquo;Viśvāvasu&amp;rsquo; it&amp;rdquo;. Note the sonorous internal rhyme of &amp;lsquo;-nt&amp;rsquo; sounds. The quoted words are used as verbs, a very curious construction. It is often noted that English has a remarkable dexterity with its verbs &amp;ndash; for example, it&amp;rsquo;s barely been a few years since it became commonly known, and yet &amp;ldquo;to google&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;to facebook&amp;rdquo; seem perfectly normal. Sanskrit too has this flexibility. Here, the verbs are created from proper names. So what does &amp;lsquo;Kṛśānu&amp;rsquo;-ing or &amp;lsquo;Viśvāvasu&amp;rsquo;-ing something mean? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-04-30__30</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-30__30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-04-30__30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-04-30, 03:08:10 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/qmwr6FMnuNY&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;एको गुणः खलु निहन्ति समस्त-दोषान्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(eko guṇaḥ khalu nihanti samasta-doṣān)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;One good quality makes up for every fault&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; to write such simple, intelligible lines in verse is extremely hard! This has all the best qualities of a subhaṣita &amp;ndash; this line is the &amp;rsquo;take-away&amp;rsquo;, can stand independently and expresses an interesting insight. The rest of the verse presumably justifies this. How? Before you read on, try thinking of what could fit in the past 3 lines :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-05-08__31</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-05-08__31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-05-08__31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-05-08, 05:06:42 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/qPOg0GLQqO8&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तस्य दोषो महान् एको गुणान् आक्रम्य तिष्ठति !&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(tasya doṣo t guṇān ākramya tiṣṭhati !)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;## Meaning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;His one great fault clouds all his virtues!&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; the original is a very idiomatic form familiar across Indian languages, literally saying &amp;ldquo;His one great fault stamps down on all his virtues and sits!&amp;rdquo;. The &amp;ldquo;sits&amp;rdquo; is used in a sense of permanent occupation, and clearly the speaker is agitated&amp;hellip; but hold on just a minute here, this sounds like the exact opposite of the idea we were hawking last week! One good quality was supposed to cloud out all faults! What&amp;rsquo;s happening here? Are we pulling a switcheroo on you? We&amp;rsquo;ll explain it all, but just take a moment to guess who might be saying this to whom!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-05-13__32</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-05-13__32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-05-13__32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-05-13, 03:09:29 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/wuAw2Nu4LJw&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;भ्रेमुः ववल्गुः ननृतुः जजक्षुः / जगुः समुत्पुप्लुविरे निषेदुः !&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(bhremuḥ vavalguḥ nanṛtuḥ jajakṣuḥ / jaguḥ sam-ut-pupluvire niṣeduḥ!)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;[They] roamed about, [they] leaped, [they] danced, [they] laughed / [they] sang, [they] jumped together, [they] rested&amp;rdquo;. Whoa there, that&amp;rsquo;s more action in these two pādas than there is in two cantos of some mahākāvyas! What&amp;rsquo;s happening here? All words are verbs, and in the third-person plural of the past tense (liṭ lakāra). Guess for a moment who might have done all this, and read on :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-05-18__Romanthaḥ - 8</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-05-18__romanthaH_-_8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-05-18__romanthaH_-_8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-05-18, 18:22:54 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/7xktHipAEc0&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**सदास्वादरोमन्थः **&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have crossed the 100 readers mark! Thank you again for your continued support. Many of you continue to write in with your encouraging letters, and that keeps us going!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the last Romantha, when speaking about memories being rosier than reality, we had written a thought, &amp;ldquo;गतकालः सदा पुण्यो गतकालः सदा सुखः । स्मृतिः मृत-महिष्यास्तु शतातिद्रोणदोहना ॥&amp;rdquo;. Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh kindly wrote in to suggest that the second half can be made more idiomatic and stylistically similar to the first half: घटोध्नी हि मृता धेनुः या वन्ध्या बिभरे तनुं&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-05-23__33</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-05-23__33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-05-23__33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-05-23, 19:17:49 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/Ywz44fiV9p4&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;विदलिष्यति मूर्धा ते यदि जानन् न वक्ष्यसि !&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(vidaliṣyati mūrdhā te yadi jānan na vakṣyasi !)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Your head will burst into pieces if you know and yet stay silent!” &amp;ndash; note the clever use of ‘jānan’ to avoid a cumbersome if-then construction using yadi-jñātvā-api-tarhi etc. “Shortcuts” like these are a mainstay of free-flowing Sanskrit.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This line is so famous that we probably don’t even need to tell you where it’s from :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-06-01__34</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-01__34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-01__34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-06-01, 23:19:26 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/zarc5XQI4_4&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;सदास्वाद&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;परोपकारः पुण्याय, पापाय परपीडनम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(paropakāraḥ puṇyāya, pāpāya parapīḍanam)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Helping others is virtue, harming others is sin”. The use of the dative case (4th vibhakti) gives it a literal meaning closer to, “Helping others leads to virtue”. The alliteration and conciseness are deliberate &amp;ndash; as if this was some kind of grand summary or creed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Where does this surprisingly humanistic idea come from? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-06-06__35</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-06__35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-06__35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-06-06, 20:00:46 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/yzNMVEH94sM&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;नीचः श्लाघ्य-पदं प्राप्य स्वामिनं हन्तुम् इच्छति&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(nīcaḥ ślāghya-padaṃ prāpya svāminaṃ hantum icchati)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“An inferior man, after obtaining a good position, tries to destroy his benefactor”. An easy construction that demonstrates how smoothly the śloka metre blends with Sanskrit. Where does this equivalent of “biting that hand that feeds you” come from? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s phrase is taken from the Hitopadeśa of Narāyaṇa. It is hard to date Narāyaṇa precisely; the best we know is that he was a poet under the patronage of King Dhavalacandra of Bengal about 800-1000 years ago. Some other minor works are debatably attributed to him, but none so famous as the Hitopadeśa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-06-17__36</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-17__36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-17__36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-06-17, 00:37:48 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/lfRtaahnql0&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;भवन्नाम्ना कान्यक्षराणि सौभाग्यम् अवलम्बितानि ? कस्य वा देशस्य भवद्-विरहः सुजनान् बाधते ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(bhavannāmnā kānyakṣarāṇi saubhāgyam avalambitāni ? kasya vā deśasya bhavad-virahaḥ sujanān bādhate ?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Which alphabets are blessed by being part of your name? Which country is it whose good men suffer separation from you?” In other words, “What’s your name? Where are you from?” This kind of highly cultured, indirect and poetic way of speaking (some would say we’re repeating adjectives) goes very well with Sanskrit, and has none of the distant awkwardness an English translation has. So who is doing this refined talking?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-06-23__Romanthaḥ - 9</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-23__romanthaH_-_9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-23__romanthaH_-_9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-06-23, 09:07:54 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/BTTLcx_V3S8&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thank you again for your continued support. We continue to receive your encouraging letters, and that alone is the fuel that keeps us going!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In edition #36 on the Bhoja-prabandha, we had not mentioned the source of the title phrase (&amp;ldquo;Bhavannāmnā kāni&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;). Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh kindly wrote in to ask us to do so: the line is a direct quote from Kālidāsa himself, and appears in the play Abhijñāna-śākuntalaṃ, in the first act where Priyamvada inquires thus of Duśyanta. Ballāladeva has yet another brilliant aucitya to his credit, using Kālidāsa&amp;rsquo;s own inimitable words to introduce him!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-06-28__37</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-28__37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-06-28__37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-06-28, 19:48:49 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/wgPPtXiaZmg&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;कृत्याकृत्य-व्यपगत-मतिः दीन-शाखा-मृगोऽयं &amp;ndash; सन्ताड्यैनं दशन-विवृतिं पश्यतः ते फलं किं ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(kṛtyākṛtya-vyapagata-matiḥ dīna-śākhā-mṛgo&amp;rsquo;yaṃ &amp;ndash; santāḍyainaṃ daśana-vivṛtiṃ paśyataḥ te phalaṃ kiṃ ?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“This is a poor monkey, not even aware of what must and must not be done. What pleasure could you get by beating him up and making him bare his teeth?”. “kṛtyākṛtya-vyapagata-matiḥ” is a classic compound. So who is this monkey? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s phrase is taken from the Ātmārpaṇa-stuti of Appayya Dīkṣita. Appayya Dīkṣita was a southern scholar who lived about 500 years ago in Adayaplam, near today’s Aarani in Tamil Nadu. He was a sage and scholar of Advaita, and was very famous even in his own time. He was a prolific writer: he is credited with nearly a hundred works, and about half of those are easily available. The majority of his works are technical &amp;ndash; treatises on Vedānta, commentaries expounding the Advaita philosophy, and some works on literary theory (alankāra śāstra). He was very active and forceful in written debates, and has written tens of works criticizing or supporting ideas, philosophies and other works. These in turn had an active reception, in the form of stutis by devoted followers to virulent attacks by rivals, including one hilariously titled “Appayya-kapola-capeṭikā” (“A slap to Appayya’s face”) :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-07-07__38</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-07-07__38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-07-07__38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-07-07, 22:37:49 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/lfHnnvxL9qY&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;वल्गद्-गाण्डिव-मुक्त-काण्ड-वलय-ज्वालावली-ताण्डव-&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;भ्रश्यत्-खाण्डव-रुष्ट-पाण्डवम् अहो को न क्षितीशः स्मरेत् ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(valgad-gāṇḍiva-mukta-kāṇḍa-valaya-jvālāvalī-tāṇḍava-&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;bhraśyat-khāṇḍava-ruṣṭa-pāṇḍavam aho ko na kṣitīśaḥ smaret?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Which king will not think of the Pāṇḍava (Arjuna) angry at the Khāṇḍava forest, which is being destroyed by the dances (tāṇḍava) of the flames arising from the swarm of arrows dispatched by (his) springing Gāṇḍiva bow?” Phew! The breathlessness of the phrase, the ingenuity of alliterating a big ‘āṇḍava’ sound, the majesty that builds up almost along with the compound &amp;ndash; Who is the genius behind this? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-07-19__39</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-07-19__39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-07-19__39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-07-19, 06:41:05 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/nrNrh3gK_Wk&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सशपथम् अनुनीय ब्रह्मणा गोमयांभः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;परिमृजित-निजोरौ आशु संवेशितोऽस्मि&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(saśapatham anunīya brahmaṇā gomayāṃbhaḥ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;parimṛjita-nijorau āśu saṃveśito&amp;rsquo;smi)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Brahma immediately cleaned his own lap with a sacred paste, swore a hurried oath, and insisted that I sit there!” ‘saśapathaṃ’ &amp;ndash; ‘with an oath’ &amp;ndash; is a very intense form of insisting, employed only when the person being accorded hospitality is held in very high esteem. What’s more, the Creator himself is cleaning his lap with a sacred paste! How illustrious must the speaker be! Who might he be? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-07-24__40</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-07-24__40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-07-24__40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-07-24, 07:24:25 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/-0dp7HLs2hE&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;प्रशान्त-दावेव वनान्त-लक्ष्मीः, गतोपरागा गगन-स्थलीव, / कलिन्दजा मर्दित-कालियेव&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(praśānta-dāveva vanānta-lakṣmīḥ, gatoparāgā gagana-sthalīva, / kalindajā mardita-kāliyeva)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Like a forest after a blaze has subsided, like the sky after an eclipse has passed, like Yamunā after the demon-serpent Kāliya was killed&amp;hellip;” &amp;ndash; note the simplicity of style and the juxtaposition of simple images in an innovative sequence. The three similes progress from the most immediate to the most abstract: a forest fire directly causes physical pain; an eclipse is ‘higher up’ &amp;ndash; everyone can see it, and the darkness it casts has a more pervasive effect on the right order of things; the story of Kāliya is from the realm of mythology and peoples’ conception of their own culture. So what is it that’s found release at so many levels? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-08-01__Romanthaḥ - 10</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-01__romanthaH_-_10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-01__romanthaH_-_10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-08-01, 00:20:26 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/p2h9K4FlEPU&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve chugged along to our tenth reminiscence already! Thank you again for your continued support. We continue to receive your encouraging letters and feedback, and are very grateful.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In edition #37 on Appayya Dīkṣita, we had mistakenly attributed the Vairāgya-śataka (in the Thought for the day) to Appayya; the work was actually written by Appayya&amp;rsquo;s protege, NīlakaṇṭhaDīkṣita.Our thanks to Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh for pointing this out. Dr. Ganesh also told us that the hilariously named &amp;ldquo;Appayya-kapola-capeṭikā” (“A slap to Appayya’s face”) was in response to his work, &amp;ldquo;Madhva-tantra-mukha-mardana&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Crushing the face of the Madhvas&amp;rdquo;) :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-08-04__41</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-04__41/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-04__41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-08-04, 03:00:56 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/QM22PlXAHwA&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ता मज्झिमो विअ वरं / दुज्जण-सुअणेहि दोहि वि ण कज्जं&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(तन्मध्यमः एव वरं / दुर्जन-सुजनाभ्यां द्वाभ्याम् अपि न कार्यम्)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(tā majjhimo via varaṃ / dujjaṇa-suaṇehi dohi vi ṇa kajjaṃ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Someone in between is best. Neither good men nor bad men will do”. This āryā line is in Maharashtri Prakrit, and accompanied here, as is the convention when printing Prakrit lines for a Sanskrit-knowing audience, by a chāyā (“shadow”, 1:1 equivalent) in Sanskrit. Note how the Sanskrit words seem softened and slurred. As for the meaning, what’s happening here?! Average is the new good? Why? How?!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-08-14__42</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-14__42/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-14__42/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-08-14, 03:52:02 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/1tcjr7-FwBk&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;एवा मे प्राण ! मा बिभेः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(evā me prāṇa! mā bibheḥ )&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“So, my life-breath, do not fear”. This is the typical firm, concise style of a Vedic hymn, especially of a refrain. It’s evidently being spoken to oneself, or to someone one considers as close as one’s life-breath. Note the use of the prohibitive particle ‘mā’ (“don’t”) with the aorist tense (luṅ lakāra). Where is this from? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-08-24__43</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-24__43/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-24__43/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-08-24, 05:16:16 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/lK5Lf8DqjVY&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;द्वेष्टि श्वश्रूरप जाया रुणद्धि न नाथितो विन्दते मर्डितारम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(dveṣṭi śvaśrūrapa jāyā ruṇaddhi na nāthito vindate marḍitāram)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“[My] mother-in-law hates me; my wife wards me away; A troubled man finds no one to comfort him.” A number of curious grammatical features can be noticed here, but let’s leave them aside for a minute. Who is this poor chap who’s gotten into so many domestic troubles? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-08-31__44</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-31__44/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-08-31__44/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-08-31, 22:21:45 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/lczkqkXWQek&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;स्त्यानापविद्ध-घन-शोणित-शोण-पाणिः / उत्तंसयिष्यति कचांस्तव देवि भीमः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(styānāpaviddha-ghana-śoṇita-śoṇa-pāṇiḥ / uttaṃsayiṣyati kacāṃstava devi bhīmaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“His hands red from the thick coagulated blood [of Duryodhana], my dear, this Bhīma will tie your braid up again!” Why is Bhīma in such a rage? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today’s phrase is from Veṇī-samhāra (“Binding of the braid”), a play based on selected episodes of the Mahābhārata. The author, Bhaṭṭa Nārāyaṇa, lived about 1200 years ago, and was one of five Brahmins who were invited from Kannauj by the then-King of Bengal, Ādiśūra, for the performance of an important ritual. The five stayed on in Bengal, and many sources suggest that they are the origin of almost the entire Brahmin community there. Some famous families, including the Tagores, trace their lineage directly to Bhaṭṭa Nārāyaṇa himself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-09-10__Romanthaḥ - 11</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-09-10__romanthaH_-_11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-09-10__romanthaH_-_11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-09-10, 20:30:01 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/1JGZic0MkeI&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s time for our eleventh reminiscence. It appears we have a great fan of P. G. Wodehouse in our midst &amp;ndash; in episode #41, Dr. Phani Kumar noticed that the mathematician&amp;rsquo;s dedication was very similar to PGW&amp;rsquo;s dedication of &amp;ldquo;The heart of a goof&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;To my daughter Leonara without whose never-failing sympathy and encouragement this book would have been finished in half the time&amp;rdquo; :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-09-17__45</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-09-17__45/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-09-17__45/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-09-17, 21:30:48 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/O92IC-Xr-S0&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;इहास्ति नास्तीति य एष संशयः परस्य वाक्यैः न ममात्र निश्चयः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ihāsti nāstīti ya eṣa saṃśayaḥ parasya vākyaiḥ na mamātra niścayaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“My doubts about what exists and what doesn’t can’t be resolved by others’ words”. Who is this, looking to forge his own understanding and sounding very like an enlightened scientist? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today’s phrase is from the Buddha-carita. The author Aśvaghoṣa, one of the earliest of Sanskrit poets, lived about 2000 years ago, and is widely held to be the greatest of classical Sanskrit poets prior to Kālidāsa (not to be confused with epic poets of the Mahābhārata and Rāmāyaṇa, who are of course in another league altogether). He was born in modern-day Ayodhya, and spent most of his life in the Buddhist kingdoms of north India.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-09-28__46</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-09-28__46/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-09-28__46/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-09-28, 19:33:46 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/tconfPA50PU&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सनयनजलो रोमोद्भेदः सतां तम् अपोहति&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(sanayanajalo romodbhedaḥ satāṃ tam apohati )&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“The tears and goosebumps of excitement of the worthy [audience] soothes it”. It is a conventional Sanskrit belief that the audience gets goosebumps by anything emotionally intense &amp;ndash; unlike the modern sense where it’s expected only in fright.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today’s phrase is from the bhāṇa named Pāda-tāḍitaka by Śyāmilaka. A bhāṇa is a kind of comedic play with only one act and one actor playing many roles, somewhat like a stand-up comedy act. The Pāda-tāḍitaka was composed in the time of the Gupta era, about 1600 years ago. It is commonly bunched together with three other bhāṇas &amp;ndash; Padma-prābhṛtaka of Śūdraka, Dhūrta-viṭa-saṃvāda of Īśvaradatta, and Ubhayābhisārikā of Vararuci &amp;ndash; to form the Caturbḥāṇī. All four are bawdry comedies involving the business of courtesans, love intrigues and scenes from the ordinary life of Gupta-era India. As usual, we know very little about the authors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-10-06__47</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-10-06__47/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-10-06__47/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-10-06, 20:16:23 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/YK78AY-Efpc&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;दैवं वर्णय येन सोऽपि सहसा नीतः कथाशेषताम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(daivaṃ varṇaya yena so&amp;rsquo;pi sahasā nītaḥ kathā-śeṣatām)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“[Instead,] Speak of Fate, which caused even him to pass on to legend”. ‘nītaḥ kathā-śeṣatām’ literally means ‘led away to only-legend-remaining-ness’ Who is this apparently great man? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day, King Bhoja was on a tour of his southern provinces. He was passing along the coast, when he noticed a half-submerged boulder. It seemed to have something written on it. On closer inspection, he could make out this half-verse (in puṣpitāgrā metre):&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-10-17__48</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-10-17__48/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-10-17__48/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-10-17, 01:32:51 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/RdpZehtiSL4&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सन्नामिव महाकीर्तिं श्रद्धामिव विमानिताम् /&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;प्रज्ञामिव परिक्षीणाम् आशां प्रतिहतामिव&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(sannāmiva mahākīrtiṃ śraddhāmiva vimānitām /&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;prajñāmiva parikṣīṇām āśāṃ pratihatāmiva)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Like once-great fame that has decayed, like faith insulted, like intelligence withered, like hope dulled”. All words are in the dvitīyā vibhakti (accusative), meaning that this entire verse can be the X in a sentence that says, ‘He saw X’. This kind of ‘embedded description’ is one of Sanskrit’s prime features. So who is this evidently unhappy lady, being described thus? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-10-24__Romanthaḥ - 12</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-10-24__romanthaH_-_12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-10-24__romanthaH_-_12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-10-24, 00:00:12 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/B3Rf0lzep3k&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We received a rich crop of feedback for the last few editions, and we sincerely thank you for your support and encouragement. Let&amp;rsquo;s begin with a few things we missed saying in the editions themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In edition #47 (Hanumannāṭaka), we had covered a verse where Hanumān felt very shy when Rāma expressed his joyous gratefulness towards him. The verse had Hanumān thinking that he had done nothing great, that he was just a messenger, and that Rāma&amp;rsquo;s embrace was too great a prize for such a &amp;rsquo;trivial&amp;rsquo; task.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-11-04__49</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-11-04__49/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-11-04__49/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-11-04, 19:00:12 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/b5TOuZo89Mc&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पञ्चत्वं समुपागतं वचनतः ते वेद्मि रक्षोऽधम&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(pañcatvaṃ samupāgataṃ vacanataḥ te vedmi rakṣo’dhama )&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“You vile demon! Your [overly arrogant] words tell me your end is near!” It is a common belief that villains near their end display great audacity &amp;ndash; probably that very audacity causes their end. Evidently, the speaker here is quite offended by her interlocutor, and makes a reference to that belief. Quite straightforward, right? &amp;hellip;Right? :-) Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-11-12__50</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-11-12__50/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-11-12__50/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-11-12, 19:36:27 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/72tfXt-C5X8&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;रथ्या-पार्श्वे शकुनि-शकुनं वक्ति मुक्ति-प्रसक्तिम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(rathyā-pārśve śakuni-śakunaṃ vakti mukti-prasaktim)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“By the roadside, it speaks of good omens and freedom (mukti) to passers-by.” śakuni-śakuna is a kind of omen associated with birds, for example a parrot picking out a card from a stack. ‘mukti’ can refer either to ‘freedom’, as in freedom from daily troubles like angry creditors or moody spouses, or to ultimate liberation. The beautiful śabdālaṇkāra is self-evident: ‘śakuni-śakuna’ ‘vakti mukti-prasaktim’. So what’s with this bird and these unspoken aspirations? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-11-18__51</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-11-18__51/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-11-18__51/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-11-18, 06:54:57 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/xWTcW99mLmk&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;स्यान् मीन-मेष-गणना त्रिदशान्तराणाम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(syān mīna-meṣa-gaṇanā tridaśāntarāṇām)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“The other gods dilly-dally and hesitate!”. ‘dilly-dally’ in the original is the delightfully idiomatic ‘mīna-meṣa-gaṇanā’ &amp;ndash; ‘counting mīna (the astrological sign Pisces) and meṣa (Aries)’, i.e. deliberately delaying by consulting astrological charts, etc. This phrase has carried over intact to many daughter languages like Kannada and Telugu. Now why are the gods themselves consulting astrological charts?! Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-11-24__52</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-11-24__52/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-11-24__52/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-11-24, 22:15:02 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/dtWJjpPdkPQ&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अस्माभिः गजवैद्यकम् अपहाय अजवैद्यकम् अभ्यस्तम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(asmābhiḥ gajavaidyakam apahāya ajavaidyakam abhyastam)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“We had to abandon elephant-doctor-hood and take to practicing goat medicine”. Spoken in the first person plural, indicating an elevated sense of self-worth, but clearly this is a major fall in status. Who is this poor chap, and why this precipitous fall in his professional fortunes? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today’s verse is taken from the prahasana (comedic play) Laṭaka-melaka by Śankhadhara. The playwright lived about 900 years ago near Kannauj, and is famous for this single work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2013-12-09__Romanthaḥ - 13</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-12-09__romanthaH_-_13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2013-12-09__romanthaH_-_13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2013-12-09, 21:32:10 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/xicV_N0_Ys8&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We recently completed a full year’s set of articles (although it took us a little more than a year) and have reached our 13th reminiscence! The group has grown to over 150 members, almost solely by word-of-mouth. The journey appears so short in our minds &amp;ndash; we still remember wondering how to hedge our ambitious claims of having a post per week! Thank you again for your continued support. We continue to receive your encouraging letters, and that alone is the fuel that keeps us going!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-01-12__Romanthaḥ - 14</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-01-12__romanthaH_-_14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-01-12__romanthaH_-_14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-01-12, 18:52:21 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/daFuzRlzF9I&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Happy new year!! We wish the new year brings you the best of health, wealth and spirits.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We’ll resume in a couple weeks with our regular postings. Meanwhile, we finally have a unified draft copy of all Sadāsvāda editions combined, and are elated to share it with you! It is available as a publicly published Google document here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://goo.gl/c7cpSR&#34;&gt;http://goo.gl/c7cpSR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition, it is also available for download as a PDF at a website that we’re starting to build: &lt;a href=&#34;http://sadasvada.com&#34;&gt;http://sadasvada.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-01-20__53 - Mahābhārate Gṛdhra-Jambuka-Samvādaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-01-20__53_-_mahAbhArate_gRdhra-jambuka-samvAd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-01-20__53_-_mahAbhArate_gRdhra-jambuka-samvAd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-01-20, 21:29:58 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/VbDNLJ2bvI4&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;53&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अङ्केनाङ्कं च संक्रम्य रुरुदुर् भूतले तदा&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(aṅkena aṅkaṃ ca saṃkramya ruruduḥ bhūtale tadā)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Passing him from lap to lap, they cried sitting on the ground”. A very touching and distinct image — it automatically brings in a setting of mourning and bereavement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from the Mahābhārata (Śānti (12th) parva, chapter 149). The Śānti parva is full of moral stories and dialogues between the main characters in the aftermath of the great war. As if representing the turmoil in the minds of the characters after the destruction of the war, the narrative-Gaṅgā of the story is interrupted by thousands of small streams that join it from all directions. One such small stream, called the Gṛdhra-Jambuka-Samvāda (The dialogue between the Vulture and the Jackal) is the subject of this chapter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-02-02__54 - Rāmāyaṇe Uttara-kāṇḍe Hanūmad-Rāma-Samvādaḥ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-02__54_-_rAmAyaNe_uttara-kANDe_hanUmad-rAm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-02__54_-_rAmAyaNe_uttara-kANDe_hanUmad-rAm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-02-02, 00:42:20 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/2MN2b3DfgIA&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;54&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;शेषस्येहोपकाराणां भवाम ऋणिनो वयम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(śeṣasya iha upakārāṇāṃ bhavāmaḥ ṛṇino vayam)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;And for the rest [of your helpful deeds], I will [forever] remain in debt”. bhavāmaḥ is actually in plural; it is quite common to see the ‘Royal We’ in Sanskrit.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from the Uttara-kāṇda of the Vālmīki Rāmāyaṇa, in the chapter relating the farewell to the monkey army and other allies after the successful war. The Uttara-kāṇḍa has long been infamous for several elements that don’t gel with the rest of the work, and it is widely believed that it was a later addition. What is a modern reader to do when faced with the challenge of accommodating such inharmonious portions of an epic, a widely revered one at that? For sure, it has to be something with which one can make peace with oneself — after all, as Kālidāsa has Duṣyanta say in the Abhijñāna-śākuntalaṃ, सतां हि सन्देह-पदेषु वस्तुषु प्रमाणम् अन्तःकरण-प्रवृत्तयः, satāṃ hi sandeha-padeṣu vastuṣu pramāṇam antaḥkaraṇa-pravṛttayaḥ, “When the noble-minded are in doubt, the inclinations of their hearts are the authority to decide”. We think the best way is to gratefully accept what is beautiful, and cherish it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-02-08__Sadasvada 55 -- Some Śabda-citras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-08__Sadasvada_55_--_Some_shabda-chitras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-08__Sadasvada_55_--_Some_shabda-chitras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-02-08, 06:05:07 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/PqHC4tu4Af4&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;55&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;टिड्ढाणञ्द्वयसच्चुटूङसिङसोस्तिप्तस्झिसिप्थस्थमिब्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ṭiḍḍhāṇañdvayasaccuṭūṅasiṅasostiptasjhisipthasthamib)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;?&amp;amp;*!”$%^*!!! What in blazes is this! Forget the meaning, how do you even pronounce this monstrosity?! Read on to find out, but if you’ve somehow managed to not get your tongue into knots trying to say this line aloud, you’ll have seen that it is in perfect śārdūla-vikrīḍita metre :-)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It seems, gentle reader, that we’ve been going soft on you! The last two chapters featured simple, beautiful śloka verses that almost didn’t need a translation, and even before that, we’d been featuring one verse after another to highlight the simple beauty of Sanskrit. Where, we hear you ask, is the storied bombast of Sanskrit’s ornateness that has frightened away poor students for centuries? Where is that oppressive harshness of sound which has been compared to the crackling of burning reeds? Where, in short, is the paisa vasool, if one cannot stupefy and terrorize one’s audience by the sheer power of one’s stentorian (and incomprehensible) speech?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-02-15__56 - Pāṇini&#39;s Aṣṭādhyāyī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-15__56_-_pANini-s_aShTAdhyAyI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-15__56_-_pANini-s_aShTAdhyAyI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-02-15, 20:56:30 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/GzLhi40SE-c&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;56&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;इको यण् अचि&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(iko yaṇ aci)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“When ac occurs, of ik, yaṇ” — this has all the features of a sūtra: extreme brevity, full of technical terms (ac, ik, yaṇ) and conveying a lot in a little. A famous quip in Sanskrit goes, “अर्ध-मात्रा-लाघवेन पुत्रोत्सवं मन्यन्ते वैयाकरणाः” (ardha-mātrā-lāghavena putra-utsavaṃ manyante vaiyākaraṇāḥ) “Shortening a sūtra by half a syllable gives grammarians as much joy as the birth of a son!” Let’s see how happy this chapter’s sūtra would have made its author!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-02-22__Romanthaḥ - 15</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-22__romanthaH_-_15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-22__romanthaH_-_15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-02-22, 07:06:43 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/OPOpyyE6TxY&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your continued patronage and support. This is our first review of the new year, and of the new cycle of Sadāsvāda’s posts.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 53 detailed the Gṛdhra-Jambuka-Samvāda from the Mahābhārata. This passage is one of the most powerful ones we have seen in all of our reading. An acquaintance of ours, when he came to hear it the first time, was so struck that remarked, “This story I will remember for the rest of my life.” Our reactions were very similar, and we’re glad many of you wrote in to say you enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-02-28__57 - Kālidāsa&#39;s Meghadūta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-28__57_-_kAlidAsa-s_meghadUta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-02-28__57_-_kAlidAsa-s_meghadUta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-02-28, 08:56:35 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/gdNblE48JhI&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;57&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;स्वल्पी-भूते सुचरित-फले स्वर्गिणां गां गतानां /&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;शेषैः पुण्यैर् हृतम् इव दिवः कान्तिमत् खण्डम् एकम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(svalpī-bhūte sucarita-phale svargiṇāṃ gāṃ gatānāṃ /&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;śeṣaiḥ puṇyair hṛtam iva divaḥ kāntimat khaṇḍam ekam)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“When those in heaven start running low on puṇya, this is the place they choose to retire to, because it’s almost a piece of heaven itself!” Whoa! Before we get to the details of the Sanskrit and how this puṇya business works, what place is this, and who do we contact to apply for a corner site there? Read on to find out :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-04-21__58 - Bāṇa&#39;s Kādambarī - The Śukanāsopadeśa - Part 1-2 of 4</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-04-21__58_-_bANa-s_kAdambarI_-_The_shukanAsop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-04-21__58_-_bANa-s_kAdambarI_-_The_shukanAsop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-04-21, 02:15:27 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/5hUf_QQEKr0&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;58&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अद्य अपि आरूढ-मन्दर-परिवर्त-आवर्त-भ्रान्ति-जनित-संस्कारा इव परिभ्रमति ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(adya api ārūḍha-mandara-parivarta-āvarta-bhrānti-janita-saṃskārā iva paribhramati)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“She still seems to be dizzy with the feeling produced by [the churning of the ocean by] Mount Mandara, and roams around in circles.” This is a gross translation of a very complex sentence. The sentence literally is “Even today, she roams around in circles like X”. The dynamite here is the bahuvrīhī compound X,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-04-27__Sadasvada - 59 - Bāṇa&#39;s Kādambarī - The Śukanāsopadeśa - Part 3-4 of 4</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-04-27__Sadasvada_-_59_-_bANa-s_kAdambarI_-_Th/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-04-27__Sadasvada_-_59_-_bANa-s_kAdambarI_-_Th/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-04-27, 10:30:47 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/Z8XM4EnsWKs&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;59&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अति-कुटिल-कष्ट-चेष्टा-सहस्र-दारुणे राज्य-तन्त्रे&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ati-kuṭila-kaṣṭa-ceṣṭā-sahasra-dāruṇe rājya-tantre)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“In this sphere of statecraft, made terrible by the thousands of evil and deceitful impulses that pervade it, …” The sound alone can make us fall in love with the phrase, forget the compression and intricate structure!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We will continue Bāṇabhaṭṭa’s magnificent Śukanāsopadeśa that we introduced in the last chapter (Chapter 58) and complete it here. Picking up where we left off, Śukanāsa was saying:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-05-11__60 - A muktaka on selfless love</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-05-11__60_-_A_muktaka_on_selfless_love/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-05-11__60_-_A_muktaka_on_selfless_love/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-05-11, 08:09:25 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/eLy0iAdtCk8&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;60&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;आस्तां तावद् वचन-रचना-भाजनत्वं विदूरे&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(āstāṃ tāvad vacana-racanā-bhājanatvaṃ vidūre)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“[The question of my very] worthiness to [even] converse with you, let that be aside”. One of a translator’s most cherished challenges is when he feels the need to pad the translation with clarifying parentheses and footnotes. By that measure, this mandākrānta verse seems to be off to a fantastic start from the first line! ‘bhājana’ is an idiomatic word, literally meaning ‘vessel’, but taken to mean ‘recipient’, often ‘worthy recipient’ in a deferential, respectful way. (A synonym of this, ‘pātra’, which means the same thing, appears to have become much more popular in Sanskrit’s daughter languages – ‘prīti-pātra’, ‘gaurava-pātra’, etc.) The line here literally means “Set aside speaking-composing-worthiness”. The fact that it is ‘vacana-racanā’ ‘composing speech’ and not just ‘vacana’ suggests that it is not just any kind of blabber, but one in which the speaker is fully involved, the kind of conversation where all of one’s senses and mind are ultra-attentive. Adding ‘bhājanatva’ ‘worthiness of being a recipient’ to that suggests that this speech is very highly valued by the speaker. Note also the euphonic alliteration formed by vacana-racanā-bhājana- – one wonders if such micro-artistry is a by-product of the original thought, or the other way round! But after all this work, the poet dismissively says, ‘let it be!’. A free translation to English would be something like, “Those hopes of having long and witty conversations with you, set them aside;” Phew! Where is this leading to? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-05-20__Romanthaḥ - 16</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-05-20__romanthaH_-_16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-05-20__romanthaH_-_16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-05-20, 23:42:26 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/W1qSrWEEFmA&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We reached the milestone of 60 posts last week, and thank you for your continued support. There were some delays in the last few editions owing to personal exigencies, but we should be back on track.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, a blast from the past! Several chapters ago, we had featured a funny verse about a naughty mendicant:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;भिक्षो मांस-विषेवणं प्रकुरुषे?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;किं तेन मद्यम् विना!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;मद्यं चापि तव-प्रियं?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;प्रियम् अहो वेश्याङ्गनाभिः सह!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-05-24__61 - Some vibhūtis</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-05-24__61_-_Some_vibhUtis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-05-24__61_-_Some_vibhUtis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-05-24, 19:29:47 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/e18jNTkAA2s&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;61&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;नीतिर् अस्मि जिगीषताम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(nītir asmi jigīṣatām)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I am the moral conduct of ambitious men.” ‘jigīṣat’ is literally ‘those with the desire to win’, so ‘ambitious’ fits reasonably; but ‘nīti’ is a very loaded word, evoking shades of moral conduct, ethics and fairness. So who is the speaker, who identifies himself with the delicious idea of moral restraint in a setting of high ambition? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-06-06__62 - An ancient provocateur</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-06-06__62_-_An_ancient_provocateur/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-06-06__62_-_An_ancient_provocateur/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-06-06, 21:36:28 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/cjNizC3G1SQ&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;62&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथ कथम् परमेश्वरस्य निःश्रेयस-प्रद-त्वं अभिधीयते ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(atha katham paramesvarasya niḥśreyasa-prada-tvaṃ abhidhīyate ?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Now how can the ability to grant the greatest good be said to belong to Parameśvara?” Note the distinct, highly compressed construction: it is literally “Now how [Of Parameśvara] [Greatest-good-granting-ness] [is considered]?” The use of the passive voice and words ending in ‘-tva’, a suffix meaning ‘-ness’, is a hallmark of philosophical discussions in Sanskrit. It allows for great compression, and gives a certain ‘feel’, much like formal technical writing evokes a distinct feeling today. Another notable element here is the nice word ‘niḥśreyasa’ – literally ‘that which has no better’. So who is this, stirring up doubts about the Supreme Lord’s abilities?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-06-28__63 - The Śaraṇāgati-gadya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-06-28__63_-_The_sharaNAgati-gadya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-06-28__63_-_The_sharaNAgati-gadya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-06-28, 02:20:26 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/Lc_lEqA0BBo&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;63&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अवकॢप्त-समस्त-वस्तु-विहीनोऽपि, अनन्त-तद्-विरोधि-पापाक्रान्तोऽपि, अनन्त-मद्-अपचार-युक्तोऽपि, अनन्त-मदीयापचार-युक्तोऽपि,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(avakḷpta-samasta-vastu-vihīno api, ananta-tad-virodhi-pāpākrānto api, ananta-mad-apacāra-yukto api, ananta-madīyāpacāra-yukto api,)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“[&amp;hellip;] Even though you may be devoid of every right quality, even though you may be pervaded by wickedness that directly opposes those qualities, even though you may have wronged me, even though you may have wronged my people, […]” Phew! The weight of all those bulky bahuvrīhi compounds are balanced only by the puny ‘api’s (‘even though’s)! What’s going on here? Note also the sighting of the rare vowel ऌ in the wild!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-08-10__64 - Some laukika-nyāyās</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-08-10__64_-_Some_laukika-nyAyAs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-08-10__64_-_Some_laukika-nyAyAs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-08-10, 09:18:26 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/PHDXPrxmE4w&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;64&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;वधू-माष-मापन-न्याय&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(vadhū-māṣa-māpana-nyāya)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, “Daughter-in-law – dal – measuring – rule”, or “The example of the daughter-in-law measuring the dal”. It has just enough information to remind one of something, but the full story is tantalizingly hidden. What might it be?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the most remarkable features of Sanskrit is the incredible depth to which seemingly simple forms of expression have been developed. The nyāya genre is a great example.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-08-23__Romanthaḥ - 17</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-08-23__romanthaH_-_17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-08-23__romanthaH_-_17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-08-23, 04:36:46 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/Wftrh1g8TKw&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your continued support and feedback. There were again some delays in the last few editions owing to personal exigencies, and in view of that we have relaxed our posting schedule to once per fortnight. Hopefully, this should be a more sustainable pace.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In chapter 61 on the Vibhūti-yoga of the Bhagavad-gītā, we had translated ‘nīti’ in the space of ‘moral conduct, ethics and fairness’. While this has been the primary meaning in Sanskrit’s daughter languages in recent centuries, Śatāvadhāni Dr. R. Ganesh noted that the classical meaning of the word was more in the space of ‘management’, ‘leadership-quality’, ‘administration’, ‘polity’, etc. It gives a subtly different meaning, though the underlying message of sustaining gains and long-term thinking is reaffirmed. We thank Dr. Ganesh for this perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-09-06__65 - The Pāṇḍava-gītā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-09-06__65_-_The_pANDava-gItA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-09-06__65_-_The_pANDava-gItA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-09-06, 04:48:57 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/gvJYAN4y3IU&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;65&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;जानामि धर्मं न च मे प्रवृत्तिः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(jānāmi dharmaṃ na ca me pravṛttiḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I understand Dharma, but cannot get myself to apply it.” How come?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s verse is from a very difficult work called the Pāṇḍava-gīta (also called the Prapanna-gīta). It is a devotional anthology of unknown authorship, and is probably a few hundred years old. As with most Sanskrit anthologies, many of the original sources of the verses are untraceable. We label it ‘difficult’ not because of any linguistic challenge, but a poetic one: out of its 80-odd verses, barely a couple are mildly interesting, and only one solitary verse truly has poetic beauty. When starting out to read a work, one hopes to find many gems to add to one’s collection — and it is an especial feeling of exasperation to find only one. We’d discussed a similar problem in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/qmwr6FMnuNY&#34;&gt;chapter on Cāṇakya&lt;/a&gt;, where we agreed that in most such cases, ‘eko guṇaḥ khalu nihanti samasta-dośān’ ‘One good quality makes up for all the faults’!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-09-28__66 - Special: Rangavalli</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-09-28__66_-_Special_Rangavalli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-09-28__66_-_Special_Rangavalli/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-09-28, 03:46:07 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/-9B7qlQVnO8&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;66&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ದೇವನಲ್ಲ &amp;ndash; ಬರಿಯ ಬೊಂಬೆ! &amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ಹಸೆಯೆ ಸೋಜಿಗ!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(dēvanu alla &amp;ndash; bariya bombe! &amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;haseye sōjiga!)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“The Deity is but a doll — the magic is in the rangoli!”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We decided to try something special this time! Over the last few chapters, we’ve made a number of references to Kannada verses and works in our commentary (Kannada is our mother tongue). The implicit understanding was that Kannada being a daughter language of Sanskrit meant that its literature gels organically with Sanskrit’s corpus — from the level of words and sounds, to idioms and styles, even to ideals and worldviews. We thought of going one step further and featuring a beautiful Kannada poem that is perfectly resonant with our recent explorations of the Sanskrit thought-space, and yet distinct from it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-10-13__67 - Uddaṇḍa&#39;s Kokila-sandeśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-10-13__67_-_uddaNDa-s_kokila-sandesha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-10-13__67_-_uddaNDa-s_kokila-sandesha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-10-13, 03:46:25 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/KSV5L1ptwwc&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;67&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;त्वत्-सम्बद्धो मम शत-गुणः सङ्गमाद् विप्रयोगे&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(tvat-sambaddho mama śata-guṇaḥ saṅgamād viprayoge)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“But for you, [my love] has grown a hundred times in separation!”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the Kokila-sandeśa of Uddaṇḍa-śāstrī. The poet was one of the 18 gems who adorned the court of Māna-vikrama, the 81st Zamorin of Calicut, who ruled most of Kerala around 450 years ago. Uddaṇda-śāstrī was an honorific name given to the poet, who was born as Irugupanātha in a village near Kāñcī. He traveled looking for patronage, and legend has it that when he arrived at the Zamorin’s court, he recited this verse:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-10-20__68 - An ingenious system of notation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-10-20__68_-_An_ingenious_system_of_notation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-10-20__68_-_An_ingenious_system_of_notation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-10-20, 05:22:15 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/BaDT9hwrP6Y&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;68&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;शङ्कुकर्णो नगेश्वरः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(śaṅkukarṇo nageśvaraḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“The mountain-king has pointy ears.” What’s this about?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Suppose you’re ambling by a riverbank on a lazy Sunday afternoon, and stumble into a stone with an inscription:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;रासिक्य-दं रञ्जकं हरिं जीवमधुना ऽनतोऽस्मि&amp;rdquo; इति मूलम् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;लोकात् भयं मा धर, तन् मूलमिदं धी-साधनम्&amp;rdquo; इति सूची ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;स्व-वर्गस्य एकाधिके या विनश्यति सा माया ।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-10-27__Romanthaḥ - 18</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-10-27__romanthaH_-_18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-10-27__romanthaH_-_18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-10-27, 02:05:05 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/COahKrRzfqQ&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We can’t believe we’re near the end of 2014 already! Our plan is write 4 more chapters, and then take a break in December to compile this year’s chapters into the second volume of our book. Meanwhile, we were very pleasantly surprised to see that the group has grown to nearly 260 members! We haven’t quite figured out how to promote the group yet, and so this growth is solely from you spreading the word – thank you very much for that, and please do keep it going! If you have any ideas on what we could do better, we’re all ears!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-11-02__69 - Śudraka&#39;s Padma-prābhṛtaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-11-02__69_-_shudraka-s_padma-prAbhRtaka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-11-02__69_-_shudraka-s_padma-prAbhRtaka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-11-02, 09:33:42 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/isvnvf4055U&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;69&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;क्व संचिचरिषुः ? तिष्ठ तावत् । किम् असि दुद्रूषुः ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(kva saṃcicariṣuḥ ? tiṣṭha tāvat | kim asi dudrūṣuḥ ?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“To where are you desirous of perambulating? Sit for a while. Why have you become one who wishes to make haste?” &amp;ndash; In other words, “Where are you going? Sit down. Why are you in a hurry?” If the first translation sounded stilted and artificial, we’ve done our job. :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-11-09__सदास्वादः - ७० - डिकेन्स्-वर्यस्य पिक्विक् पेपर्स्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-11-09__sadAsvAdaH_-_70_-_Dikens-varyasya_pikv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-11-09__sadAsvAdaH_-_70_-_Dikens-varyasya_pikv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-11-09, 22:05:53 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/VwTeYckIhKo&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sadāsvāda&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;७०&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Both expressed their opinion that a more independent, a more enlightened, a more public-spirited, a more noble-minded, a more disinterested set of men than those who had promised to vote for him, never existed on earth.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अर्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“उभाव् अपि स्व-संकल्पौ निवेदयाम्-आसतुः यद् आत्मावल्म्बने वा, प्रबुद्धत्वे वा, लोक-कल्याण-निरतत्वे वा, उदात्त-मनःसञ्चारणे वा, स्थित-प्रज्ञत्वे वा स्व-पक्ष-जनान् लेशम् अपि अतिक्रान्तवन्तः को ऽपि त्रिभुवनेषु वेधसा ऽपि न मृग्य इति ।”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-11-27__71 - Ānanda-vardhana&#39;s Dhvanyāloka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-11-27__71_-_Ananda-vardhana-s_dhvanyAloka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-11-27__71_-_Ananda-vardhana-s_dhvanyAloka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-11-27, 21:15:47 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/IKqat7-8TSw&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;71&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;न्यक्कारो ह्ययम् एव मे यद् अरयस् ; तत्राप्य् असौ तापसः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(nyakkāro hyayam eva me yad arayas ; tatrāpy asau tāpasaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Enemies &amp;ndash; that [plural word] is itself a humiliation for me! And on top of that he’s an ascetic!” Perhaps the speaker might have reconciled with one misguided fool becoming his enemy, but enemies? More than one?! The shame! The poetic heart of this line is in that plural word ‘enemies’, which we can imagine spoken with great shock and disbelief. Likewise, we can naturally imagine ‘nyakkāra’ ‘humiliation’ and ‘tāpasa’ ‘ascetic’ spoken with great contempt. Phew, there appears to be as much work for our imagination as there has been for the line’s creator’s!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2014-12-06__72 - K. S. Arjunwadkar&#39;s Kaṇṭakāñjali</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-12-06__72_-_K._S._Arjunwadkars_kaNTakAnjali/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2014-12-06__72_-_K._S._Arjunwadkars_kaNTakAnjali/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2014-12-06, 16:13:03 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/ve9QZywNLxU&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;72&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;खादन् भेलपुरीं पुरो बलिभुजां नेष्ये ऽपराह्णान् कदा&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(khādan bhelapurīṃ puro balibhujāṃ neṣye aparāhṇān kadā)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“When will I get to spend [those] afternoons, eating Bhel-puri in front of crows?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the Kaṇṭakāñjali of Krishna Srinivas Arjunwadkar. Prof. Arjunwadkar was born in Belgaum in 1926, and had a traditional Sanskrit education starting with his father’s tutelage. Through the course of his studies, he developed proficient scholarship in his mother tongue Marathi and in Sanskrit. He went on to be a distinguished professor, exploring grammar, literature, philosophy, history and science through his copious writings. He was a champion of Sanskrit revival, and engaged with the language in multiple dimensions – writing poetry himself, building bridges between spoken Marathi and Sanskrit, rejuvenating traditions like Yoga in the public mind, and so on. He passed away in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2015-01-24__Romanthaḥ - 19</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-01-24__romanthaH_-_19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-01-24__romanthaH_-_19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2015-01-24, 01:57:38 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/oQdb-AArbvI&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We wish you a wonderful, healthy, happy new year; may the recent transition into Uttarārayaṇa make everyone’s life brighter. It has been more than a month since our last post, again because of personal exigencies. For the new year, we fervently wish we don’t have to repeat this line!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The group has grown to over 280 members, nearly double of what it was at this time last year, and we’re very grateful for your interest. Our plan is to continue with the bi-weekly posts, revisiting some works we’ve covered as well as exploring new ground.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2015-02-07__73 - Līlāśuka&#39;s Kṛṣṇa-karṇāmṛta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-02-07__73_-_lIlAshuka-s_kRShNa-karNAmRta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-02-07__73_-_lIlAshuka-s_kRShNa-karNAmRta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2015-02-07, 06:26:32 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/5JwEbKrbuvk&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;73&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अग्रे दीर्घतरो ऽयम् अर्जुन-तरुस् तस्याग्रतो वर्त्मनि&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(agre dīrghataro &amp;lsquo;yam arjuna-tarus tasyāgrato vartmani)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“[You see] this tall Arjuna tree ahead? [Follow] the road beyond that, &amp;hellip; ” &amp;ndash; sounds like we’re getting directions to someplace! Where?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the Kṛṣṇa-karṇāmṛta, a collection of devotional verses attributed to a saint Bilvamangala Svāmi (“Līlāśuka”). He lived about 700 years somewhere in South India. We had first introduced this work nearly two years ago, and wanted to begin this year by revisiting it. There is so much poetic beauty in this collection that we could write about it for the next ten chapters and still not come close to exhausting it, so our only concern here is length. :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2015-02-24__74 - Kālidāsa&#39;s Raghuvaṃśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-02-24__74_-_kAlidAsa-s_raghuvaMsha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-02-24__74_-_kAlidAsa-s_raghuvaMsha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2015-02-24, 05:08:21 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/U2KfLYqP0SA&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;74&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तद्-गुणैः कर्णम् आगत्य चापलाय प्रचोदितः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(tad-guṇaiḥ karṇam āgatya cāpalāya pracoditaḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, “By their virtues which came into my ear, I was compelled to fickleness”. The original is rich with idiomatic usage: In many Indian languages, we still often hear an equivalent of “It came into my ear” to mean “I heard”. The ‘cāpala’, ‘fickleness’, refers in a self-effacing manner to something the poet did. So a more ‘natural’ translation would be, “I happened to hear of their virtues, and cannot stay quiet!” Phew, who is this, sending us into such delicious idiomatic knots in just half a śloka, and what did he do?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2015-04-26__75 - The Yakṣa-praśna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-04-26__75_-_The_yaxa-prashna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-04-26__75_-_The_yaxa-prashna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2015-04-26, 08:14:55 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/zc5mY6ir-BA&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;75&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;कः पन्थाः?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(kaḥ panthāḥ?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Literally, “What is the Way?” In the original, as with most Indian languages, the symbolic ‘weight’ attached to the word ‘way’ is quite obvious from context; in English, we have to resort to using ‘the’ and capitalizing it. Be that as it may, who’s asking?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**&lt;br&gt;&#xA;**&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the famed Yakśa-praśnā of the Mahābhārata. It appears in the Vana-parva, at the end of the Pāṇḍavas’ 12 year exile and just as they are about to commence their 1 year of ajñāta-vāsa, living incognito.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2015-06-04__76 - Bāṇabhaṭṭa&#39;s Kādambarī -- Agastya&#39;s āshrama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-06-04__76_-_bANabhaTTa-s_kAdambarI_--_Agastya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-06-04__76_-_bANabhaTTa-s_kAdambarI_--_Agastya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2015-06-04, 07:43:41 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/wxce6oUN6L0&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;76&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;बलि-कर्म-कुसुमान्युद्धरन्त्याः सीतायाः करतलाद् इव संक्रान्तो&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यत्र रागः स्फुरति लता-किसलयेषु&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(bali-karma-kusumāni uddharantyāḥ sītāyāḥ karatalād iva saṃkrānto&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;yatra rāgaḥ sphurati latā-kisalayeṣu)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Where the tender shoots of creepers glisten with redness, transferred as if from the delicate hands of Sītā who was plucking flowers for worship”. The seeming nonchalance in placing the ‘iva’, the late arrival of ‘yatra’ which heightens the punch and the rich density of verbs even in one prose phrase &amp;ndash; you know where we’re going!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2015-07-05__Romanthaḥ - 20</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-07-05__romanthaH_-_20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-07-05__romanthaH_-_20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2015-07-05, 01:35:53 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/8mlEovuGc30&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been more than six months since our last reminiscence. Work and family commitments have slowed down our pace considerably, but we were very happy to be receiving a constant stream of feedback on our older chapters. On another happy note, the group now has over 300 subscribers!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, a blast from the past! In the chapter &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/PHDXPrxmE4w&#34;&gt;on laukika-nyāyas&lt;/a&gt; last year, we’d spoken of the ‘vṛddha-kumārī-vākya-nyāya’, ‘[The example of] the old virgin woman’. This comes from an example in the Mahābhāṣya of Patañjali. Indra appeared before a poor, old virgin woman and asked her to make one — only one — wish. She promptly asked,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2015-07-13__77 - Anger in the Amaru-śataka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-07-13__77_-_Anger_in_the_amaru-shataka/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-07-13__77_-_Anger_in_the_amaru-shataka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2015-07-13, 03:41:28 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/i-Z4VouHEPc&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;77&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;एकस्मिन् शयने पराङ्-मुखतया वीतोत्तरं ताम्यतोः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ekasmin śayane parāṅ-mukhatayā vītottaraṃ tāmyatoḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Lying on the same bed, turned away from each other, suffering in silence&amp;hellip;” Smells like some domestic trouble!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the Amaru-śataka, one the most famous collections of love-poetry in Sanskrit. We’d featured it in one of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/el3bOFvRmEY&#34;&gt;earliest chapters&lt;/a&gt;, and are picking it up from there.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, orders being obeyed can be very disheartening — for the one giving orders! A girl complains to her friend:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2015-07-27__78 - Moonrise on the southern shore</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-07-27__78_-_Moonrise_on_the_southern_shore/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2015-07-27__78_-_Moonrise_on_the_southern_shore/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2015-07-27, 04:12:18 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/YMp4JJrEZhw&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;78&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;वाहि वात यतः कन्या तां स्पृष्ट्वा माम् अपि स्पृश&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(vāhi vāta yataḥ kanyā tāṃ spṛṣṭvā mām api spṛśa)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Fly, O Wind, touch her, and touch me”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the Rāmāyaṇa, from the beginning of the Yuddha-kānda. The monkey army has just arrived at the ocean shore. Rāma has been convinced by Sugrīva and others that building a bridge across the ocean to Lankā is the way forward. One phase of Rāma’s life—the months of agony following Sītā’s abduction—is just about to end. That phase was filled with introspection and reminiscence; the phase following is full of action and choices. This scene is the last instance where Rāma longs for Sītā in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-02-28__79 - One verse</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-02-28__79_-_One_verse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-02-28__79_-_One_verse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-02-28, 20:14:11 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/-MG0pMmtxGk&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;79&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ददाम्यहं तण्डुलम् एव शुष्कम्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(dadāmi ahaṃ taṇḍulam eva śuṣkam)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“All I give back is [a morsel of] dry rice”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the Mātṛ-pañcakam, a short set of verses attributed to Ādi Śaṅkara. He is said to have written these when his mother passed away. Among them lies the single most powerful jolt we have experienced in all our poetry reading:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-04-06__80 - The story of Indradyumna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-04-06__80_-_The_story_of_Indradyumna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-04-06__80_-_The_story_of_Indradyumna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-04-06, 20:41:33 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/gNiAAuNzPoI&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;80&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;भवान् इन्द्रद्युम्नं राजानम् अभिजानाति [?]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(bhavān indradyumnaṃ rājānam abhijānāti ?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Do you remember King Indradyumna?” Well, who wants to know?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the Vana-parva of the Mahābhārata [&lt;em&gt;sarga&lt;/em&gt; 191 in the BORI critical edition, 199 in the Gorakhpur edition, and 198 in K. M. Ganguli’s translation]. In their initial days of exile in the forest, the Pāṇḍavas meet a number of sages, and Yudhiṣṭhira delights in hearing tales from them. They meet the sage Mārkaṇḍeya, who was famed to be immortal, and very old.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-04-10__81 - The upamā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-04-10__81_-_The_upamA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-04-10__81_-_The_upamA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-04-10, 01:01:55 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/4sbgFrc8Lpo&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;81&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;कपयश् चेरुर् आर्तस्य रामस्येव मनोरथाः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(kapayaḥ ceruḥ ārtasya rāmasya iva manorathāḥ)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“The monkeys searched [the forest for Sītā], like the anxious Rāma’s thoughts”. 80 chapters on, we feel comfortable in dropping any pretense of balance or restraint: this is the best upamā we have seen, in any work, in any language.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This verse appears in the 12th sarga of the Raghuvaṃśa. Each verse in this sarga is a summary of many sargas of Vālmīki’s Rāmāyaṇa — and knowing Kālidāsa, it turns out to be a virtuoso’s playful masterclass in saṃksepa. One may very reasonably think that it is impossible to say anything more after Vālmīki, especially when given just a hundredth of the space; but of course, Kālidāsa laughs at such silly notions of reasonableness, and sits a daśāṅgula apart from anything our minds could imagine. In spite of the fixedness of the content, his genius—his unique fingerprint—is manifest in nearly every other verse. After reading so much original thought, we almost begin to wonder why we ever thought the story of Rāma was told already.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-05-02__Romanthaḥ - 21</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-05-02__romanthaH_-_21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-05-02__romanthaH_-_21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-05-02, 08:55:00 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/5CaRNx3gG-s&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We just reached a milestone of 80 posts, after a long hiatus due to personal events. How much things can change between two posts, how much of life can happen! Many thanks to everyone who wrote in with their kind notes of concern and support. The group has nearly 350 subscribers now, and virtually everyone here has come from word-of-mouth. We’re grateful for your encouragement and enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-05-12__82 - Special: Puṇyakōṭi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-05-12__82_-_Special_PuNyakoTi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-05-12__82_-_Special_PuNyakoTi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-05-12, 23:15:58 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/plVgZ57TJMY&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;82&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ಧರಣಿ ಮಂಡಲ ಮಧ್ಯದೊಳಗೆ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ಮೆರೆಯುತಿಹ ಕರ್ಣಾಟ ದೇಶದಿ&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“In the Karṇāṭa kingdom, resplendent in the world, &amp;hellip;”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;— This is possibly the most famous line in the Kannada language!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s line is the opening of the Govina hāḍu, one of the most well-known songs in the Kannada language. It was written by an unknown poet sometime between the days of the Vijayanagara empire (c. 1400’s) and the renaissance in Kannada literature (c. late 1800’s). There are stories with similar content in the Padma-purāṇa and an obscure work called the Itihāsa-samuccaya, but both are rather marginal, and neither appears to have captured the public imagination anything like the Kannada version.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-05-26__83 - The Kabandha episode</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-05-26__83_-_The_Kabandha_episode/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-05-26__83_-_The_Kabandha_episode/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-05-26, 01:15:05 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/n5LkHSNQWA0&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;83&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;कालस्य सुमहद् वीर्यं सर्व-भूतेषु लक्ष्मण&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(kālasya sumahad vīryaṃ sarva-bhūteṣu lakṣmaṇa)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“[See] the power of Time over everyone, Lakṣmaṇa”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the Araṇya kāṇda of the Vālmīkī Rāmayaṇa. Sītā has been abducted. Rāma and Lakṣmaṇa, desperately searching for her, come across the dying Jaṭāyu. The poor bird only manages to tell the name ‘Rāvaṇa’, and that he was taking Sītā south &amp;ndash; nothing more. Rāmā and Lakṣmaṇa tearfully conduct the funeral rites for Jaṭāyu. Then,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-06-12__84 - Dilīpa&#39;s curse</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-06-12__84_-_dilIpa-s_curse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-06-12__84_-_dilIpa-s_curse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-06-12, 00:22:12 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/99xrCdzCj_Q&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;84&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अवजानासि मां यस्माद् अतस् ते न भविष्यति&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(avajānāsi māṃ yasmād atas te na bhaviṣyati)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Because you disrespect me, you will not have [children]”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter’s phrase is from the first sarga of Kālidāsa’s Raghuvaṃśa. We have written at length about the various facets of greatness of Kālidāsa in many previous chapters (phrase artistry &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/iRivTBtYKVY&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, genius at all levels from sound to structure &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/gdNblE48JhI&#34;&gt;57&lt;/a&gt;, tonal artistry &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/U2KfLYqP0SA&#34;&gt;74&lt;/a&gt;, genius of comparisons &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/4sbgFrc8Lpo&#34;&gt;81&lt;/a&gt;), so we’ll do something different: we’ll highlight a section that some readers may be unhappy about, and explore whether we can still find joy in it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-07-02__Romanthaḥ - 22</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-07-02__romanthaH_-_22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-07-02__romanthaH_-_22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-07-02, 21:03:48 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/2zHmLXhDjWA&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many thanks as always for your great feedback. First off, we received a number of comments on some of our old chapters, and nothing could give us more delight. We’re very grateful for all your inputs below, please keep them coming!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/e18jNTkAA2s&#34;&gt;chapter 61&lt;/a&gt; on the Gīta, we had noted how it was Arjuna who happened to need Krishna’s instruction, instead of, say, Yudhiṣṭhira, and how this was somewhat of a surprise given their characters. Dr. Arvind Iyer recalled an observation by Prof. Purushottama Lal, where he attributes this anomaly to the fact that Arjuna has had very different experiences than the rest. For example, he has traveled more and stayed away more than any other prince in the Kuru line, thereby increasing his sense of family; he is more individualistic, in the sense that he feels that he can walk away, even at the time of inspecting the enemy formation after the conches have been blown; and yet, because he is individualistic, there is a strong sense of pacifism and detachment from strong social forces around him (‘kim no rājyena, Govinda? Kim bhogair, jīvitena vā?’); he has no insecurity about his prowess, and therefore has the space to worry about morality, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-07-24__85 - Some anonymous anyoktis</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-07-24__85_-_Some_anonymous_anyoktis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-07-24__85_-_Some_anonymous_anyoktis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-07-24, 19:41:21 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/635wwFskvV4&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;85&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;परापर-परिज्ञानानभिज्ञो भवान्&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(para-apara-parijñāna-anabhijñaḥ bhavān)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“You are devoid of any sense of knowing about who is your own, and who is not”. The intricate musicality of the phrase leaps at us, but the meaning is just as intricate. para/apara has many uses in denoting distinction &amp;ndash; ‘other’/’one’s own’, ‘different’/’not different’, ‘beyond/here’ etc. parijñāna, literally ‘knowledge around’, is a special, higher kind of expertise, which isn’t directed at a thing in particular, but on it, about it and around it &amp;ndash; what its value is, where it fits, what to do with it, etc. abhijñāna is ‘skill’ or more softly, ‘recognition’. In essence, the speaker is complaining about the lack of a higher discriminatory capacity. Sound-wise, this has to be among the most intricate phrases we have featured.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-08-05__86 - Bhartṛhari&#39;s Śatakas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-08-05__86_-_bhartRhari-s_shatakas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-08-05__86_-_bhartRhari-s_shatakas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-08-05, 02:56:53 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/f0pUcf1SERk&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;86&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;व्रीडा चेत् किमु भूषणैः ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(vrīḍā cet kimu bhūṣaṇaiḥ?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“When there is shyness, what is the use of ornaments and decorations?” Very telegraphic, but the depth of poetic connection within just 8 syllables makes us do a double take. There can only be one fellow who can do this with śārdūla-vikrīḍitas&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been many chapters since we spoke of an old favorite, Bhartṛhari. We had featured one of his verses in &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/T7G1UGxOSKc&#34;&gt;chapter 3&lt;/a&gt;, and had referred to many in passing in other chapters. That is perhaps a consequence of his greatness: the few hundred verses attributed to him are so well-known in Sanskrit and many regional languages that they are inseparable parts of everyday conversations. It simply does not occur to us to seek out the author of such evergreen phrases as ‘kālāya tasmai namaḥ’, ‘vidyā paraṃ daivataṃ’, ‘vairāgyam evābhayaṃ’ ‘kaṣṭam apaṇḍitatā vidheḥ’, ‘na hi suptasya siṃhasya praviśanti mukhe mṛgāḥ’, ‘nyāyyāt patho pravicalanti padaṃ na dhīrāḥ’ &amp;ndash; the thoughts of one man have come to so perfectly represent the voice of an entire culture. We are reminded of a joke by D. F. Wallace:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-08-23__87 - Tārā&#39;s lament</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-08-23__87_-_tArA-s_lament/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-08-23__87_-_tArA-s_lament/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-08-23, 05:07:47 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/ECp0uffXV1Y&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;87&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;धन्वी कथं भवसि राघव माम् अविध्वा ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(dhanvī kathaṃ bhavasi rāghava mām avidhvā ?)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“How can you be an archer without having killed me?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from Bhoja’s Campū-rāmāyaṇa. We had introduced the author and the work &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sadaswada/m8k_e5OklE0&#34;&gt;72 chapters ago&lt;/a&gt;, with a solitary verse as an example. We can’t believe it has been three-and-a-half years since then: it feels like yesterday when we accidentally tuned in to a Kannada AIR program when an expositor was describing that event with great feeling! Perhaps this is a feature of a certain kind of poetry, which instantly sears itself into a portion of memory that is unaffected by time or circumstance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-09-14__88 - Kumāravyāsa&#39;s Karṇabheda Part 1 of 2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-09-14__88_-_kumAravyAsa-s_karNabheda_Part_1_o/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-09-14__88_-_kumAravyAsa-s_karNabheda_Part_1_o/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-09-14, 04:20:37 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/RmvyoAe-n8Y&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;88&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;ನಡುವೆ ನೀನೋಲಗದೊಳ್ &amp;ndash; ಒಪ್ಪುವ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ಕಡು ವಿಲಾಸವ ಬಿಸುಟು, ಕುರುಪತಿ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ನುಡಿಸೆ, &amp;ldquo;ಜೀಯ, ಹಸಾದ&amp;rdquo; ವೆಂಬುದು&amp;hellip; ಕಷ್ಟ ನಿನಗೆಂದ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;naḍuve nīnu ōlagadoḷ &amp;ndash; oppuva&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;kaḍu vilāsava bisuṭu, kurupati&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;nuḍise, &amp;ldquo;jīya, hasāda&amp;rdquo; eṃbudu&amp;hellip; kaṣṭa ninage enda&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“&amp;hellip;and you in the middle, holding court &amp;ndash; throwing away such great glory that befits you, if you choose to go bowing whenever Duryodhana calls, [mumbling] “Your mercy, Master”, … you will find it difficult.” We don’t know what glory the speaker is talking about, but with just the picture of the alternative alone we’re convinced we don’t want to make the wrong choice!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-10-02__89 - Kumāravyāsa&#39;s Karṇabheda Part 2 of 2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-10-02__89_-_kumAravyAsa-s_karNabheda_Part_2_o/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-10-02__89_-_kumAravyAsa-s_karNabheda_Part_2_o/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-10-02, 08:00:38 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/RTfwzkDK4Gw&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;89&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ಹಲವು ಮಾತೇನಖಿಳ ಜನಕೆ-&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;-ನ್ನುಳಿವು ಸೊಗಸದು. ಕೌರವೇಶ್ವರ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ನೊಲುಮೆ ತಪ್ಪಿಸಿ ಭುವನದೊಳಗೆನಗಾಪ್ತ ಜನವಿಲ್ಲ .&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;halavu mātu ēnu akhiḷa janake&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;enna uḷivu sogasadu. kauravēśvarana&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;olume tappisi bhuvanada oḷage enage āpta jana illa .&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“What more is there to say? My living doesn’t please anyone. Except for Duryodhana’s friendship, there is nothing in his world that I can call mine.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We continue from the last chapter on the Kannada epic Kumāravyāsa-bhārata (formally the Karṇāṭa-bhārata-kathāmañjarī). Krishna has just told Karṇa the secret of his birth. Karṇa is reeling from the shock: his mortal enemies have been revealed to be his brothers, and his visceral, almost existential drive to kill them for Duryodhana’s sake has suddenly been thwarted. His first thoughts on hearing the revelation were for Duryodhana’s welfare, not his own. He continues, lost in his own thoughts as Krishna looks on:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-10-29__Romanthaḥ - 23</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-10-29__romanthaH_-_23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-10-29__romanthaH_-_23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-10-29, 03:16:19 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/nlre4JaSqKI&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादरोमन्थः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear readers,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The last few chapters elicited a wide variety of responses. Thank you for your continued support!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In chapter 78 and the following Romantha 21, we had discussed many examples of how the mind seems to get attached to small things, almost as a rule. Gestures, mental images, tiny things that caught one’s eye &amp;ndash; all seem to have an outsized influence on our actions and behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-11-12__90 - Sītā&#39;s concern</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-11-12__90_-_sItA-s_concern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-11-12__90_-_sItA-s_concern/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-11-12, 05:13:55 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/7j77XbGbfLQ&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;90&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;स्मारये त्वां न शिक्षये&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(smāraye tvām na śikṣaye)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I’m only reminding you, not teaching you”. This phrase has been borrowed verbatim into many regional languages as well, and used to be a staple of refined speech when offering a dissenting opinion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This phrase is from the of the Araṇya kāṇḍa of the Vālmīkī Rāmāyaṇa. Rāma, together with Sītā and Lakṣmaṇa, is at the periphery of the Daṇḍaka forest, visiting many of the ṛṣis who have set up their hermitages there. Rāma and Lakṣmaṇa have just slain the rākṣasa Virādha, and the hermits dwelling nearby all come to thank and bless them for this feat. In their dialogue, they request that Rāma protect them from the many hordes of rākṣasas that rove the Daṇḍaka forest. To this request, Rāma replies with characteristic humility:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2016-11-21__91 - Divan-e-Ghalib</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-11-21__91_-_Divan-e-Ghalib/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2016-11-21__91_-_Divan-e-Ghalib/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2016-11-21, 05:28:39 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/TBvGbv1J2bM&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;91&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;दर्द् मिन्नत्-कश्-ए दवा न हुआ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(dard minnatkaś-e davā na huā)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;meaning&#34;&gt;Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“My pain did not fall under the debt of any medicine” अयि भो! &amp;ldquo;वैद्यकं मम निष्फलमभूत्&amp;rdquo; इति सरलभावं ऋण-परिभाषे कोऽयं कवयति? अपि च, &amp;ldquo;मिन्नत्-कश्-ए-दवा&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;औषध-ऋणी&amp;rdquo;) इति विलक्षण-मधुर-प्रयोगः कस्य वा हस्तलाघवम् ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पादोऽयं मिर्जा असदुल्ला बेग् खान् महोदयस्य &amp;ldquo;दीवान्-ए-ग़ालिब्&amp;rdquo; नाम सुविख्यात-संग्रहाद् उद्धृतः । मुघल-साम्राज्यावसान-काले जातोऽयं कविः उर्दू-भाषा-कविकुले प्रायः प्रथमस्थानम् अलङ्करोति &amp;ldquo;ग़ालिब्&amp;rdquo; इति नामाङ्कितेन । तस्य कालः अस्मद्-राष्ट्रस्यैव महान् संधिकाल इव भासते । यथा यथा मुघल-राज्यलक्ष्मीः नवीन-भर्तारम् अन्विषन्तीव पश्चिमं प्रति याता, तथा तथा मिर्जा-महोदयस्य जगत् सर्वं पश्चिमावधिमिव प्राप्तम् । मुघल-काव्य-संप्रदायः, उर्दू-फार्सी-भाषा-विलास-वैभवम्, दिल्ली-नगर्याः तद्-वीथीनां च अतिलोकरमणीयं वर्चः, सुकुमार-मनोहर-समयाश्च सर्वे मिर्जा-महोदयस्य समान-व्यसनिनः इव तेनैव सह स्मृतिपथं ययुः ।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2017-01-09__92 - H. R. Bacchan&#39;s Madhuśālā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2017-01-09__92_-_H._R._Bacchans_madhushAlA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/AsvAdaH/sadAsvAdaH/2017-01-09__92_-_H._R._Bacchans_madhushAlA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Mohan K.V&#x9;2017-01-09, 09:58:22 &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/g/sadaswada/c/YsOWJpGmJ84&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सदास्वादः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;92&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;राह पकड़ तू एक चला चल, पा जाएगा मधुशाला&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(rāh pakad tū ek calā cal, pā jāegā madhuśālā)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;“Pick a path and get going, you’ll find the tavern”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To catch the rhythm, we can ignore the Hindi pronunciation for a moment, and assume that all consonants are full (i.e. ignore ‘schwa syncope’). A clear 8-8-8-6 mātra pattern emerges:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;राह पकड़ तू / एक चला चल, / पा जाएगा / मधुशाला&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
