<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;00 Meta on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/00/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;00 Meta on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/00/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>00 INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/00/00_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/00/00_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One Vishnusharman, shrewdly gleaning&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All worldly wisdom’s inner meaning,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In these five books the charm compresses&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of all such books the world possesses&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And this is how it happened.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the southern country is a city called Maidens’ Delight. There lived a king named Immortal-Power. He was familiar with all the works treating of the wise conduct of life. His feet were made dazzling by the tangle of rays of light from jewels in the diadems of mighty kings who knelt before him. He had reached the far shore of all the arts that embellish life. This King had three sons. Their names were Rich-Power, Fierce-Power, Endless-Power, and they were supreme blockheads.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pub note</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/00/Pub_note/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/00/Pub_note/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since the dawn of civilisation, ever since man first realised the imperative need to know himself and, through that self-knowledge, to win friends and influence people so to secure his own happiness and well-being no less than those of his fellowmen, the Panchatantra stories have unfailingly offered him significant and dynamic aid.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In terms of historical time, these stories have been current among the Indian populace for at least five thousand years, probably longer. Nor has their popularity been limited exclusively to the confines of the Indian subcontinent, where the stories first found their origin. They have been told and retold, with perhaps a twist here and a turn there, among other peoples in other lands; in other climes and in other tongues — in short, among all peoples of the world through more than twenty centuries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TRANSLATOR’S INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/00/TRANSLATORS_INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/00/TRANSLATORS_INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One Vishnusharman, shrewdly gleaning&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;All worldly wisdom’s inner meaning,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In these five books the charm compresses&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of all such books the world possesses.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;*&amp;mdash;*INTRODUCTION TO THE &lt;em&gt;Panchatantra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Panchatantra&lt;/em&gt; contains the most widely known stories in the world. If it were further declared that the &lt;em&gt;Panchatantra&lt;/em&gt; is the best collection of stories in the world, the assertion could hardly be disproved, and would probably command the assent of those possessing the knowledge for a judgement. Assuming varied forms in their native India, then traveling in translations, and translations of translations, through Persia, Arabia, Syria, and the civilized countries, brought delight to hundreds of millions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
