<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Part 1 - The Present Work</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-general-history-of-the-study&#34;&gt;1. General History of the Study&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since the West came to know of the Sanskrit literature through William Jones’s translation of the Śakuntalā&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the nature and origin of the ancient Indian theatre have always interested scholars, especially the Sanskritists, all over the world. H. H. Wilson who published in 1826 the first volume of his famous work on the subject&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; deplored that the Nātyaśāstra, mentioned and quoted in several commentaries and other works, had been lost for ever&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. F. Hall who published in 1865 his edition of the Daśarūpa&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, a medieval work on the Hindu dramaturgy, did not see any Ms. of the Nāṭyaśāstra till his work had greatly advanced&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. And for the time being he printed the relevant chapters of the Nāṭyaśāstra as an appendix to his Daśarūpa. Later on he undertook to critically edit the Ms. of the Nāṭyaśāstra he acquired; but this venture was subsequently given up, due perhaps to an insufficiency of materials which consisted of one unique Ms. full of numerous &lt;em&gt;lacunae&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But even if the work could not be brought out by Hall, his very important discovery soon helped others to trace similar Mss. elsewhere. And in 1874 Heymann, a German scholar, published on the basis of Mss. discovered up till that date a valuable article&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on the contents of the Nāṭyaśāstra. This seems to have been instrumental in attracting competent scholars to the study of this very important text. The French Sanskritist P. Regnaud published in 1880 chapter XVII&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and in 1884 chapter XV (in part) and the chapter XVI&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of the Nāṭyaśāstra. This was soon followed by his publication of chapters VI and VII in 1884.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; And J. Grosset another French scholar and a pupil of Regnaud, published later on (in 1888) chapter XXVIII&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of the Nāṭyaśāstra which treated of the general theory of Hindu music.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Part 2 - The Ancient Indian Theory of Drama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-the-meaning-of-nāṭya&#34;&gt;1. The Meaning of Nāṭya&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word “Nāṭya” has often been translated as ‘drama’ and the plays of ancient India have indeed some points of similarity with those of the Greeks. But on a closer examination of the technique of their production as described in the Nāṭyaśāstra, the Hindu dramas represented by the available specimens, will appear to be considerably different. Unless this important fact is borne in mind any discussion on the subject is liable to create a wrong impression. As early as 1890 Sylvain Lévi (pp. 423-424) noticed that Indian Nāṭya differed from the Greek drama from which the Westerners derived their early conception of the art. Though it is not possible to agree with Lévi on all points about the various aspects of this difference and the causes which he attributed to them, no one can possibly have any serious objection against his finding that, “Le &lt;em&gt;nāṭaka&lt;/em&gt; par se nature autant que par son nom se rapproache de la dance scenique; le &lt;em&gt;drame&lt;/em&gt; est l’action même” (&lt;em&gt;loc, cit&lt;/em&gt;), Lévi however did not for reasons stated above fully utilize in this connection the Nāṭyaśāstra which contains ample materials for clarifying his conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Part 3 - Literary Structure of the Drama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-ten-types-of-play&#34;&gt;1. Ten Types of Play&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Nāṭaka&lt;/em&gt;. To understand the literary structure of the Hindu drama, it will be convenient to take up first of all the Nāṭaka which is the most important of the ten kinds of play described in the Nāṭyaśāstra&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-subject-matter-and-division-into-acts&#34;&gt;(a) Subject-matter and division into Acts.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Nāṭaka is a play having for its subject-matter a well-known story and for its Hero a celebrated person of exalted nature. It describes the character of a person descending from a royal seer, the divine protection for him, and his many superhuman powers and exploits, such as success in different undertakings and amorous pastimes; and this play should have an appropriate number of Acts (XX.10-12).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Part 4 - The Ancient Indian Drama in Practice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-occasions-for-dramatic-performance&#34;&gt;1. Occasions for Dramatic Performance&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Hindu drama like similar other forms of ancient art and poetry seems to have been of religious origin, and it developed probably out of dances and songs in honour of a deity like Siva who in later times came to be styled the great dancer-actor (&lt;em&gt;naṭarāja&lt;/em&gt;). As time passed, the dance with songs gradually assumed the form of regular dramatic spectacles, and the range of subjects treated was extended beyond the legends connected with the exploits of a particular deity. It is just possible that this development of the religious aspect came in course of time to be partially arrested, and plays began to be composed more with a purely secular character. And this change considerably loosened its original connexion with the popular deities. Possibly due to this the Hindu drama in the historic period of its career, is found to be acted sometimes for moral edification as in the case of the Buddhist plays, sometimes for the aesthetic enjoyment of the elite as in the case of Kālidāsa’s works, and sometimes (in?) hononr of a deity as in case of one of Bhavabhūti’s plays. In spite of (?) various uses, the Hindu drama unlike its modern counterparts did possibly never become an ordinary amusement of everyday life. It was??stly on special occasions like a religious festival, a marriage ceremony,??ing’s coronation, a friend’s visit that dramatic performances were held??.269; AD. 12-14). But among all these occasions religious festivals were the most common for the performance of drama. It was natural that on such occasions the drama was a popular entertainment as well, the public being then in a holiday mood.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Part 5 - Literature on the Ancient Indian Drama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-the-early-writers&#34;&gt;1. The Early Writers&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śilālin&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Kṛśāśva&lt;/em&gt;. Pāṇini (circa 500 B.C.) refers (IV.3.110-111) to the Naṭasūtras of Śilālin and Kṛśāśva. As the works of these two authors have perished beyond recovery we are not in a position to have any exact idea about their contents. But Lévi and Hillebrandt have taken them to be manuals for actors (&lt;em&gt;naṭa&lt;/em&gt;) though Weber and Konow have considered these to have been sets of rules for dancers and pantomimists, and Keith has accepted their view. Konow further thinks that the treatises of Śilālin and Kṛśāśva were absorbed in the body of the Nāṭyaśāstra (ID. p. 1)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Part 6 - The Nāṭyaśāstra: The Text and its Commentators</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-its-author&#34;&gt;1. Its Author&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Nāṭyaśāstra is commonly attributed to Bharata Muni.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But Bharata cannot be taken as its author, for in the Nāṭyaśāstra itself his mythical character is very obvious, and the majority of the Purāṇas are silent about the so called author of the Nāṭyaśāstra&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and there is not a single legend about him in any of the extant Purāṇas or the Rāmāyaṇa and the Mahābhārata. The word &lt;em&gt;Bharata&lt;/em&gt; which originally meant ‘an actor’ seems to have given rise to an eponymous author of the &lt;em&gt;Bharataśāstra&lt;/em&gt; or the &lt;em&gt;Naṭaśāstra&lt;/em&gt; (the manual of actors).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Part 7 - Data of India’s Cultural History in the Nāṭyaśāstra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Besides giving all sorts of information relating to the dramaturgy and histrionics as well as the allied arts of dance and music, the Nāṭyaśāstra includes considerable other materials for the cultural history of India. The most important among these will be discussed below under their several heads.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-language&#34;&gt;1. Language&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Nāṭyaśāstra gives some description of Pkt. (XVIII. 1-25) and examples of Dhruvā songs in Pkt. (XXXII). From these materials it seems that the Pkt. of the Nāṭyaśāstra lie mid-way between the Pkt. of the classical dramas and that of Aśvaghoṣa’s plays. Besides this there occur in this work (XVIII. 44, 48) some references about the nature of languages used by the ancient tribes like the Barbaras, Kirātas, Andhras, Dramiḍas, Śabaras and Caṇḍālas. There are besides other interesting matters relating to the language used by men of different professions and status in life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Part 8 - The Date of the Nāṭyaśāstra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/kalAvisheShaH/nATyam/nATya-shAstram/manamohanAnuvAdaH/00/intro/1/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More than sixteen years ago, a careful investigation of the linguistic, metrical, geographical and ethnographic data, of the evidence to be drawn from the history of poetics and music, of the Kāmaśāstra and the Arthaśāstra, and from inscriptions the present writer came to the conclusion that the available text of the Nāṭyaśāstra existed in the second century after Christ, while the tradition which it recorded may go back to a period as early as 100B.C. (The Date of Bharata-Nāṭyaśāstra, in the JDL. Vol. XXV. 1934).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Since this conclusion was made, a more intensive study of the text as well as accession of fresh data has confirmed the writer’s belief in its soundness. These additional materials are being discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
