<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;भामहाचार्यः on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/prastutiH/alankAraH/bhAmahAchAryaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;भामहाचार्यः on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/prastutiH/alankAraH/bhAmahAchAryaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>काव्यालङ्कारः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/prastutiH/alankAraH/bhAmahAchAryaH/kAvyAlankAraH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/prastutiH/alankAraH/bhAmahAchAryaH/kAvyAlankAraH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[काव्यालङ्कारः&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=NDcwMjM1ODc1OTA4Mjc1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तन्त्रोद्यानपुष्पहारे शास्त्रसरे - ।३।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOREWORD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;BY&lt;br&gt;&#xA;M. KRISHNAMACHARIAR, M.A., M.L., Ph. D., M. R. A. S.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Poetics, or Alankarasastra, means the Science ofpoetry. It embraces in its sphere, theory of poetry, the origin, form and variety of poet&amp;rsquo;s work, its faults andmerits, and a description of several embellishments whichdistinguish poetic from unpoetic compositions. In itswidest sense it covers the field of music, dancing and erotics. The earliest literature of the Hindus is poetic andis the natural effusion of man&amp;rsquo;s instinct. But poetics asa science must be of later origin, for without a volume ofpoetry (&lt;em&gt;lakshya&lt;/em&gt;) there cannot be a science (&lt;em&gt;lakshana&lt;/em&gt;) dealing with the regulation of its composition. Tradition saysthat Goddess of Learning, Sarasvati, created Kavya-purusha as the Personification of Poetry, and the Creatorsent him down to the human world for the propogation ofpoetics. In 18 chapters, he taught the subject to hisseventeen pupils. The several topics were embodied bythese desciples in separate treatises, Kavirahasya bySahasraksha, Auktika by Uktigarbha, Ritinirnaya bySuvarnanabha, Anuprasa by Pracetayana, Yamaka andCitra by Citrangada, Sabdaslesha by Sesha, Vastava byPulastya, Upama by Aupakayana, Atisaya by Parasara,Arthaslesha by Utithya, Ubhayalankarika by Kubera,Vainodika by Kamadeva, Rupaka by Bharata, Rasadhikara by Nandikesvara, Dosha by Dhishana, Guna byUpamanyu and Aupanishadika by Kucimara. These references are given by Rajasekhara in Kavyamimamsa(I. 1). It has been thought fashionable to treat theseaccounts as fictitious, but when we see that much of theearliest literature has been lost and replaced by later compendia, which, on account of the ease of study, have tendedto throw the older treatises into oblivion, it is possible thatthese traditional accounts are not after all a fraud. Opinions of many of these early writers are noticed in later&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>भामहः काव्यालङ्कारः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/prastutiH/alankAraH/bhAmahAchAryaH/bhAmahaH_kavyAlankAraH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxaNam/prastutiH/alankAraH/bhAmahAchAryaH/bhAmahaH_kavyAlankAraH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;विस्तारः (द्रष्टुं नोद्यम्)&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhamaha: Kavyalamkara&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhamaha: Kavyalamkara&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Based on: Kāvyālaṅkāra of Bhāmaha, Paricchedas 1 to 6 With English Translation&lt;br&gt;&#xA;and Notes on Paricchedas 1 to 3 by C. Sankara Rama Sastri.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Madras, Mylapore : Sri Balamanorama Press, 1956.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(Sri Balamanorama Series, 54)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Input by Dominic Goodall (EFEO)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;(The text is not proofread!)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PLAIN TEXT VERSION&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[Notes by D. Goodall:]&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Some corrections from Raniero GNOLI&amp;rsquo;s&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Udbhaṭa&amp;rsquo;s Commentary on the Kāvyālaṃkāra of Bhāmaha with an Appendix by Margherita Taticchi including some fragments of Kālidāsa&amp;rsquo;s Raghuvaṃśa.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Literary and Historical Documents from Pakistan II. Rome: Istituto Italiano per il Medio ed Estremo Oriente, 1962.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
