<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 LOSS OF GAINS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 LOSS OF GAINS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE MONKEY AND THE CROCODILE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/01_THE_MONKEY_AND_THE_CROCODILE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/01_THE_MONKEY_AND_THE_CROCODILE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On the shore of the sea was a great rose-apple tree that was never without fruit. In it lived a monkey named Red-Face.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now one day a crocodile named Ugly-Mug crawled out of the ocean under the tree and burrowed in the soft sand. Then Red-Face said: “You are my guest, sir. Pray eat these rose-apples which I throw you. You will find them like nectar. You know the proverb:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 HANDSOME AND THEODORE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/02_HANDSOME_AND_THEODORE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/02_HANDSOME_AND_THEODORE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a frog-king in a well, and his name was Theodore. One day when tormented by his relatives, he climbed from bucket to bucket up the water-wheel, and finally emerged. Then he thought: “How can I pay those relatives back? For the proverb says:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While one brings comfort in distress,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Another jeers at pain;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By paying both as they deserve,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A man is born again.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, he saw a black snake named Handsome crawling out of his hole. And on seeing him, he thought once more: “I will invite that black snake into the well, and clean out all my relatives. For the saying goes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 FLOP-EAR AND DUSTY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/03_FLOP-EAR_AND_DUSTY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/03_FLOP-EAR_AND_DUSTY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a lion named Fierce-Mane, who lived in a part of a forest. And for servant he had a jackal, a faithful drudge named Dusty.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now one day the lion fought with an elephant, and took such cruel wounds on his body that he could not stir a foot. And since the master could not sir, Dusty grew feeble, for his throat was pinched by hunger. Then he said to the lion: “O King, I am tortured with hunger until I cannot drag one foot after another. So how can I serve you?” “My good Dusty,” said the lion, “hunt out some animal that I can kill even in my present state.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 THE POTTER MILITANT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/04_THE_POTTER_MILITANT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/04_THE_POTTER_MILITANT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a potter in a certain place. One day he carelessly ran with all his might into the jagged edge of a broken pot, and tumbled. And though the jagged edge tore his forehead, he struggled to his feet, blood streaming over his body. Now as the wound was unskilfully treated, the scar cicatrized horribly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After some time, the land was afflicted with famine, and he felt the pinch of hunger. So he joined certain life-guards, went to another country, and became a life-guard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 THE JACKAL WHO KILLED NO ELEPHANTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/05_THE_JACKAL_WHO_KILLED_NO_ELEPHANTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/05_THE_JACKAL_WHO_KILLED_NO_ELEPHANTS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a part of a forest lived a lion and his wife. One day the lioness gave birth to twins. And the lion killed deer and things every day, and gave them to the lioness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But one day as he ranged the forest, he had met nothing when the blessed sun sank to his setting. As he trotted home, he found a baby jackal on the trail. And he pitied it because it was a baby. So he held it between his teeth and carefully carried it home, giving it to the lioness alive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 THE UNGRATEFUL WIFE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/06_THE_UNGRATEFUL_WIFE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/06_THE_UNGRATEFUL_WIFE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a Brahman in a certain city who loved his wife more than his life. But she squabbled with his family every day, and never rested. Since he could not endure the squabbling, yet was devoted to his wife, he left his family and started for another country far away.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the middle of a great forest, the Brahman’s wife said: “My dear, I am tortured by thirst. Please look about for water.” And he did as she requested, but when he returned with water, he found her dead.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 KING JOY AND SECRETARY SPLENDOR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/07_KING_JOY_AND_SECRETARY_SPLENDOR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/07_KING_JOY_AND_SECRETARY_SPLENDOR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a king named Joy, lord of the sea-girdled earth, whose power and manliness were famed afar, whose footstool was reticulated with interlacing beams of light from the diadems of uncounted hosts of kneeling princes, whose glory was unspotted as the autumn moonbeams. He had a secretary named Splendor, who had absorbed the total truth of all the scientific text-books, but whose wife pouted in a lovers’ quarrel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 THE ASS IN THE TIGER-SKIN</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/08_THE_ASS_IN_THE_TIGER-SKIN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/08_THE_ASS_IN_THE_TIGER-SKIN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a laundryman named Clean-Cloth in a certain town. He had a single donkey who had grown very feeble from lack of fodder.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the laundryman wandered in the forest, he saw a dead tiger, and he thought: “Ah, this is lucky. I will put this tiger-skin on the donkey and let him loose in the barley fields at night. For the farmers will think him a tiger and will not drive him out.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 THE FARMER’S WIFE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/09_THE_FARMERS_WIFE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/09_THE_FARMERS_WIFE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a farmer who lived with his wife in a certain place. And because the husband was old, the wife was forever thinking of lovers, and could not possibly be contented at home. Her one idea was strange men.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now a rogue who lived by pilfering, noticed her and said. “You lovely creature, my wife is dead, and I am smitten with love at the sight of you. Pray enrich me with love’s perfect treasure.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 THE PERT HEN-SPARROW</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/10_THE_PERT_HEN-SPARROW/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/10_THE_PERT_HEN-SPARROW/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain wood lived a sparrow and his wife who had built their nest on the branch of a tree. One day in the month of February a monkey took shelter under the tree; for he had been caught in an unseasonable hail-storm, and his body shivered to the slightest breeze. Since his teeth were making music and his face was woebegone and his hands and feet were tightly clenched, the hen-sparrow said to him compassionately:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 HOW SUPERSMART ATE THE ELEPHANT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/11_HOW_SUPERSMART_ATE_THE_ELEPHANT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/11_HOW_SUPERSMART_ATE_THE_ELEPHANT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a jackal named Supersmart in a part of a forest. One day he came upon an elephant that had died a natural death in the wood. But he could only stalk about the body; he could not cut through the tough hide.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At this moment a lion, in his wanderings to and fro, came to the spot. And the jackal, spying him, obsequiously rubbed his scalp in the dust, clasped his lotus paws, and said: “My lord and king. I am merely a cudgel-bearer, guarding this elephant in the king’s interest. May the king deign to eat it.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 THE DOG WHO WENT ABROAD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/12_THE_DOG_WHO_WENT_ABROAD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/04_LOSS_OF_GAINS/12_THE_DOG_WHO_WENT_ABROAD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a dog named Spot in a certain town, which was afflicted by a long famine. And as food gave out, dogs and others began to lose their homes. In fear of this, Spot felt his throat pinched by hunger, and he went to another country far away.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a city of that country he found a citizen’s wife who was slipshod in her housekeeping, so he entered her house every day, and ate his fill from a diversified bill of fare. But as he left the house, other dogs, drunk with aristocratic spleen, closed in from all sides, and tore him in every limb with their fangs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
