<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 WINNING OF FRIENDS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 WINNING OF FRIENDS on काव्ये विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE BHARUNDA BIRDS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/01_THE_BHARUNDA_BIRDS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/01_THE_BHARUNDA_BIRDS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By a certain lake in the world lived birds called “bharunda birds.” They had one belly and two necks apiece.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While one of these birds was sauntering about, his first neck found some nectar. Then the second said: “Give me half.” And when the first refused, the second neck angrily picked up poison somewhere and ate it. As they had one belly, they died.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“And that is why I say:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 GOLD’S GLOOM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/02_GOLDS_GLOOM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/02_GOLDS_GLOOM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the southern country is a city called Maidens’ Delight, and in the neighborhood a shrine to Shiva. In a cell near by lived a hermit named Crop-Ear. During his begging hour he would fill his alms-bowl with dainties from the city, eatables jellified, melting in the mouth, toothsome, flavored with sugar, treacle, and pomegranate. Then, returning to his cell, he satisfied himself according to the ordinance, hid what food was left in the alms-bowl, and hung it on a peg, keeping it for the servants’ breakfast. On this food I subsisted with my companions. And so the time passed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 MOTHER SHANDILEE’S BARGAIN</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/03_MOTHER_SHANDILEES_BARGAIN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/03_MOTHER_SHANDILEES_BARGAIN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At one time I asked a certain Brahman in a certain town for shelter during the rainy season, and this he gave me. So there I lived, occupied with pious duties.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day I woke betimes, and listening to a conversation between my host and his wife, I heard the Brahman say: “My dear, tomorrow will be the winter solstice, an extremely profitable season. So I will go to another village in search of donations. And you, in honor of the sun, should give some Brahman food to the extent of your ability.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 SELF-DEFEATING FORETHOUGHT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/04_SELF-DEFEATING_FORETHOUGHT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/04_SELF-DEFEATING_FORETHOUGHT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a hillman in a certain place who set out to increase his sins by hunting. As he walked along, he met a boar that resembled the top of Sooty Mountain. Straightway he drew an arrow as far as his ear, and recited this verse:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fitted shaft and bow-string’s tension&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He sees, and shows no apprehension;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The psychological conclusion&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Is: Death has prompted this intrusion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then with a sharp arrow he shot the boar, who in turn angrily tore the hillman’s stomach with a pointed fang that shone like the crescent moon, so that the man fell dead. The boar also, after killing the hunter, died in torment from the arrow-wound.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 MISTER DULY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/05_MISTER_DULY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/05_MISTER_DULY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain city lived a merchant named Ocean. His son picked up a book at a sale for a hundred rupees. In this book was the line:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What’s duly his, a man receives.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now Ocean saw it and asked his son: “My boy, what did you give for this book?” “A hundred rupees,” said the son. “Simpleton!” said Ocean, “if you pay a hundred rupees for a book with one line of poetry written in it, how do you calculate to make money? From this day you are not at home in my house.” After this wigging, he showed him the door.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 SOFT, THE WEAVER</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/06_SOFT_THE_WEAVER/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/06_SOFT_THE_WEAVER/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town lived a weaver. His name was Soft, and he spent his time making garments dyed in various patterns, fit for such people as princes. But for all his labors, he could not collect a bit of money beyond food and clothes. Yet he saw other weavers, who made coarse fabrics, rolling in wealth, and he said to his wife: “Look at these fellows, my dear. They make coarse stuff, but they earn heaps of money. This city does not offer me a decent living. I am going to move.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 HANG-BALL AND GREEDY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/07_HANG-BALL_AND_GREEDY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/07_HANG-BALL_AND_GREEDY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a certain town lived a bull named Hang-Ball. From excess of male vigor he abandoned the herd, tore the river-banks with his horns, browsed at will on emerald-tipped grasses, and went wild in the forest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In that forest lived a jackal named Greedy. One day he sprawled at ease with his wife on a sandy river-bank. At that moment the bull Hang-Ball came down to the same stretch of sand for a drink. And the she-jackal said to her husband when she saw the hanging testicles: “Look, my dear! See how two lumps of flesh hang from that bull. They will fall in a moment, or a few hours at most. So you must follow him, please.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 THE MICE THAT SET ELEPHANTS FREE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/08_THE_MICE_THAT_SET_ELEPHANTS_FREE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/08_THE_MICE_THAT_SET_ELEPHANTS_FREE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was once a region where people, houses, and temples had fallen into decay. So the mice, who were old settlers there, occupied the chinks in the floors of stately dwellings with sons, grandsons (both in the male and female line), and further descendants as they were born, until their holes formed a dense tangle. They found uncommon happiness in a variety of festivals, dramatic performances (with plots of their own invention), wedding-feasts, eating-parties, drinking-bouts, and similar diversions. And so the time passed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 SPOT’S CAPTIVITY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/09_SPOTS_CAPTIVITY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/kAvyam/laxyam/champUH/nItiH/pancha-tantram/en/ryder-arthur/02_WINNING_OF_FRIENDS/09_SPOTS_CAPTIVITY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Long ago, when I was six months old, I used to gambol in front of all the rest, as a youngster does. Out of sheer spirits I would run far ahead, then wait for the herd. Now we deer have two gaits, called the Jump-Up and the Straightaway. Of these I knew the Straightaway, but not the Jump-Up.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While amusing myself one day, I lost touch with the herd. At this I was dreadfully worried, gazed about the horizon to learn where they might be, and discovered them ahead. Now they had avoided a snare by means of the Jump-Up; they stood in a body ahead of me, and waited, all looking at me. But I, ignorant of the Jump-Up, was caught in the hunter’s snare.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
